<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>15</num>
  <heading>PARKING</heading>
  <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">1 <strong>Cross reference— </strong>Ordinances prescribing parking prohibitions, parking limitations or loading zones saved from repeal, <cite path="1-12|(5)">§ 1-12(5)</cite>; police, Ch. 18; vehicle parking in parks, <cite path="16-5">§ 16-5</cite>; streets and sidewalks, Ch. 22; transportation, Ch. 25; regulation of parking on parade routes, <cite path="25-10">§ 25-10</cite>; bicycle parking, <cite path="25-184">§ 25-184</cite>; off-street parking and loading, <cite path="27-283">§ 27-283</cite> et seq.</annotation>
  <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>State Law reference— </strong>Stopping, standing or parking prohibited in specified places, F.S. <cite path="316-1945">§ 316-1945</cite>; additional parking regulations, F.S. § 316.195.</annotation>
  <container>
    <prefix>ARTICLE</prefix>
    <num path-omit="true">I</num>
    <heading>ADMINISTRATIVE PROVISIONS</heading>
    <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">2 <strong>Cross reference— </strong>Administration, Ch. 2.</annotation>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">1</num>
      <heading>GENERAL PROVISIONS; ADMINISTRATIVE AUTHORITY; DEFINITIONS</heading>
      <section>
        <num>15-1</num>
        <heading>Title.</heading>
        <text><cite path="15">This chapter</cite> shall be known and may be cited as the "City of Tampa Parking Ordinance."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-1), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-2</num>
        <heading>Applicability.</heading>
        <text>The provisions of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> shall apply throughout the corporate limits of the city and to the use of parking-related property owned or operated by the city.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-2), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-3</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <text>For the purpose of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>, certain abbreviations, terms, phrases, words and their derivatives shall have the following meanings:</text>
        <text><em>Calendar days</em> mean and include Saturdays, Sundays, and legal holidays. Thus, in computing any period of time prescribed or allowed by <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>, the day of the act, event or default from which the designated period of time begins to run shall not be included; however, the last day of the period so computed shall be included, even if it is a Saturday, Sunday or legal holiday, any provision of this Code to the contrary notwithstanding. If any period of time under <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> is sought to be complied with by means of mailing, the date of actual receipt of the mail by the parking division, not the date of posting, shall be deemed the date of compliance.</text>
        <text><em>Coin</em> means any coin, authorized for currency by the United States Government, required to be inserted in parking meters by city resolution or ordinance.</text>
        <text><em>Delinquent status</em> means a ticket where payment is past due and includes tickets that have not been paid, or for which a request for a parking violation hearing has not been made. A ticket which has been found to be in violation after a hearing shall be in delinquent status if not paid within the time period set. A violation set for a parking violation hearing which results in default shall immediately be in delinquent status. A ticket will remain in delinquent status until paid in full, unless dismissed or found not to be a violation.</text>
        <text><em>Director</em> means the director, or his or her designee, of the department referred to as the City of Tampa Logistics and Asset Management Department but shall include any department which may subsequently assume such duties.</text>
        <text><em>Duly certified code enforcement officer</em> for purposes of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> means any designated employee or agent of the city whose duty it is to enforce codes and ordinances enacted by the city and has been trained and certified to issue parking tickets pursuant to Florida law.</text>
        <text><em>Habitual parking status</em> means any vehicle bearing a license plate that has been issued five (5) or more parking tickets for any violation of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> within the past three hundred sixty-five (365) calendar days.</text>
        <text><em>Hearing officer</em> means the code enforcement special magistrate assigned to hear parking violation hearings and challenges to parking ticket violations and immobilization of vehicles in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        <text><em>Non-motorized vehicle</em> means any vehicle which does not have an attached source of mechanical energy such as an engine in order to make it move, but has to be attached, drawn, pushed, or pulled in order for it to be moved. Non-motorized vehicles include, but are not limited to, travel trailers, watercraft, boats, and watercraft or boat trailers.</text>
        <text><em>Owner</em> means any person, firm, corporation, or association controlling any motor vehicle or mobile home by right of purchase, gift, lease, or otherwise as defined under F.S. § 320.01, as of the date of the violation. The owner of a vehicle bearing a license plate that has been issued a ticket shall be liable for payment of all penalties and costs.</text>
        <text><em>Park</em> or <em>parking</em> means the standing of a vehicle, whether occupied or not, otherwise than temporarily for the purpose of and while actually engaged in loading or unloading merchandise or passengers.</text>
        <text><em>Parking division</em> means the division referred to as the City of Tampa Logistics and Asset Management Parking Division, but shall include any division which may subsequently assume such duties.</text>
        <text><em>Parking enforcement specialist</em> means a person designated as a parking enforcement specialist who has successfully completed a training program established and approved by the Florida Criminal Justice Standards and Training Commission.</text>
        <text><em>Parking meter</em> means a mechanical or electronic timing device authorized by ordinance of this municipality to be used for the purpose of regulating or controlling parking and which is actuated by the payment of authorized legal tender by manual or electronic means.</text>
        <text><em>Parking violation hearing</em> means a hearing by a hearing officer in which a driver or owner of a vehicle bearing a license plate that has been issued a ticket, or an owner of a vehicle who was issued a notice of default status may contest the issuance of a parking ticket or notice of default status. Parking violation hearings shall provide the opportunity for testimony and evidence to be presented and the rules of evidence shall be liberally construed to allow for the presentation of testimony and evidence. Parking violation hearings shall also be used by a person with standing to challenge the immobilization of a vehicle in a post-immobilization hearing.</text>
        <text><em>Pay station</em> means a type of parking meter which is electronic and which parking time limits are designated on a receipt issued from the pay station.</text>
        <text><em>Residential guest parking permit</em> means an identification pass affixed to a vehicle issued, temporarily, to a resident located within the residential parking permit only area by the city in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="15-3">this section</cite>.</text>
        <text><em>Residential parking permit</em> shall mean an identification pass affixed to a vehicle issued to a resident or business located within the residential parking permit only area by the city in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="15-3">this section</cite>.</text>
        <text><em>Residential parking permit only areas</em> shall mean those areas where the residential parking permit system is in effect. Such areas are designated in <cite path="15-104|(b)">section 15-104(b)</cite>.</text>
        <text><em>Resident vehicle</em> shall mean a motor vehicle owned or leased by a person residing in the residential parking permit only area.</text>
        <text><em>Stand</em> or <em>standing</em> means the halting of a vehicle, whether occupied or not, otherwise than temporarily for the purpose of and while actually engaged in receiving or discharging passengers.</text>
        <text><em>Stop or stopping, when prohibited,</em> means any halting, even momentarily, of a vehicle, whether occupied or not, except when necessary to avoid conflict with other traffic or to comply with the direction of a law enforcement officer or traffic-control sign or signal.</text>
        <text><em>Ticket</em> means a citation issued for a violation of the Code as described in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        <text><em>Vehicle</em> means every device in, upon or by which any person or property is or may be transported or drawn upon any public street within the city, excepting devices moved by human power or used exclusively upon stationary rails or tracks.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-3), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 94-148, § 1, 8-4-94</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-244, § 1, 9-18-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-255, § 1, 10-19-06</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 1, 7-14-2011</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 2, 6-22-2017</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2020-39, § 1, 6-4-2020</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2020-96, § 2, 10-1-2020</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Cross reference— </strong>Definitions and rules of construction generally, <cite path="1-2">§ 1-2</cite>.</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-4</num>
        <heading>Administrative authority.</heading>
        <text>The provisions of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> shall be administered and enforced by the official. For the purpose of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>, the official's designee shall be the director.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-4), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Cross reference— </strong>Administrative authority of the official, <cite path="1-13">§ 1-13</cite>; delegation of administrative authority, <cite path="1-14">§ 1-14</cite>.</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-4.5</num>
        <heading>Authority to issue citations for parking tickets.</heading>
        <text>Parking enforcement specialists, and police officers are authorized to issue parking tickets for violations of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>. Duly certified code enforcement officers are authorized to issue parking tickets for violations of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>, except for violations within the central business district as defined in chapter 27.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2020-96, § 3, 10-1-2020</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-5</num>
        <heading>Installation of parking meters; duty of director to maintain; operation.</heading>
        <text>Parking meters shall be placed upon the curb in proximity to the individual parking spaces to be designated, and each of the parking meters, except pay stations, shall be set to show or display a signal indicating whether the space is or may be lawfully occupied. Each pay station shall produce a receipt indicating the lawful parking period. The director shall provide for the installation, control, operation and use of the parking meters provided for in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> and shall maintain such meters in good workable condition. Each parking meter, except pay stations, shall be so set as to display a signal showing legal parking upon the actuation by the payment of authorized legal tender by manual or electronic means therein for a period of time conforming to the parking limit as determined by the director for the individual parking space. Pay stations shall be so set as to produce a receipt upon the actuation of payment of authorized legal tender and shall indicate the lawful parking period. Each meter shall by its device clearly set out and continue in operation from the time of actuation by payment until the expiration of the time fixed by the director as to the parking limit for the individual parking space. Each meter, except pay stations, shall also be so arranged that upon the expiration of the parking limit it will indicate by a proper signal that the lawful parking period has expired. Each pay station will produce a receipt indicating the time of expiration of the lawful parking period. One (1) parking meter may be used for the purpose of regulating or controlling parking for one (1) or more parking spaces in one (1) or more parking zones.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-5), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 2, 7-14-2011</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-6</num>
        <heading>Parking meter zones.</heading>
        <text>Certain described parts of streets, city owned and/or operated off-street lots, garages or property and parks, beach and recreation areas or other property within the city limits may from time to time be designated by the director as parking meter zones. In such zones the director shall cause parking meters to be installed in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-6), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-7</num>
        <heading>Marking of parking spaces.</heading>
        <text>The director shall select and place lines or marks on the curb, property or on the street to designate a parking space for which a parking meter or space is to be used.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-7), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 3, 7-14-2011</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-8-15-25</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">2</num>
      <heading>FEE AUTHORITY AND TYPES</heading>
      <section>
        <num>15-26</num>
        <heading>Fees—City council to establish.</heading>
        <text>The city council shall have the authority to set fees by resolution.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-21), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-27</num>
        <heading>Same—Types enumerated.</heading>
        <text>Fees may be charged for the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Use of a city owned or operated parking meter zone or space or other parking facility or property;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Late payments of fees for monthly parking in a city owned or operated parking facility or property;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Special parking permits;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Business parking permits;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Residential parking permits;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Guest residential parking permits;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Replacement of special parking permits, business parking permits residential parking permits and guest residential parking permits;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>Adjustments to special parking permits, business parking permits, residential parking permits and guest residential parking permits and such as adjustments required by vehicle tag number changes;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text>Granted requests to reserve parking meter spaces or to remove parking meters or parking signs and reinstallation thereof;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text>Immobilization and impoundment of vehicles as provided for in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(11)</num>
          <text>Shuttle service to and from city owned or operated parking facility or property.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-22), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 90-217, § 1, 8-16-90</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-255, § 2, 10-19-06</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-28-15-40</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>ARTICLE</prefix>
    <num path-omit="true">II</num>
    <heading>REGULATIONS; PERMITS; PENALTIES</heading>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">1</num>
      <heading>GENERAL PARKING REGULATIONS</heading>
      <section>
        <num>15-41</num>
        <heading>Parking in city lots, garages, public streets and other property.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any vehicle stopped, standing or parked in a single parking space on any city owned or operated parking lot, garage, public street or other property shall be parked within the lines marked for such single parking space. It is unlawful to stop, stand or park any vehicle across any such line or mark or to park such vehicle in any such way that the same shall not be within the area so designated by such lines or markings for that single parking space.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for any person to remove a vehicle from any city owned or operated parking lot, garage, public street or other property after the person shall have parked thereon without first making payment of authorized legal tender by manual or electronic means or for any person to make any attempt thereof to defraud the city.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful to fraudulently alter, duplicate, damage, destroy, throw away or copy any control card, spitter ticket, permit, tag, decal or receipt used for parking control issued by the parking division or to make any attempt thereof to defraud the city.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful to deposit or cause to be deposited in any meter, pay station, other electronic device, mechanical equipment or change maker or coin receptacle on any city owned or operated parking lot, garage, public street, or other property any slug, device, metallic or other substitute for a coin of the United States of America or to make any attempt thereof to defraud the city.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful and an offense for any person to deface, injure, tamper with, open, willfully break, destroy or impair the usefulness of any equipment installed on any city owned or operated parking lot, garage, public street or other property or to make any attempt thereof.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for the operator of a vehicle to stop, park or leave standing a vehicle on a city owned or operated parking lot, garage, public street or other property, using pay stations, other electronic devices, mechanical equipment, meters or gates for revenue control, for a period longer than twenty-four (24) hours without first making arrangements in advance with the parking division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>No vehicle shall enter into a parking garage which exceeds the height restriction posted on the clearance bar at the entrance of each garage.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for an operator of a vehicle to stop, stand or park such vehicle in a space not designated or designed for its size. Standard cars are considered to be vehicles Class 9 or larger, as defined in accordance with the current domestic and imported passenger car size classification.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful to stop, stand or park in city owned or operated parking lots, garages or other properties that are reserved for monthly parking without properly displaying appropriate documentation of payment for parking privileges for the current period (hangtag, decal, etc.).</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-35), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 97-20, §§ 1, 2, 1-23-97</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2009-71, § 2, 5-7-09</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 4, 7-14-2011</annotation>
          <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container"><strong>Editor's note— </strong>Ord. No. 2009-71, § 2, adopted May 7, 2009, changed the title of <cite path="15-41">§ 15-41</cite> from "Parking in city lots, garages and other property" to read as herein set out.</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-42</num>
        <heading>Parking within designated spaces.</heading>
        <text>Any vehicle stopped, standing or parked in or alongside a parking space as designated pursuant to <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> shall park within the lines or markings designating such parking space. It is unlawful to park any vehicle in any such way that the same shall not be within the area so designated by such lines, markings, or sign post that corresponds with the parking space. The front bumper of the vehicle must be even with the lines, markings, or sign post that corresponds with the parking space or in close proximity thereto without parking beyond the established post or sign.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-36), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 5, 7-14-2011</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2014-16, § 1, 3-6-2014</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-43</num>
        <heading>Parking in front of residences or public or private driveways.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All taxicabs, buses and motor vehicles for hire are prohibited from stopping, standing or parking at any time in front of any residence without permission from the owner or the occupant of such residence.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for any person to stop, stand or park a vehicle, whether occupied or not, within ten (10) feet from the edge of a public or private driveway except in metered spaces or otherwise marked spaces available for parking or to momentarily pick up or discharge a passenger.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for any person to stop, stand or park a vehicle across the street from a driveway if the street width is twenty-five (25) feet or less except in metered spaces or otherwise marked spaces available for parking or to momentarily pick up or discharge a passenger.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-37), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2001-149, § 1, 7-19-01</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-17, § 2, 1-12-06</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-33, § 1, 3-2-2017</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Cross reference— </strong>Standing or parking vehicle across from or within ten feet of driveway, <cite path="25-194">§ 25-194</cite>.</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-44</num>
        <heading>Ten feet of roadway to remain open for vehicular traffic.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful for any operator to stop, stand or park any vehicle upon a street, in a traffic lane, any alley or other city owned or operated property in such a manner or under such conditions as to leave available less than ten (10) feet of the width of the traffic lane or roadway for free movement of vehicular traffic, except that an operator may stop only during the actual loading or unloading of passengers or when necessary in obedience to traffic regulations or traffic signs or signals or a police officer.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-38), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-45</num>
        <heading>Vehicles other than taxicabs, buses, etc., parking in designated stands.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful for the operator of any vehicle other than a bus, taxicab or for-hire automobile to stop, stand or park in an officially designated bus, taxicab or for-hire automobile stand, except that the operator of any passenger vehicle may temporarily stop in any such stop or stand for the purpose of and while actually engaged in the loading or unloading of passengers.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-39), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-46</num>
        <heading>Trucks occupying more than one parking space.</heading>
        <text>No truck, tractor truck or trailer shall occupy more than one (1) parking space where designated, except while loading or unloading and while all meters used have been properly activated and/or when proper parking permits have been obtained and except in cases of emergency.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-40), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-47</num>
        <heading>Parking motor vehicles of eighty-six inches or more in width on certain streets prohibited.</heading>
        <text>No motor vehicle, as defined by Florida Statues as may be amended, of eighty-six (86) inches or more in overall width (not including mirrors) shall be parked on any street, alley, or city owned or operated property, other than for loading and unloading, if parked adjacent to property designated by Chapter 27 of <cite>this Code</cite> as a residential district. A written warning will be provided prior to the issuance of a ticket. After twelve (12) hours, if the motor vehicle is parked in any prohibited location, a ticket may be issued. Failure to move the motor vehicle in violation from streets, alleys, or city owned or operated property within two (2) hours after the issuance of a ticket shall subject the motor vehicle to immobilization and/or impoundment as provided under <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-41), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2020-39, § 2, 6-4-2020</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-48</num>
        <heading>Freight, loading and unloading spaces restricted.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Spaces designated "freight zone, freight trucks only" shall be restricted to freight trucks and other vehicles properly marked and identified and while actually engaged in the loading and unloading of materials or in cases of emergency.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No person shall stop, stand or park a vehicle for any purpose or length of time other than for the expeditious unloading and delivery or pickup and loading of materials in any place marked as a freight zone. During the hours when the provisions applicable to such zones are in effect, in no case shall the stop for loading and unloading exceed one (1) hour.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><cite path="15-48">This section</cite> is applicable only to commercial vehicles which must be identified by permanent or removable markings on both sides of the exterior of the vehicle, in letters not less than three (3) inches high, of the name of the company operating such vehicle.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Spaces designated "load and unload" are restricted to the maximum time indicated on the sign or timing mechanism device while any vehicle is actually engaged in loading and unloading. It is unlawful for any person to permit a vehicle to remain in any space for longer than the designated time. For any continuous parking in the same space, a violation will be deemed to have occurred for each interval of time designated that the vehicle remains in that space.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>For the purpose of <cite path="15-48">this section</cite>, a "timing mechanism device" is a parking device which does not accept coinage and displays a signal for the amount of parking time allotted. Such device is actuated by the turning of a handle.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-42), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-49</num>
        <heading>Parking vehicles on street for purposes of sale.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful for any person to park any vehicle displayed for sale upon any city owned or operated lot, garage or other property or street.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-43), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-50</num>
        <heading>Parking vehicles for primary purpose of vending, displaying or advertising goods, services or place of business.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful for any person to stop, stand or park on any street or city owned or operated parking lot, garage or other property, any vehicle for the purpose of vending, displaying or advertising goods, services or any place of business.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-44), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 92-160, § 1, 10-1-92</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-51</num>
        <heading>Parking on city right-of-way.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful to park in the right-of-way except in designated parking spaces or parking lanes. For the purposes of <cite path="15-51">this section</cite>, the term "right-of-way" shall have the definition provided in the city subdivision chapter.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-45), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-52</num>
        <heading>Parking vehicles with altered or expired license tags.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful for any vehicle to be stopped, standing or parked in any city owned or operated parking space, parking lot or other parking facility or property if such vehicle is not licensed in accordance with the laws of the state, if it displays a license tag that is expired or altered such that a person cannot reasonably discern the complete license tag number or if it does not display a valid license tag.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-46), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-53</num>
        <heading>Parking on housing authority properties.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for a person to stand or park a vehicle on either side of any public street in or abutting the following Tampa Housing Authority properties without a valid, properly displayed resident parking permit or three-day visitor parking permit issued for that particular property:</text>
          <text>
            <table>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td>Property</td>
                  <td>Address of Property</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Azeele Apartments</td>
                  <td>2801 Azeele Street <br/>Tampa, Florida 33609</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Mary Bethune Hi-Rise</td>
                  <td>1515 Union Street <br/>Tampa, Florida 33607</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Plantation Apartments</td>
                  <td>212 South Howard Street <br/>Tampa, Florida 33606</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>St. Louis/St. Conrad</td>
                  <td>2310 St. Louis Street <br/>Tampa, Florida 33607</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Azzarelli</td>
                  <td>5038 Temple Heights <br/>Tampa, Florida 33617</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Scruggs Manor</td>
                  <td>11202 North 22nd Street <br/>Tampa, Florida 33612</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Bay Ceia</td>
                  <td>3422 South MacDill <br/>3424 South MacDill <br/>3411 South Carter <br/>Tampa, Florida 33629</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Cutlass Arms</td>
                  <td>4728 South Trask <br/>Tampa, Florida 33611</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>C. Blythe Andrews</td>
                  <td>2201 East Osborne <br/>Tampa, Florida 33610</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Central Park Village</td>
                  <td>100 India Street <br/>Tampa, Florida 33602</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Giddens Apartments</td>
                  <td>4706 Muskogee Court <br/>Tampa, Florida 33610</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Seminole Park</td>
                  <td>4706 Muskogee Court <br/>Tampa, Florida 33610</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Moses White Estates</td>
                  <td>4706 Muskogee Court <br/>Tampa, Florida 33610</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>North Boulevard Homes</td>
                  <td>1529 West Main Street <br/>Tampa, Florida 33607</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Rembrandt Homes</td>
                  <td>4228 Monet Court <br/>Tampa, Florida 33616</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Riverview Terrace</td>
                  <td>202 East Broad Street <br/>Tampa, Florida 33604</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Tom Dyer Homes</td>
                  <td>7406 North Dixon Street <br/>Tampa, Florida 33604</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>College Hill Homes</td>
                  <td>2400 East Lake Avenue <br/>Tampa, Florida 33605</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>J.L. Young Apartments</td>
                  <td>8220 North Florida Avenue <br/>Tampa, Florida 33604</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Parkview Apartments</td>
                  <td>1314 West Sligh Avenue <br/>Tampa, Florida 33604</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Squire Villa</td>
                  <td>5817 North Rome Avenue <br/>Tampa, Florida 33604</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Ponce De Leon</td>
                  <td>1709 26th Avenue <br/>Tampa, Florida 33605</td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>Robles Park Village</td>
                  <td>3814 North Central Avenue <br/>Tampa, Florida 33603</td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </text>
        </para>
        <text>&amp;nbsp;</text>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Resident parking permits and three-day visitor parking permits shall be issued by the Tampa Housing Authority, form to be approved by the Tampa Police Department, and shall be valid only for parking in the Tampa Housing Authority property for which they were issued.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A resident parking permit must be conspicuously affixed to the inside upper left corner of the back window of the motor vehicle. A three-day visitor parking permit must be conspicuously displayed on the inside of the front window of the motor vehicle. A three-day visitor parking permit will be valid only for the vehicle for which it is issued.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 92-160, § 2, 10-1-92</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-54</num>
        <heading>Illegal use of license plates, exemption parking permits, or temporary exemption parking permits issued to persons with disabilities.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for any person to unlawfully use a license plate, an exemption parking permit, or a temporary exemption parking permit issued to persons with disabilities.</text>
          <text>As used herein, "unlawful use" of a license plate, exemption parking permit, or a temporary exemption parking permit issued to persons with disabilities means the use or display of such license plate, exemption parking permit, or temporary exemption parking permit by an operator or other person in charge of a motor vehicle other than by the person to whom it was duly issued; provided, that, a person who is chauffeuring a disabled person shall be allowed, without need for an identification parking permit or a special license plate, momentary parking in any "parking by disabled permit only" public or private parking spaces, for the purpose of loading or unloading such disabled person. No penalty shall be imposed upon the driver for such momentary parking.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>When investigating the possibility of a violation of <cite path="15-54">this section</cite>, a law enforcement officer, a duly certified code enforcement officer, or a parking enforcement specialist has the right to demand to be shown the vehicle registration, driver's license, or any state or other forms of identification of the operator or other person in charge of the motor vehicle or of the person eligible for such license plate, exemption permit, or temporary exemption parking permit. If such request is refused, the person refusing shall be issued a citation for a violation of this subsection. That person shall not be found guilty of violating this subsection if, prior to or at time of his court or hearing appearance, he produces in court or to the clerk of the court in which the charge is pending a vehicle registration, driver's license, or any state or other forms of identification which confirms that he is the same person to whom was issued the license plate, exemption parking permit, or temporary exemption parking permit used or displayed at the time of citation or that he is eligible for such license plate, exemption permit, or temporary exemption parking permit.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A law enforcement officer or a parking enforcement specialist has the right to confiscate a license plate, an exemption parking permit, or a temporary exemption parking permit issued to persons with disabilities when, based upon personal investigation, the officer or specialist has reasonable cause to believe that there is a violation of <cite path="15-54">this section</cite>. If the operator or other person in charge of the motor vehicle fails or refuses to surrender the license plate, exemption parking permit, or temporary exemption permit, that person shall be issued a citation for a violation of this subsection.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 95-225, § 1, 10-26-95</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2020-96, § 4, 10-1-2020</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-55</num>
        <heading>Continuous parking in non-metered parking spaces.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for any person to permit a vehicle to remain in any parking space in violation of sections 15-41, 15-42, 15-43, 15-44, 15-45, 15-46, 15-47, 15-48, 15-49, 15-50, 15-51, 15-52, and 15-53 of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for any person to permit a vehicle to remain in any parking space for more than (2) hours after a citation has been issued for violation of <cite path="15-55|(a)">subsection (a)</cite> of <cite path="15-55">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For any continuous parking in the same parking space, no more than one (1) offense under <cite path="15-55|(a)">subsection (a)</cite> of <cite path="15-55">this section</cite> and one (1) offense under <cite path="15-55|(b)">subsection (b)</cite> of <cite path="15-55">this section</cite> shall be deemed to have occurred on any one (1) date. In the case of any continuous parking in violation of <cite path="15-55|(a)">subsection (a)</cite> or <cite path="15-55|(b)">subsection (b)</cite> hereof covering parts of two (2) or more dates, one (1) offense under <cite path="15-55|(b)">subsection (b)</cite> shall be deemed to have occurred on each of such dates.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-244, § 2, 9-18-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-56</num>
        <heading>Charging station parking.</heading>
        <text>No person shall park any vehicle in any parking space located in any city owned or operated parking garage or parking lot which is clearly marked as being reserved for the use of an electric vehicle charging station located within said parking garage or lot, unless such vehicle is actually using the electric vehicle charging station.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 6, 7-14-2011</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-57-15-80</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">2</num>
      <heading>PARKING METER REGULATIONS</heading>
      <section>
        <num>15-81</num>
        <heading>Hours of operation for parking meters.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful to park in a parking meter zone without complying with the provisions of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> during the hours of operation for use of metered parking in said parking meter zone. The hours of operation for use of metered parking in parking meter zones shall be as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>7:00 a.m. to 6:00 p.m., Monday through Sunday, for all metered parking located in beach, park and recreation areas;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>8:00 a.m. to midnight, Monday through Sunday, for all metered parking located in the area bound by the Garrison Channel to the south, by and including Whiting Street to the north, by and including Ashley Street to the west, and by and including Meridian Avenue to the east;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>8:00 a.m. to 8:00 p.m., Monday through Saturday, and 1:00 p.m. to 8:00 p.m. Sunday, for all metered parking located in the area bound by and excluding Whiting Street to the south, by and including Kennedy Boulevard to the north, by and including Ashley Street to the west, and by and including Nebraska Avenue to the east;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Monday through Saturday, from 8:00 a.m. to 3:00 a.m. of the following day, for all metered parking located in Ybor City in the area bound, for purposes of this subsection, by and excluding Palm Avenue on the north, by and excluding 21st Street on the east, by and excluding 6th Avenue on the south, and by and excluding 12th Street on the West;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>8:00 a.m. to 6:00 p.m., Monday through Friday, for all other metered parking in the city;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>8:00 a.m. to 8:00 p.m., Monday through Sunday, for all metered parking located in the Hyde Park Village, bound by S. Rome Street to the west, S. Oregon Street to the east, W. De Leon Street to the north and S. Dakota Avenue to the south.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-50), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 90-217, § 2, 8-16-90</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 95-260, § 1, 12-14-95</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 96-230, §<cite path="1-3">§ 1-3</cite>, 10-17-96</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 96-271, § 1, 12-19-96</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 97-70, § 1, 4-10-97</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 8, 7-14-2011</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-162, § 1, 11-16-2017</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-82</num>
        <heading>Duty of operators of vehicles to actuate the parking meter; parking beyond time fixed for such vehicle.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>When any vehicle shall be parked in any time regulated parking space as designated pursuant to <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>, where controlled by a parking meter, the owner or operator of such vehicle shall, upon entering the parking space, immediately actuate the parking meter. The parking meter may be actuated by manual or electronic means and/or by payment of authorized legal tender, and the parking space may then be used by such vehicle during the parking time limit prescribed by the director for that part of the street in which such parking is located or by state law. If the vehicle shall remain parked in any such parking space beyond the parking limit allowed, the parking meter, except for a pay station, shall display a sign showing illegal parking and, in that event, such vehicle shall be considered as parked overtime.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for any person to permit a vehicle to remain or be placed in any parking space when the parking meter indicates or displays a signal showing that such vehicle is parked overtime or when the pay station receipt indicates that parking time limits have expired.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for any person to permit a vehicle to remain in any parking space for more than two (2) hours after a citation has been issued for violation of <cite path="15-82|(b)">subsection (b)</cite> of <cite path="15-82">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>For any continuous parking in the same parking space, no more than one (1) offense under <cite path="15-82|(b)">subsection (b)</cite> of <cite path="15-82">this section</cite> and one (1) offense under <cite path="15-82|(c)">subsection (c)</cite> of <cite path="15-82">this section</cite> shall be deemed to have occurred on any one (1) date. In the case of any continuous parking in violation of <cite path="15-82|(b)">subsection (b)</cite> or <cite path="15-82|(c)">subsection (c)</cite> hereof covering parts of two (2) or more dates, one (1) offense under <cite path="15-82|(b)">subsection (b)</cite> and one (1) offense under <cite path="15-82|(c)">subsection (c)</cite> shall be deemed to have occurred on each of such dates.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>When signs are erected giving notice of time limits, no person shall park a vehicle in any parking meter space and/or zone for a continuous period of time longer than that period of time designated by such signs. In order to enforce this provision no person shall roll the tires of a vehicle or attempt to remove the markings made by a parking enforcement specialist prior to removing the vehicle from the parking space.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-51), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 97-20, §§ 1, 3, 1-23-97</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 97-20, §§ 1, 3, 1-23-97</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2000-64, § 1, 3-2-00</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-244, § 3, 9-18-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 9, 7-14-2011</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2014-16, § 2, 3-6-2014</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-83</num>
        <heading>Depositing slugs, etc., in meters.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful to deposit or cause to be deposited in any parking meter any slug, device, metallic or other substitute for a coin of the United States of America or to make any attempt thereof to defraud the city.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-52), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-84</num>
        <heading>Defacing or injuring meters.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful for any person to deface, injure, tamper with, open or willfully break, destroy or impair the usefulness of any parking meter installed under the terms of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> or to attach to any meter or post any type of object or thing which may cause damage, concern or safety hazards.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-53), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Cross reference— </strong>Damage to city property, <cite path="1-21">§ 1-21</cite>.</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-85</num>
        <heading>Taxicabs, buses, etc., parking in parking meter areas.</heading>
        <text>All taxicabs, buses and motor vehicles for hire are hereby prohibited from parking at any place upon city owned or operated streets, lots, garages or other property known as "parking meter spaces" and at any place in those areas in which parking is restricted as to the length of time for such parking, except between the hours of 10:00 p.m. and 7:00 a.m.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-54), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-86</num>
        <heading>Non-motorized vehicle parking prohibited.</heading>
        <text>Unless otherwise authorized in <cite>this Code</cite>, it shall be unlawful to park any non-motorized vehicle upon any street, alley, or city owned or operated property, other than for loading and unloading. A written warning will be provided prior to the issuance of a ticket. After twelve (12) hours, if the non-motorized vehicle is parked in any prohibited location, a ticket may be issued. Failure to move the non-motorized vehicle in violation from streets, alleys, or city owned or operated property within two (2) hours after the issuance of a ticket shall subject the non-motorized vehicle to immobilization and/or impoundment as provided under <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 3, 6-22-2017</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2020-39, § 3, 6-4-2020</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-87-15-100</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">3</num>
      <heading>PERMITS, PERMIT REGULATIONS</heading>
      <section>
        <num>15-101</num>
        <heading>Special parking permits.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The director may grant and issue, renew, deny or revoke special parking permits that, when properly displayed, will allow parking in a parking meter space without the requirement to make payment in the meter. Fees shall be assessed for a special parking permit. Requests for special parking permits shall be made in writing to the parking division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Special parking permits may be issued for the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Vehicles owned or leased by federal, state, county or city agencies while on official agency business and engaged in routine delivery services, repair, maintenance and/or inspectional work activities within the city limits;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Vehicles owned or leased by public utility companies who are actually engaged in the emergency repair of existing public utilities within the city limits. Such vehicles must be identified by permanent or removable markings on both sides of the exterior of the vehicle, in letters not less than three (3) inches high, of the name of the company operating the vehicles. A copy of the vehicle registration verifying company ownership or a copy of the "lease back employee agreement option" identifying such vehicle for company business must be submitted with the written request for such permit.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Permits issued to federal, state, county and city vehicles may be issued for one (1) calendar year. All other permits will be issued for a maximum of six (6) months and will be subject to a close evaluation of need and usage in accordance with policies and procedures developed by the director.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The director may grant and issue, renew, deny or revoke business parking permits or decals to regulate, control or allow parking at a city owned or operated parking facility, property or parking meter space. Fees shall be assessed for a business parking permit or decal. Requests for business parking permits and decals shall be made in writing to the parking division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The permits or decals provided for in <cite path="15-101">this section</cite> may be used at any parking meter space in the downtown of the city and/or Ybor City area for the specific hours, days and dates authorized.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The permit is to be renewed every three (3) months on the city quarterly schedule (January, April, July and October). The renewal request must be submitted fifteen (15) days prior to the expiration date on the permit.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-65), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2001-191, § 1, 8-16-01</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 10, 7-14-2011</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-102</num>
        <heading>Business parking permits and decals.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The director may grant and issue, renew, deny or revoke business parking permits or decals to regulate, control or allow parking at a city owned or operated parking facility, property or parking meter space. Fees shall be assessed for a business parking permit or decal. Requests for business parking permits and decals shall be made in writing to the parking division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The permits or decals provided for in <cite path="15-102">this section</cite> may be used at any parking meter space in the downtown of the city and/or Ybor City area for the specific hours, days and dates authorized.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The permit is to be renewed every three (3) months on the city quarterly schedule (January, April, July and October). The renewal request must be submitted fifteen (15) days prior to the expiration date on the permit.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-66), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 11, 7-14-2011</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-103</num>
        <heading>Reservation of parking meter spaces and removal of parking meters, posts or parking signs.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The director may grant or deny requests to temporarily reserve a parking meter space or remove a parking meter, post or parking sign. Fees shall be assessed for reserved parking meter spaces and removed parking meters, posts and parking signs, except that the fees may be waived for the purpose of creating a loading and unloading space, cab space, freight space, bus space, and parking space designated for city, county, state and federal officials. Requests shall be made to the parking division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A request to reserve a parking meter space may be granted for a vehicle including:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A truck or van which is actively engaged in the transportation of an excess amount of construction material, equipment, office furniture or money. The majority of the truck's cargo must be loaded or unloaded from the truck or van to a work area or building which is no more than two hundred (200) feet from the reserved parking meter space.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A vehicle used for or on official city business.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A request to remove a parking meter, post or parking sign may be granted for circumstances including when construction in the immediate area may cause damage to the parking meter, post or parking sign.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The director may revoke any grant to temporarily reserve a parking meter space or to remove a parking meter, post or parking sign if the use of such grant violates, or conflicts with, any provision of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-67), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 92-160, § 4, 10-1-92</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 12, 7-14-2011</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-104</num>
        <heading>Residential parking permit only area.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Application.</em>
          </text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A residential parking permit shall be issued to resident or business of a residential parking permit only area upon meeting the following requirements:</text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>Proof of residency in a single-family or multifamily dwelling within the residential parking permit only area; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>Proof of operation of a business within the residential parking permit only area.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>If a resident provides proof of residency within a residential parking permit only area, then a resident shall be entitled to the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>A minimum of one (1) residential parking permit per residence issued at no charge.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>If a residence does not contain any off-street parking, then a minimum of two (2) residential parking permits issued at no charge.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <text>Residents may purchase a third residential parking permit if needed.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>If a business provides proof of operation within a residential parking permit only area, then a business shall be entitled to the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>A minimum of four (4) residential parking permits per business issued at no charge which are valid from 4:00 a.m. to 9:00 p.m. During said hours the business' employees and their customers may park at designated spaces.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>The residential parking permits may be used interchangeably between the business' employees and their customers.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Guest residential parking permits may be requested from the parking division on an as-needed basis and are entitled to the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>A maximum one (1) guest residential parking permit per residence issued at no charge.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>Additional twenty-four-hour guest residential parking permits may purchased from the parking division.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <text>Additional seven (7) day guest residential parking permits may purchased from the parking division.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Permits shall be effective for six (6) months from date of issuance and must be renewed for each subsequent six-month period.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>Unless city signs clearly indicate to the contrary, a vehicle parked in a designated residential parking permit only area which has a valid residential parking permit for that residential parking permit only area affixed to the vehicle in accordance with the regulations of the residential parking permit only system shall not be in violation for overtime parking by virtue of parking for a period of time in excess of those allowed.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The following residential parking permit only areas and their boundaries are hereby established as follows:</text>
          <text>6th Avenue by the North;</text>
          <text>Adamo Drive by the South;</text>
          <text>Nick Nuccio Parkway and North 13th Street by the West;</text>
          <text>North 21st Street to the East;</text>
          <text>From 3rd Avenue up to 6th Avenue, between 15th Street and 21st Street;</text>
          <text>The 100 and 200 block[s] of North 12th Street;</text>
          <text>The 100 and 200 block[s] of South 12th Street;</text>
          <text>In the area of Kennedy Boulevard by the North, but excluding Kennedy Boulevard;</text>
          <text>In the area of Swann Avenue by the South, but excluding Swann Avenue;</text>
          <text>In the area of Armenia Avenue to the West, but excluding Armenia Avenue;</text>
          <text>Fremont Avenue to the East;</text>
          <text>The 100 block of South Packwood Avenue;</text>
          <para>
            <num>N.</num>
            <text>19th Street, between E. 12th Avenue and E. Palm Avenue;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>N.</num>
            <text>20th Street, between E. 12th Avenue and E. Palm Avenue;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>E.</num>
            <text>11th Avenue, between N. 20th Street and N. 21st Street;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>E.</num>
            <text>12th Avenue, between N. 19th Street and N. 21st Street;</text>
            <text>The 600 block of South Rome Avenue.</text>
            <text>When determining a residential parking permit only area, the area shall include both sides of the street, drive or avenue, listed as a boundary unless the area description clearly indicates to the contrary.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-247, § 2(39-68), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-255, § 3, 10-19-06</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2007-235, § 1, 11-15-07</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2008-202, § 1, 12-4-08</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2010-130, § 1, 9-23-2010</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2012-31, § 2, 3-15-2012</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2012-87, § 1, 8-2-2012</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-105</num>
        <heading>Denial, honoring and revocation of permits.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Permits provided for in this division may be denied for the following no exhaustive reasons:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The vehicle does not comply with a requirement stated in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The applicant has failed to appear in court when summoned for a parking violation or failed to pay a fine or charge for a parking violation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>As to a special parking permit, the number of stops made each day for loading and unloading and freight purposes are sufficiently low enough to warrant use of spaces specifically prescribed for such use in other sections of <cite>this Code</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Permits provided for in this division shall not be honored and may be revoked if any of the following non-exhaustive regulations are not observed:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The permit must be current and properly displayed on the front dash in front of the driver, by hang tag on the vehicles rear-view mirror or displayed on the rear window and be fully visible from the outside of the vehicle. It is unlawful for the operator of a vehicle to improperly display or display an expired or altered permit as authorization to park in a metered space without actuating by making payment of authorized legal tender by manual or electronic means into the parking meter.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>It is unlawful to display a permit in such a manner that the pertinent information is obscured.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>It is unlawful to display a permit in a vehicle other than the one for which it was issued.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>It is unlawful to exceed the parking time limit authorized by the permit.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>It is unlawful to use or attempt to use such permit for other than its purpose allowed in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>A vehicle displaying a permit must be parked in a legal manner and in a designated parking space.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><em>Revocation of a residential parking permit.</em> For any of the following reasons, a residential parking permit may be revoked by the parking division after providing notice to the holder of permit of the reasons for such revocation and providing an opportunity for the pass holder to respond to the parking division:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Providing false information when applying for the residential parking permit.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>If a residential parking permit is affixed to a vehicle for which it was not issued, it may be immediately revoked by order of the parking division. Such revocation immediately voids the permit.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>If a residential parking permit issued to an individual for a resident vehicle is revoked to <cite path="15-105">this section</cite>, then that individual or anyone residing in the same residence with that individual shall not be permitted to apply for a residential parking permit for a two-year period unless good cause can be shown that the act resulting in the revocation was unintentional.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-255, § 4, 10-19-06</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2011-84, § 13, 7-14-2011</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-106-15-119</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">4</num>
      <heading>PENALTIES AND ENFORCEMENT</heading>
      <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container">3 <strong>Editor's note—</strong> Ord. No. 2017-90, §<cite path="4-16">§ 4-16</cite>, adopted June 22, 2017, amended division 4 in its entirety to read as herein set out. Former division 4, §<cite path="15-121">§ 15-121</cite>-15-130 pertained to penalties. See Code Comparative Table for complete derivation.</annotation>
      <section>
        <num>15-120</num>
        <heading>Enforcement, in general.</heading>
        <text>Enforcement of parking violations, and impoundment and immobilization of vehicles as provided herein, serves a municipal purpose. Article VIII, section 2(b) of the Florida Constitution along with F.S. § 166.021, gives municipalities "home rule" powers. Article V, Section 1 of the Florida Constitution along with F.S. Ch. 162, empowers local governments to use local code enforcement boards or special magistrates. F.S. Ch. 316, provides the City with original jurisdiction over all streets and highways, except state roads, and allows for the placement of traffic control devices. In addition, F.S. Ch. 316, provides local jurisdictions with the authority to regulate specified activities on streets and highways to include, but not limited to parking and restricting the use of the streets. Municipalities are expressly authorized to regulate the parking of motor vehicles for any purpose with respect to streets, highways, or other property under the jurisdiction of the municipality. It is the intent of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> to regulate and enforce the enumerated areas within which the city may control certain traffic movements or parking within the jurisdiction of the City of Tampa as provided under F.S. Ch. 316. F.S. Ch. 316, shall be supplemental to any provisions of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>, but nothing herein shall be in conflict with F.S. Ch. 316. Unless otherwise specified, the regulation and disposition of violations of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> shall be enforced by using a hearing officer as defined herein.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 6, 6-22-2017</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-121</num>
        <heading>Issuance of parking tickets; payment or contesting tickets; penalties for parking violations; requesting a parking division review.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A law enforcement officer or parking enforcement specialist who discovers a vehicle parked in violation of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> or other law may issue a parking ticket form as may be used by the parking division to a vehicle as identified by the license plate number, vehicle identification number, or with other specificity to ensure the vehicle in violation can be identified and deliver it to the driver; or if the vehicle is unattended, attach such ticket to the vehicle in a conspicuous place, except that a uniform traffic citation prepared by the Florida Department of Highway Safety and Motor Vehicles may not be issued by being attached to an unattended vehicle. A uniform traffic citation shall not be used for a parking violation of the Code. Under Division 4, the term "vehicle" shall include "non-motive vehicle".</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The parking ticket shall provide:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The date and time of issuance;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The name or identification number of the officer or traffic enforcement specialist who issued the ticket;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>A description of the violation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The penalty amount;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The period of time in which it must be paid or set for a parking violation hearing before it is considered in delinquent status;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>The vehicle information;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Information on how and where the ticket may be paid; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Information on how the ticket may be contested.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The driver or owner of the vehicle which was issued a ticket shall elect to pay the ticket as described in paragraph (d) or request a parking violation hearing as described in paragraph (g). Failure to pay a ticket, or request a parking violation hearing, within the specified time period shall result in the ticket being in delinquent status, unless the ticket has already been dismissed under a parking division review as described in paragraph (i).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Unless otherwise specifically provided in <cite path="15-121">this section</cite>, the violation of any provision of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> relating to parking shall be a noncriminal civil infraction punishable by a penalty of twenty-nine dollars ($29.00) or if full payment is received by the city parking division within fourteen (14) calendar days of the date of the violation. Instructions for making payments shall be described on the ticket.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A violation of <cite path="15-82">section 15-82</cite>, duty of operators of vehicles to actuate the parking meter; parking beyond time fixed for such vehicle, shall be punishable by penalty of twenty-four dollars ($24.00) if paid to the city within fourteen (14) calendar days of the date of the violation. A violation of F.S. § 316.1955, enforcement of parking requirements for persons who have disabilities, shall be punishable by a penalty of two hundred fifty dollars ($250.00) if paid to the city within fourteen (14) calendar days of the date of the violation. Any penalty collected for such a violation may be deposited in a separate account to be used in the following manner: (a) one-third to be used to defray expenses for administration of this violation; and (b) two-thirds to be used to provide funds to improve accessibility and equal opportunity to qualified persons who have disabilities in the city and to provide funds to conduct public awareness programs in the city concerning persons who have disabilities. A violation of F.S. § 316.1945(1)(b)2., stopping, standing, or parking prohibited within fifteen (15) feet of a fire hydrant, or F.S. § 316.1945(1)(b)5., stopping, standing or parking prohibited within twenty (20) feet of the driveway entrance to any fire station and on the side of a street opposite the entrance to any fire station within seventy-five (75) feet of such entrance (when properly signposted), shall be punishable by a penalty of thirty dollars ($30.00) plus a three dollar ($3.00) excess fine if paid to the city within fourteen (14) days. All excess fines collected shall be used by the city for the purpose of funding a firefighter education program. A violation of <cite path="15-54">section 15-54</cite>, illegal use of license plates, exemption parking permits, or temporary exemption parking permits issued to person with disabilities or any subsection thereof, shall be punishable by a penalty of two hundred fifty dollars ($250.00) if paid to the city within fourteen (14) calendar days of the date of the violation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Any penalty not paid to the city within fourteen (14) calendar days of the date of the violation, unless a parking violation hearing has been requested, shall result in an additional penalty at an amount of five dollars ($5.00) for a violation of code <cite path="15-82">section 15-82</cite>, and ten dollars ($10.00) for all other parking violations, or amounts approved by law for other violations under <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>A person who wishes to contest a ticket without being assessed additional penalties or costs for delinquency shall complete and submit a written request for a parking violation hearing which must be received by the parking division within fourteen (14) calendar days of the date of the violation. A request for a parking violation hearing shall be on the form prescribed by the parking division (LAM form PD01 or approved online form). Requests shall include a complete name and address of the person contesting the hearing, and if available, a phone number and e-mail address. A copy of the parking ticket must be included with the request for a hearing. Upon such request, a notice of hearing will be issued, confirming the time and date of the hearing. A copy of the person's driver's license and vehicle registration, or other document acceptable to the city attorney's office, will be necessary to set a parking violation hearing. All contested parking violation hearings shall be heard by a hearing officer. The parking division shall send a Notice of Hearing which states:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The date, time, and location of a pre-scheduled parking violation hearing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>That a person who elects to contest the ticket may be assessed a penalty of up to one hundred dollars ($100.00) if found in violation after a hearing by a hearing officer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>That a person who elects to contest a violation and then fails to appear at the parking violation hearing shall be deemed to have waived his or her right to a hearing and may be found in violation by default subject to a penalty of up to one hundred dollars ($100.00), unless otherwise authorized or prohibited by law;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>That unpaid violations will be in delinquent status and are subject to being sent to collections for payment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>That vehicles bearing license plates which are identified as belonging to owners who have tickets in delinquent status are subject to immobilization or impoundment as provided in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>The Notice of Hearing shall be sent by mail or e-mail to the person making the request for a parking violation hearing at the physical address or e-mail address provided in the request. A certification by the parking division that the Notice of Hearing was mailed to the physical address or e-mail address provided on a request for a parking violation hearing constitutes prima facie evidence that the person on the Notice of Hearing was served with the notice. Upon notification, the person requesting a parking violation hearing is required to comply with the directions on the Notice of Hearing or face a finding of violation due to default. Additional penalties or costs may be imposed by a hearing officer upon finding of a violation; however, a violation which was set for a parking violation hearing upon a timely requested parking violation hearing will not be assessed fees for delinquency if timely paid after a finding of a violation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>A person who requests a parking violation hearing waives his or her right to pay the initial civil penalty amounts set forth in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>. The hearing officer, after a hearing, shall make a determination as to whether a parking violation has been committed and may impose a civil penalty not to exceed one hundred dollars ($100.00), unless otherwise authorized or prohibited by law, plus administrative costs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>The director will establish a parking division review procedure for requesting a preliminary review by the parking division of a parking ticket issued by the parking division or an immobilization and/or impoundment of a vehicle pursuant to <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>. Any person wishing to request a parking division review shall complete a written request for a parking division review on the prescribed form by the parking division within five (5) calendar days of the date of the violation (LAR form PD 02 or approved online form). Within seven (7) calendar days of receiving a parking division review, the parking division will make a determination and mail or e-mail to the address provided in the parking division review a written notification of the determination to the person requesting the parking division review. The determination can affirm the issuance of the ticket or immobilization/impoundment, dismiss the ticket, or allow for a reduction in the penalty. For immobilization/impoundment, the determination shall either affirm the immobilization/impoundment, allow the release of the immobilization device without penalty, or complete a waiver of impoundment fees as may be appropriate. The request for a parking division review will not toll any time periods herein. The parking division review shall at a minimum allow review of an improperly written ticket, a malfunctioning pay station, a vehicle which has been sold or stolen and is no longer the property of the registered owner of the license plate affixed to the vehicle when the ticket was written, or a vehicle which was improperly immobilized and/or impounded. The director may establish procedures to allow affidavits to be submitted as described in F.S. § 316.1967. The burden shall be on the person challenging the validity of the parking ticket or immobilization and/or impoundment to the satisfaction of the director or designee. The director or designee may dismiss or reduce a ticket.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>In addition to the penalties and excess fines provided in <cite path="15-121">this section</cite>, a surcharge on parking fines of one dollar ($1.00), or such amount as may hereafter be set by city council resolution, for each violation shall be imposed for the sole purpose of funding school crossing guard programs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(l)</num>
          <text>In addition, for each parking ticket that results in the issuance of a notice of delinquent status of any provision of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> relating to parking, an administrative fee of six dollars ($6.00) shall be assessed, collected, and retained by the city for administrative cost. No such fee shall be assessed when a parking ticket is dismissed or when the person is found to not be in violation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(m)</num>
          <text>Payment made pursuant to <cite path="15-121">this section</cite> may be made by authorized legal tender or other forms of payment approved by resolution upon the recommendation of the mayor and approved by the city council.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 7, 6-22-2017</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2020-71, § 1, 9-3-2020</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-122</num>
        <heading>Vehicles parked in violation of regulations deemed nuisance; continuous parking in metered parking spaces; habitual parking status.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The owner of any vehicle shall be held responsible for any vehicle found upon a street or highway in violation of any provision of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>, or any ordinances(s) or executive order for emergency which regulates the stopping, standing or parking of vehicles. Nothing contained in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> shall limit the ability of the city to seek other enforcement action as may be permitted in the Code nor limit the ability of the City to enjoin a nuisance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for any vehicle in violation of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> to remain in any metered parking space for more than two (2) hours after a ticket has been issued for violation of any provision of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>. For continuous parking beyond each two-hour period, a new offense shall be deemed to have occurred and a law enforcement officer, a duly certified code enforcement officer, or a parking enforcement specialist is authorized to issue an additional ticket for each subsequent two-hour period.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful to park a vehicle in violation of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> which is in habitual parking status. A vehicle meeting the qualifications of habitual parking status commits an additional violation under this sub-section punishable by a penalty of one hundred dollars ($100.00) and shall be immediately immobilized, and if necessary impounded, as provided for under <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 8, 6-22-2017</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2020-96, § 5, 10-1-2020</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-123</num>
        <heading>Liability of owners; notice of delinquent status; obtaining a parking violation hearing upon a notice of delinquent status.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any vehicle issued a parking ticket is deemed to be charged with a noncriminal civil infraction and the owner shall be deemed responsible for complying with the directions on the ticket for paying or contesting the violation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Except for parking tickets dismissed after a parking division review request and review, all tickets which have not been paid or set for a parking violation hearing as described in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> shall be deemed in delinquent status at the expiration of the fourteen-day time period, and the parking division shall send the owner of the vehicle that was issued a ticket a notice of delinquent status which states:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The ticket number, date, time, description, and amount of penalties to include the original amount of the penalty, the amount of penalties for delinquency, and administrative fees;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The options for methods of payment of the ticket;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The due date;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The owner may still elect to contest a ticket and delinquent status at a parking violation hearing by appearing in front of a hearing officer who will hear testimony and consider evidence;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The date, time, and location of a pre-scheduled parking violation hearing which must be confirmed along with the method for confirming the hearing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>A copy of the owner's driver's license and vehicle registration will be necessary to confirm a hearing date;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>That failure to pay the ticket or confirm the parking violation hearing by the date specified will be deemed as a waiver of the owner's right to contest the ticket and a finding of violation will be entered for the amount stated in the notice of delinquent status;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>That an owner who elects to contest the ticket waives his or her right to pay the penalty amount in the notice of delinquent status and the owner may be assessed a penalty of up to one hundred dollars ($100.00) if found in violation after a hearing by a hearing officer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>That an owner who elects to contest a violation and then fails to appear shall be deemed to have waived his or her right to a hearing and may be found in violation by default subject to a penalty of up to one hundred dollars ($100.00);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>That unpaid violations will remain in delinquent status and are subject to being sent to collections for payment;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>That any vehicle(s) bearing a license plate identified as belonging to owners who have tickets in delinquent status are subject to immobilization or impoundment as provided in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The notice of delinquent status shall be sent by U.S. mail to the person and address given on the motor vehicle registration. A certification by the parking division that the notice of delinquent status was mailed to the address given on the motor vehicle registration constitutes prima facie evidence that the person on the notice of delinquent status was served with the notice. Mailing the notice of delinquent status to the address listed on the motor vehicle registration constitutes notification and requires the owner to comply with the directions on the notice of delinquent status.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any owner who fails to satisfy the directive on the notice of delinquent status may be assessed additional penalties or costs by a hearing officer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>An owner who wants to contest a ticket or notice of delinquent status shall confirm the parking violation hearing as instructed in the notice of delinquent status within seven (7) calendar days from the date of the notice of delinquent status. A copy of the owner's driver's license and vehicle registration will be necessary to confirm a hearing date. The director may establish other necessary procedures for an owner's confirmation of a parking violation hearing upon receiving a notice of delinquent status.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>A finding of violation occurs when a parking ticket is paid, not contested after notice of violation, in default, or after a hearing by a hearing officer results in a finding of violation. All findings of violations are considered an adjudication on the merits.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 9, 6-22-2017</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-124</num>
        <heading>Cancellation or continuances of hearings; burden of proof; payment after hearing.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>A scheduled parking violation hearing will be cancelled if full payment of the pending violation(s) is received prior to the hearing date. A person wanting to continue a parking violation hearing date shall deliver a written request for continuance to the parking department at least seventy-two (72) hours prior to the hearing date and shall be granted one continuance for a scheduled parking violation hearing of a contested ticket or post-immobilization hearing. The director shall establish the procedure for delivery of a written request for a continuance and for providing notice of the rescheduled parking violation hearing time and date.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A violation shall be proven at a hearing by a preponderance of the evidence.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A finding of violation requires all penalties and costs to be paid within seven (7) calendar days unless additional time is granted by the hearing officer or the parking division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Failure to pay outstanding penalties or costs after a finding of a violation at a hearing shall result in the ticket being in delinquent status if not paid within the time period allowed.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 10, 6-22-2017</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-125</num>
        <heading>Additional penalties and enforcement to include immobilization, impoundment, and use of a collection agency.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The parking division, Tampa Police Department, or personnel as designated by the director are authorized to attach a device that is capable of immobilizing a vehicle as described in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> when:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>It is determined that the plate number attached to a vehicle or the owner of a vehicle owes one hundred ($100.00) dollars or more to the parking division as a result of tickets which are in delinquent status, according to the records of the parking division;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A violation of sub<cite path="15-122|(c)">section 15-122(c)</cite> exists, relating to habitual parking status;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>A violation of <cite path="15-86">section 15-86</cite> exists, relating to non-motorized vehicles;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>A violation of <cite path="15-47">section 15-47</cite>, relating to motor vehicles of eighty-six (86) inches or more in overall width;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Otherwise authorized by Code or law to include F.S. Ch. 316, for violations of Florida's Uniform Traffic Control Laws.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In order to ensure the safety of the vehicle, a vehicle immobilized between the hours of 8:00 a.m. and 9:00 p.m. shall be impounded if the reason for the immobilization has not been resolved and the immobilization device has not been removed by 9:00 p.m. on the day of the immobilization. A vehicle immobilized between the hours of 9:00 p.m. and 8:00 a.m. may be immediately impounded. Violations of <cite path="15-86">section 15-86</cite>, relating to non-motorized vehicles, may be immediately impounded or immobilized for the purpose of immediate impoundment and shall not be released until any immobilization and impoundment penalties and costs are paid. Nothing herein shall prohibit a vehicle from being immobilized or impounded where otherwise authorized by Code or law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The clerk of the circuit court and the county court, or the parking division shall supply the Florida Department of Highway Safety and Motor Vehicles with an electronic data file listing persons who have three (3) or more outstanding parking violations or who have any outstanding violations of F.S. § 316.1955. The provisions of F.S. § 320.03(8) shall apply to each person whose name appears on such lists.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The city may send all penalties and costs owed under <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> to collections and where authorized by law, place a lien on real or personal property, to include liens for recovering, towing, or storing vehicles as authorized under F.S. § 713.78.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 11, 6-22-2017</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2020-39, § 4, 6-4-2020</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-126</num>
        <heading>Immobilization or impoundment of vehicles.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Immobilization referred to in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> shall be by an immobilization device attached to the vehicle at the place where it is found, except that no vehicle shall be immobilized on private property or within the traveled portion of any street or on any portion of a street when immobilization at such place would create a hazard to the public or to the traffic. At the same time as the immobilizing device is attached to the vehicle, a warning notice shall be affixed to the windshield or other prominent place on the vehicle stating that the immobilizing device has been so attached, cautioning the operator not to attempt to operate the vehicle while the immobilizing device is still attached and informing the operator that the vehicle is under immobilization, the reason for the immobilization, and where the proper person must go in order to arrange for the removal of the immobilization device or request a post-immobilization hearing. Immobilization fees shall be paid to the parking division. A person with standing who wishes to request a post-immobilization hearing in front of a hearing officer shall follow the procedure set out under <cite path="15-128">section 15-128</cite> of <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Impoundment referred to in <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> shall be done in accordance with on F.S. § 713.78. Impoundment of a vehicle under <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> will require the Police Department to authorize the vehicle to be removed to a police impound lot. A vehicle impounded under <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> will be subject to all liens and terms described under F.S. § 713.78, in addition to payment of all penalties and costs that are due. A person wishing to challenge the immobilization of a vehicle shall follow the procedure described under F.S. § 713.78. The parking division will establish a procedure for sending notice to the owner that the vehicle has been impounded along with the reason for the impoundment, location of the vehicle, and the process for obtaining the vehicle. The city will also ensure a notice is sent as required under F.S. § 713.78. Upon request, a person whose vehicle has been immobilized shall be provided with an itemized list of all penalties and costs owed which resulted in the immobilization. A vehicle impounded as authorized under <cite path="15-125|(a)|(1)">section 15-125(a)(1)</cite>, relating to delinquent status, or as authorized under <cite path="15-125|(a)|(2)">section 15-125(a)(2)</cite>, relating to habitual parking status, shall be released upon proof of payment of penalties and costs to the parking division or a release from the parking division along with payment of all costs related to the impoundment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>An owner may request a parking division review by following the same procedures as provided for parking division review under <cite path="15-121|(j)">section 15-121(j)</cite>. However, a parking division review for immobilization shall be made by the close of the next business day after the immobilization and the review shall be done prior to the end of the next business day following the request for a parking division review for immobilization. The director shall establish a procedure for the immediate removal of an immobilization device when a person pays all past due penalties and costs and an immobilization fee as established by resolution, and there are no more tickets in delinquent status.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 12, 6-22-2017</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-127</num>
        <heading>Removal of immobilizing device unlawful.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful for any person to attempt or to remove, damage, destroy or tamper with an immobilizing device affixed to a vehicle by the city. A violation of <cite path="15-127">this section</cite> shall be punished in accordance with City Code <cite path="1-6">Section 1-6</cite>. Release of an immobilized vehicle will take place in accordance with <cite path="15-129">section 15-129</cite>.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 13, 6-22-2017</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-128</num>
        <heading>Establishment of post-immobilization hearings.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any person wishing to challenge the immobilization of a vehicle pursuant to <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> shall be entitled to a post-immobilization hearing before a hearing officer. Post-immobilization hearings shall be handled on the same date and time as parking violation hearings. A person who wishes to contest an immobilization without being assessed additional penalties or costs for impoundment shall post a bond for the entire amount in dispute and complete and submit a written request for post-immobilization hearing which must be received by the parking division within two (2) business days of the date of the immobilization. A request for a post-immobilization hearing shall be on the form provided by the parking division. Requests shall include a complete name and address of the person requesting a hearing, and if available, a phone number and e-mail address. A description of the dispute must be included with the request for a hearing. Upon such request, a notice of hearing will be issued, confirming the time and date of the hearing. A copy of the person's driver's license and vehicle registration will be necessary to schedule a post-immobilization hearing. All contested hearings shall be heard by a hearing officer who hears parking violation hearings. The parking division shall send a notice of hearing which states:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The date, time, and location of a pre-scheduled post-immobilization hearing;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>That a person who elects to contest the ticket waives his or her right to pay the initial amount due at the time of the immobilization unless a bond was posted and the person will accrue additional penalties and costs for the impoundment of the vehicle until a hearing is held and a determination is made as to whether the vehicle was immobilized in accordance with chapter 15, Tampa Code;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>That a person who elects to contest a violation and then fails to appear shall be deemed to have waived his or her right to a hearing and any bond will be forfeited to the city; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>That any vehicles which remain impounded are subject to liens in accordance with F.S. § 713.78.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The Notice of Hearing shall be sent by mail or e-mail to the person making the request for a post-immobilization hearing to the physical address or e-mail address provided in the request. A certification by the parking division that the Notice of Hearing was mailed to the physical address or e-mail address provided on a post-immobilization request constitutes prima facie evidence that the person on the Notice of Hearing was served with the notice. Upon notification, the person wanting a post-immobilization is required to comply with the directions on the Notice of Hearing or waive his or her right to challenge the immobilization.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>A person who requests a post-immobilization hearing waives his or her right to pay the initial penalty and costs due as of the date of the immobilization unless a bond was posted. The hearing officer, after a hearing, shall make a determination as to whether an immobilization was done in accordance with <cite path="15">this chapter</cite>. If the hearing officer determines that the immobilization carried out by the city pursuant to <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> was not in accordance with the applicable ordinances, statutes and regulations, the aggrieved party shall be entitled to a reimbursement of any bond, fines, costs or penalties paid related to the contested immobilization or if the vehicle is still impounded, the vehicle shall be immediately released with a waiver of all fines, costs, and penalties.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 14, 6-22-2017</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-129</num>
        <heading>Release of immobilized or impounded vehicle.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>An immobilized vehicle under <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> may be released by the city upon: payment of all parking fines, costs, and immobilization fees; a parking division review determination to release the immobilization device without penalty; or upon a hearing officer finding in favor of the person challenging the immobilization.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A vehicle impounded under <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> may be released upon: payment of all parking penalties, costs, towing, storage, and administrative fees in accordance with F.S. § 713.78; or upon the posting of a cash or surety bond totaling all applicable amounts owed until the disposition of any hearing held in accordance with section F.S. § 713.78. A person who posts a bond under <cite path="15-129">this section</cite> and fails to file a complaint within the time period required under F.S. § 713.78 shall have waived his or her right to a hearing and the total amount of the posted bond shall be forfeited to the city.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 15, 6-22-2017</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>15-130</num>
        <heading>Disposition of unrecovered impounded vehicles.</heading>
        <text>Vehicles impounded under <cite path="15">this chapter</cite> which are not recovered may be disposed of in accordance with F.S. § 713.78.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-90, § 16, 6-22-2017</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
</container>
