<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>2</num>
  <heading>ADMINISTRATION</heading>
  <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">1 <strong>Charter reference— </strong>Conduct of government, Art. VI.</annotation>
  <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">Related law reference—General powers, Art. II.</annotation>
  <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Cross reference— </strong>Administrative provisions of building and construction regulations, <cite path="5-1">§ 5-1</cite> et seq.; administration of flood damage control procedures, <cite path="5-221">§ 5-221</cite> et seq.; administrative provisions of business regulation, <cite path="6-1">§ 6-1</cite> et seq.; code enforcement board, Ch. 9; elections, Ch. 10; administrative provisions of fire prevention and protection, <cite path="11-1">§ 11-1</cite> et seq.; human rights, Ch. 12; administrative provisions of landscaping, tree removal and site clearing, <cite path="13-1">§ 13-1</cite> et seq.; administrative provisions of parking, <cite path="15-1">§ 15-1</cite> et seq.; administrative authority of property maintenance and structural standards, <cite path="19-1">§ 19-1</cite> et seq.; administrative provisions of stormwater management, <cite path="21-1">§ 21-1</cite> et seq.; administrative provisions of streets and sidewalks, <cite path="22-1">§ 22-1</cite> et seq.; administrative provisions of subdivision, <cite path="27-153.1">§ 27-153.1</cite> et seq.; taxation, Ch. 24; administrative provisions of transportation, <cite path="25-1">§ 25-1</cite> et seq.; administrative provisions of utilities, <cite path="26-1">§ 26-1</cite> et seq.; administration of zoning regulations, <cite path="27-366">§ 27-366</cite> et seq.</annotation>
  <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>State Law reference— </strong>Municipal Home Rule Powers Act, F.S. Ch. 166.</annotation>
  <container>
    <prefix>ARTICLE</prefix>
    <num path-omit="true">I</num>
    <heading>IN GENERAL</heading>
    <section>
      <num>2-1</num>
      <heading>Title.</heading>
      <text><cite path="2">This chapter</cite> shall be known and may be cited as the "City of Tampa Administration Ordinance."</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-1), 9-28-89</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2-2</num>
      <heading>City seal—General restrictions.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to use, display or exhibit in any manner or for any purpose whatsoever the seal of the city or a facsimile thereof, except:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The officers and employees of the city in connection with city business;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>Upon compliance by such person with <cite path="2-3">section 2-3</cite>; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Such person shall have first obtained the written permission of the official and the city council.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-2), 9-28-89</annotation>
        <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>State Law reference— </strong>Wrongful use of city's name, F.S. § 817.17.</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2-3</num>
      <heading>Same—Cigar manufacturers granted use under enumerated conditions.</heading>
      <text>Any manufacturer of cigars made within the corporate limits of the city shall have and is hereby granted the privilege, which shall continue for so long as <cite path="2-3">this section</cite> shall remain in effect and as such manufacturer shall comply with the terms and conditions hereof, of using, displaying or exhibiting upon the container, package or wrapper of such cigars a facsimile of the official and corporate seal of the city upon compliance by the manufacturer with the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The manufacturer shall be the holder of a current and valid city occupational license tax receipt for the manufacture of the cigars;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The container, package, or wrapper shall bear in a prominent place and bold letters the words "Made in Tampa" or words of similar import; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>The manufacturer shall first file with the city clerk the affidavit of the proprietor thereof, or, if a corporation, the affidavit of the president thereof, showing the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>The name of the manufacturer;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>The name of each brand of cigars for which the facsimile is to be used, displayed or exhibited; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>The street address of the factory in which each brand of cigars is manufactured.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-3), 9-28-89</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2-4-2-25</num>
      <heading>Reserved.</heading>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>ARTICLE</prefix>
    <num path-omit="true">II</num>
    <heading>CITY CLERK</heading>
    <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">2 <strong>Charter reference— </strong>City clerk, Art. III.</annotation>
    <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Cross reference— </strong>Code of ethics for officials and employees, <cite path="2-326">§ 2-326</cite> et seq.</annotation>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">1</num>
      <heading>GENERALLY</heading>
      <section>
        <num>2-26</num>
        <heading>Duties generally.</heading>
        <text>It shall be the duty of the city clerk to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Record every official meeting of the city council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Be responsible for the recording, filing, indexing and safekeeping of all proceedings of the city council;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Publish legal notices unless otherwise provided;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Have charge of and file all ordinances, resolutions, executive orders, contracts, deeds, oaths of office, and all other documents of which he may be made custodian by law, or as may come into his possession as city clerk;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Be the custodian of the official city seal;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Perform all such other duties as may be designated from time to time by ordinance.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-66), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-27</num>
        <heading>Deputy city clerks.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The official is hereby authorized and empowered to appoint from time to time one (1) or more deputy city clerks, who shall hold office at the pleasure of the official.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Each deputy city clerk shall, in the event of the death, disqualification, inability to act or absence from the city of the city clerk, have and may exercise all the powers and functions and perform all of the duties now or which may be hereafter vested in or imposed upon the city clerk.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Each deputy city clerk so appointed shall take the oath as prescribed by law.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-67), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-28-2-40</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">2</num>
      <heading>ARCHIVES AND RECORDS SERVICE</heading>
      <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">3 <strong>State Law reference— </strong>Public records, F.S. Ch. 119; mandate to establish a program for disposal of records, F.S. § 119.01(2); public meetings and records, F.S. § 286.011.</annotation>
      <section>
        <num>2-41</num>
        <heading>Short title; purpose.</heading>
        <text>This division shall be known and may be cited as the "City of Tampa Archives and Records Service." The declared purpose of these sections is to provide for the proper and efficient management of the public records of the city and for the operation of a central repository for the city's permanently valuable records.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-86), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 91-184, § 1, 9-26-91</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-42</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <text>The following words, terms and phrases, when used in this division, shall have the meanings ascribed to them in <cite path="2-42">this section</cite>, except where the context clearly indicates a different meaning:</text>
        <text><em>Archival records</em> means those records, manuscripts and other records which document the origin and history of the government of the city and the development of its agencies which are worthy of permanent preservation and special administration because of the importance of the information they contain.</text>
        <text><em>City clerk</em> means the city clerk of the City of Tampa, Florida, or his duly designated representative.</text>
        <text><em>Inactive records</em> means those records no longer required in active office areas but which require further retention due to legal, fiscal, administrative or archival value.</text>
        <text><em>Maintenance of public records</em> means the creation, maintenance, protection, use and disposition of all public records of the city, including the establishment and maintenance of a system of filing and indexing public records.</text>
        <text><em>Public records</em> means all documents, papers, letters, maps, books, tapes, photographs, films, sound recordings or other materials, regardless of physical form or characteristics, made or received pursuant to law or ordinance or in connection with the transaction of official business by any officer or employee of the city; however, public records shall not be construed to mean those public records which are deemed by law to be confidential or which are prohibited from being inspected by the public or which shall be exempt from the provisions of this division or from the provisions of the state Public Records Act.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-87), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 91-184, § 2, 9-26-91</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Cross reference— </strong>Definitions and rules of construction generally, <cite path="1-2">§ 1-2</cite>.</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-43</num>
        <heading>Ownership of public records.</heading>
        <text>All public records shall be the property of the city, and, in this regard, such records shall be delivered by outgoing officials and employees to their successors.</text>
        <text>Inactive records shall be transferred to the city records center. When such records are determined archival and accepted, the archives shall be considered the legal custodial site and the city clerk shall have disposal authority.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-88), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 91-184, § 3, 9-26-91</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>State Law reference— </strong>Disposition of records at end of official's term, F.S. § 119.05.</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-44</num>
        <heading>Duties of officers and employees.</heading>
        <text>It shall be the duty of each officer and employee of the city to protect, preserve, store, transfer, destroy or otherwise dispose of, use and manage public records only in accordance with applicable federal, state or local law, or such rules as may be promulgated or approved by the city clerk.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-89), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-45</num>
        <heading>Duties of city clerk.</heading>
        <text>It shall be the responsibility of the city clerk to administer the City of Tampa Archives and Records Service. In this regard the city clerk, among all other things that may be required for the proper and efficient management of the public records of the city, shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Develop and circulate such rules and regulations as may be necessary and proper to implement and maintain the records management program;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Provide and maintain a city records center to house and preserve inactive records prior to disposition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Advise and assist city departments in the preparation of records inventory and destruction schedules;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Approve destruction schedules before disposition of the public records;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Organize and administer the City of Tampa Archives:</text>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <text>Identify and ensure the preservation of city archival records, requiring their transfer to the archives if deemed necessary.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b.</num>
            <text>Provide for and direct a city archivist/records manager who shall ensure the sound management of archival records and their availability for research.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>c.</num>
            <text>Promote educational and research use of the city archives by individuals, organizations in the community, and other researchers.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>d.</num>
            <text>Accept from any person any papers, books, records and similar materials which in the judgment of the department warrant preservation in the city archives.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>e.</num>
            <text>Appoint an advisory committee to promote the archives, provide professional assistance and foster a cooperative approach to the historical resources of the Tampa area.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Provide microfilming services for public records pursuant to rules promulgated by the city clerk for the centralization of such services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Conduct, as the city clerk deems necessary, such surveys, studies and investigations as will assist in promoting a proper and efficient records management program for the city, including information retrieval systems.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-90), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 91-184, §§ 4, 5, 9-26-91</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>State Law reference— </strong>Custodian designated, F.S. § 119.021.</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-46</num>
        <heading>Duties of departments.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Departments shall create and maintain all records with adequate and proper documentation of the organization, together with the functions, policies, decisions, procedures, and essential transactions, of the department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Departments, with the advice of the city clerk, shall establish and maintain an active, continuing program for the economical and efficient management of the records of each respective department. Such program shall, among other things, provide for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Effective controls over the creation, maintenance and use of records in the conduct of current business;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Cooperation with the city clerk in applying standards, procedures and techniques designed to improve the management of records;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Promotion of the maintenance and security of records deemed appropriate for preservation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Segregation and disposal of records of temporary value in accordance with established retention schedules.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Those public records which are not required in the current operation of the office where they are made or kept, and all public records which can properly be abolished or discontinued, shall be transferred to the city records center or archives.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Each department of the city shall designate a representative to coordinate the management of records in that department. The representative shall:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Coordinate all records management activities and functions within the department and with the city clerk;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>With the advice and assistance of the city clerk, inventory or manage the inventory of all public records for disposition scheduling and transfer action in accordance with procedures prescribed by law or rule promulgated by the city clerk.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Consult with any other personnel responsible for creation or maintenance of specific records within his department regarding records retention and transfer recommendations;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Analyze records inventory data, examine and compare division or unit inventories for duplication of records, and recommend to the city records officer minimal retentions for all copies commensurate with legal, financial and administrative needs.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Review established records retention schedules at least annually to ensure that they are complete and current.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-91), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 91-184, §<cite path="6-8">§ 6-8</cite>, 9-26-91</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-47</num>
        <heading>State laws and other regulations.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The city clerk shall be responsible for administering the archives and records service program in compliance with state laws and the regulations of appropriate state agencies relating to the scheduling and disposition of public records of the city.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The city clerk shall be responsible for the systematic destruction of the city's public records when such records have met their approved retention period and destruction has been authorized by the appropriate department head and state agency. The method of destruction will satisfy state and city requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The city clerk shall keep an index of all scheduled records which have been filed with or submitted to the appropriate state agency and shall further prepare and keep disposal certificates in accordance with state law or regulations on destroyed records.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The city clerk is authorized to promulgate rules and regulations not inconsistent with <cite path="2-47">this section</cite>, as may be necessary and proper to implement the objectives hereof.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-92), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-48-2-70</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>ARTICLE</prefix>
    <num path-omit="true">III</num>
    <heading>DEPARTMENTS</heading>
    <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">4 <strong>Charter reference— </strong>Departments, Art. V.</annotation>
    <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>State Law reference— </strong>Code of ethics for public officers and employees, F.S. § 112.311 et seq.; public records, F.S. Ch. 119; public meetings and records, F.S. § 286.011.</annotation>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">1</num>
      <heading>GENERALLY</heading>
      <section>
        <num>2-71-2-110</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">2</num>
      <heading>DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE AND FINANCE</heading>
      <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">5 <strong>Charter reference— </strong>Department of revenue and finance, § 5.01(b).</annotation>
      <section>
        <num>2-111</num>
        <heading>Annual inventory.</heading>
        <text>During each fiscal year the director of finance shall cause to be conducted a physical count of all inventory and property. The method for conducting the count will be determined by the director of finance and will comply with accepted accounting procedures. A full and detailed list of all property will be prepared and submitted to the official. Upon receiving the official's approval, a copy will be filed with the city clerk.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-151), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-112</num>
        <heading>Keeping regular books of accounts.</heading>
        <text>In addition to the duties prescribed by the Charter, the director of finance shall keep regular books of accounts of the city in which he shall enter all indebtedness of the city, and which shall at all times show the precise financial condition of the city, the amounts of bonds, orders, certificates, warrants or other evidence of outstanding indebtedness and the redemption of the same when redeemed.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-152), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-113</num>
        <heading>Countersign all evidences of indebtedness of city.</heading>
        <text>The director of finance shall countersign all bonds, certificates or other evidences of indebtedness of the city, and no such bond, certificate or other evidence of indebtedness shall be valid unless countersigned by him.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-153), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-114</num>
        <heading>Travel expense forms and regulations.</heading>
        <text>The director of finance shall provide forms for travel requests, expenses, reimbursements and mileage allowances, and prescribe such regulations as are necessary.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-154), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-115</num>
        <heading>Reporting of information.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The city shall make all rules and regulations to govern reports and accounts by all persons remitting revenues to the city for the purpose of enabling the city to ascertain whether or not such revenues are being remitted to the city in an appropriate manner as required by <cite>this Code</cite> or applicable law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The city is further given power to investigate or cause to be investigated, under its authority, all cases involving the remittance of revenues to the city as provided in <cite path="2-115|(a)">subsection (a)</cite> of <cite path="2-115">this section</cite> to determine from such investigation whether or not such revenues are remitted as required by this Code or applicable law, and the determination of the city in any case shall be prima facie valid and authentic in all courts in this state.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-155), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-116</num>
        <heading>Transmittal of annual budget supplement.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>No less then forty-five (45) days before the expiration of each fiscal year, the mayor shall submit a supplemental revenue and expenditure document concurrently with the submission of the annual budget for the next fiscal year.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The content and degree of detail of the supplemental revenue and expenditure document shall be consistent with the past practice and custom of the mayor and the council and shall contain sufficient detail to afford the city council the opportunity to make an informed decision with respect to income and expenditures for the fiscal year covered by the annual budget that is under review for approval by the city council.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Proposed changes in the content of the supplemental revenue and expenditure document that substantially deviate from the past practice and custom of the mayor and the council shall be approved by resolution of the city council prior to submission of the supplemental revenue and expenditure document pursuant to <cite path="2-116|(a)">subsection (a)</cite>, herein.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2009-139, § 1, 10-1-09</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-117-2-135</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">3</num>
      <heading>DEPARTMENT OF CONVENTION FACILITIES</heading>
      <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">6 <strong>Cross reference— </strong>Alcoholic beverages in convention centers, <cite path="3-146">§ 3-146</cite>.</annotation>
      <section>
        <num>2-136</num>
        <heading>Established; jurisdiction.</heading>
        <text>There is hereby established a department of convention facilities which shall have jurisdiction and cognizance over all activities relating to conventions and convention facilities in the city.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-171), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-137</num>
        <heading>Director.</heading>
        <text>The head of the department of convention facilities shall be called the director of convention facilities. The director shall be appointed and confirmed as is provided in section 6.03 of the Charter. The director shall be responsible to the official for the management and operation of the department and shall keep all records and accounts of the department. Further, he shall have such other powers and duties as are prescribed by ordinance.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-172), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-138</num>
        <heading>Functions.</heading>
        <text>The department of convention facilities shall have cognizance over:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>All buildings, equipment and facilities provided for convention activities in the city, including the supervision and control of the boat docking facilities adjacent to the Hills borough River beginning at the park adjacent to the Tampa Convention Center circular drive on the east side of the river along the Tampa Convention Center River Walk and ending at Platt Street in the city;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>All activities relating to any convention center and all matters relating to entertainment, securing of conventions, marketing, promotions, management, scheduling, conduct, preservation, and rules and regulations for the use of any such facilities;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>All publicity relating to convention matters;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Such other activities of a public nature as may be designated by the official.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-173), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 92-179, § 1, 11-12-92</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-139-2-165</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container"><strong>Editor's note— </strong>Ord. No. 94-132, § 1, adopted July 21, 1994, repealed §<cite path="2-139">§ 2-139</cite> and 2-140, which pertained to the advisory board. See the Code Comparative Table.</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>ARTICLE</prefix>
    <num path-omit="true">IV</num>
    <heading>RESERVED</heading>
    <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container">7 <strong>Editor's note—</strong> Ord. No. 2003-255, § 1, adopted Oct. 2, 2003, amended the title of Art. IV from "Personnel" to "Reserved." Sections 2 and 3 of said ordinance renumbered former <cite path="2-166">§ 2-166</cite> as current <cite path="2-581">§ 2-581</cite> and amended same. See also the Code Comparative Table for a detailed analysis of inclusion of Ord. No. 2003-255.</annotation>
    <section>
      <num>2-166-2-230</num>
      <heading>Reserved.</heading>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>ARTICLE</prefix>
    <num path-omit="true">V</num>
    <heading>FINANCE</heading>
    <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">8 <strong>Charter reference— </strong>Finances, Art. VII; contracts and bidding, Art. VIII.</annotation>
    <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Cross reference— </strong>Ordinances promising or guaranteeing payment of money for city, authorizing issuance of any bonds of city or any indebtedness of city or any contract or obligation assumed by city saved from repeal, <cite path="1-12|(1)">§ 1-12(1)</cite>; ordinances pertaining to annual budget or any appropriation saved from repeal, <cite path="1-12|(4)">§ 1-12(4)</cite>; public art fund, §<cite path="4-3">§ 4-3</cite>, 4-4; pensions, Ch. 17; public improvements, Ch. 20; taxation, Ch. 24.</annotation>
    <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>State Law reference— </strong>Municipal borrowing, F.S. § 166.101 et seq.; municipal finance and taxation, F.S. § 166.201 et seq.; financial matters pertaining to political subdivisions, F.S. Ch. 218.</annotation>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">1</num>
      <heading>GENERALLY</heading>
      <section>
        <num>2-231</num>
        <heading>Sureties of persons dealing with city to be licensed by state; premium of bonds of officials to be paid by city.</heading>
        <text>Whenever it may be necessary for any person to give or furnish to the city a bond for any purpose with surety, such surety shall be a surety or indemnity company licensed and authorized to do business with this state. Whenever such bond is an official bond of an officer or employee required by the Charter, the premium for such bond shall be paid by the city.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-561), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Charter reference— </strong>Bonds for officers and employees, § 6.04.</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-232</num>
        <heading>Annual postaudit.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>There shall be each year, except during a year in which the records of the city are audited by the state auditor general, a postaudit of all the books, records, inventories and reports of the director of finance, and of all officers and employees who receive and/or disburse public funds, conducted and performed by an independent certified public accountant appointed by the official with the approval of the city council. The term "independent certified public accountant" shall mean a person certified and licensed as a certified public accountant, wherein neither the person, firm, or corporation nor any member, officer, agent, or employee thereof shall have, during the period of his professional engagement or at the date of his report or during the period covered by the financial statement, any relationship with the city as officer, employee or accountant, in any manner over which the certified public accountant has performed accounting services. For purposes of <cite path="2-232">this section</cite>, "accounting services" shall mean preparing financial statements, including adjusting and closing the general books. Nothing contained in <cite path="2-232">this section</cite> shall preclude the certified public accountant from providing the city, for a fee or otherwise, with an accounting system formulation designed to improve the city's accounting capability. For purposes of <cite path="2-232">this section</cite>, the term "accounting system formulation" shall mean developing, designing and recommending to management plans, programs, procedures and methodologies to be used by management in carrying out its duties and responsibilities in a more effective and efficient way.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding any provisions contained in <cite path="2-232">this section</cite>, if federal auditing standards require that the independent public accountant have no business relationship with the city except for the performance of audits, then those federal programs covered by such regulations shall be audited in conformity with the appropriate federal regulations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to fail to comply with or to violate the provisions of <cite path="2-232">this section</cite>. The failure of the official or the city council to cause the audit to be made as provided in <cite path="2-232">this section</cite> shall be grounds for recall of such officers.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-562), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Charter reference— </strong>Audits, § 7.11.</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>State Law reference— </strong>Financial management and reporting requirements, F.S. §§ 166.241(1), 218.30 et seq.</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-233</num>
        <heading>Authority of city attorney and risk manager to dispose of claims against city.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The city attorney and/or his designee is hereby authorized to deny claims against the city without further approval of the city council when in his opinion:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>It is in the best interest of the city to do so; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A reasonable investigation has revealed that the claim is without merit.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The city attorney and/or his designee is hereby authorized to settle or pay claims against the city without further approval of the city council when, in his opinion:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>It is in the best interest of the city to do so;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>There is no substantial issue of liability involved; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The amount is no greater than twenty-five thousand dollars ($25,000.00).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The risk manager of the city and/or his designee is hereby authorized to settle or pay claims against the city without further approval of the city council when, in his opinion:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>It is in the best interest of the city to do so;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>There is no substantial issue of liability involved; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The amount is no greater than ten thousand dollars ($10,000.00).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-563), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-100, § 1, 4-20-06</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-234-2-255</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">2</num>
      <heading>CITY DEPOSITORIES</heading>
      <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">9 <strong>Charter reference— </strong>Depositories and disbursements, § 7.09.</annotation>
      <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>State Law reference— </strong>Municipal investments, F.S. § 166.261.</annotation>
      <section>
        <num>2-256</num>
        <heading>Qualified institutions; duty of director of finance.</heading>
        <text>Only banks or savings associations meeting all of the requirements of the Florida Security for Public Deposits Act, F.S. Ch. 280, and designated by the state treasurer as a qualified public depository may be designated a city depository. The director of finance shall be responsible for ensuring the status of those banks and savings associations designated as city depositories, and, once this status is verified, he may deposit city funds without the formal requirement of a depository agreement. He shall require each depository bank receiving any money as provided in <cite path="2-256">this section</cite> to provide him with a safekeeping receipt for a certificate of deposit or securities or validated receipt for such funds which he shall carefully preserve and keep and make available for inspection as provided by law.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, § 2(2-581), 9-28-89</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-257-2-275</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">3</num>
      <heading>PURCHASES AND CONTRACTS</heading>
      <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container">10 <strong>Editor's note—</strong> Ord. No. 95-109, §<cite path="1-5">§ 1-5</cite>, adopted May 25, 1995, amended Div. 3 to read as herein set out. See the Code Comparative Table.</annotation>
      <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Charter reference— </strong>Contracts and competitive bidding, § 8.04.</annotation>
      <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container"><strong>Cross reference— </strong>Ordinances promising or guaranteeing payment of money for the city and contracts or obligations assumed by the city saved from repeal, <cite path="1-12|(1)">§ 1-12(1)</cite>; public improvements, Ch. 20.</annotation>
      <section>
        <num>2-276</num>
        <heading>Approval, bidding for certain purchases and various contracts.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>All purchases by the city and all contracts for the furnishing to the city of supplies, printing, materials, equipment, machinery, appliances and other commodities, and services, including the repair of heavy equipment of the city (except those services which are professional, or highly technical or specialized), requiring an expenditure of one hundred thousand dollars ($100,000.00) or more shall be first approved by the city council upon recommendation of the mayor and made only upon a formal competitive bidding basis, which may include on-line procurements, after due advertisement for bids or qualifications for on-line procurement, as the case may be, as shall be prescribed by the city council.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The director of the purchasing department is authorized to make purchases requiring expenditures of less than one hundred thousand dollars ($100,000.00) without the approval of the city council.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The director of the purchasing department is bound and governed by the competitive bidding procedures as provided for in the City of Tampa's Purchasing Procedures Manual, 1992, as amended, on file in the office of the city clerk. The terms and conditions of said manual are hereby adopted by reference and shall have the full force and effect of law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>In the event of set-asides regarding the award of contracts for city purchases, awards and contracts to women and minority business enterprises (W/MBEs) as authorized by Chapter 26.5 of the <cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>, the competitive bidding requirement hereinabove set out shall be limited to the current list of certified W/MBEs.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 95-109, § 2, 5-25-95</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 96-168, § 1, 8-15-96</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2000-151, § 1, 6-8-00</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2002-1, § 1, 1-3-02</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-277</num>
        <heading>Approval, bidding for public improvement contracts.</heading>
        <text>Public improvement contracts, being all contracts for the furnishing to the city of labor and materials for the construction, reconstruction, alteration, repair and/or maintenance of public improvements shall be handled by the operating department except that smaller projects estimated to cost less then one hundred thousand dollars ($100,000.00) may be handled by the director of purchasing subject to the competitive bidding procedures set forth in the manual described in <cite path="2-276">section 2-276</cite> above.</text>
        <text>All public improvement contracts requiring an expenditure of one hundred thousand dollars ($100,000.00) or more shall be handled by the operating departments and shall be made only upon a competitive bid basis after plans and specifications have been prepared, are on file in the operating departments and, upon recommendation of the mayor, have been approved by the city council.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 95-109, § 2, 5-25-95</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2000-151, § 2, 6-8-00</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-274, § 1, 11-18-04</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-278</num>
        <heading>Manner and form of advertisements for bids and requests for qualifications for on-line procurements for certain purchases and contracts.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The following forms are prescribed for use by the purchasing department for the purpose of securing due advertisement for bids or requests for qualifications for on-line procurements, pursuant to <cite path="2-276">section 2-276</cite>, on all purchases by the city of supplies, printing, materials, equipment, machinery, appliances, and other commodities and services, including all contracts for the repair of heavy equipment, which require an expenditure of city funds of one hundred thousand dollars ($100,000.00) or more:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>
              <em>Invitation to bid.</em>
            </text>
            <text>Sealed bids for the furnishing of _______ will be received by the Director of Purchasing, City of Tampa, in her office until _______ a.m., _______, (Date), then and thereafter to be publicly opened and read. Bid documents are available at the Purchasing Department.</text>
            <text>Dated: _______, _______</text>
            <text>Director: _______</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>
              <em>Request for qualifications. (On-line procurement).</em>
            </text>
            <text>Sealed letters of interest and qualifications for the furnishing of _______ will be received by the Director of Purchasing, City of Tampa, in her office until _______ a.m., _______, (Date), then and thereafter to be publicly opened and read. Bid documents are available at the Purchasing Department.</text>
            <text>Dated: _______, _______</text>
            <text>Director: _______</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The form "invitation to bid" or "request for qualifications," as the case may be, provided for in <cite path="2-278|(a)">subsection (a)</cite> of <cite path="2-278">this section</cite> shall be published one (1) time at least five (5) days prior to the opening of bids or letters of interest and qualifications, as the case may be, in a newspaper of general circulation published in the city.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>For all items for which funds are budgeted, the director of purchasing is authorized and empowered to advertise for bids or requests for qualifications for on-line procurements in accordance with the provisions of <cite path="2-278">this section</cite> without further, additional or prior approval of the city council; however, the director shall attach and submit to the council along with the requested approval of the lowest responsible bid, the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>
              <em>In the case of an "invitation to bid:"</em>
            </text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>Copy of the newspaper advertisement "invitation to bid" showing the date that the advertisement was published and the name of the newspaper;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>A list of all bidders; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <text>A tabulation of all bids.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>
              <em>In the case of a "request for qualifications for on-line procurement:"</em>
            </text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>Copy of the newspaper advertisement "request for qualifications for on-line procurement" showing the date that the advertisement was published and the name of the newspaper;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>A list of all respondents to the "request for qualifications for on-line procurement;" and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <text>A tabulation of all price quotes submitted during the on-line procurement.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Nothing in <cite path="2-278">this section</cite> shall be construed as applying or relating to advertisements for bids or requests for qualifications for on-line procurements on projects, contracts, or purchases which, in whole or in part, involve the use of federal funds or bond money or which come under the city's women and minority business enterprises ordinance.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 95-109, § 3, 5-25-95</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2000-151, § 3, 6-8-00</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2002-1, § 2, 1-3-02</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-279</num>
        <heading>Approval of valid emergencies; competitive bidding and bond exemptions.</heading>
        <text>In case of valid emergencies for purchases or contracts as delineated in sections 2-276 and 2-277, the requirements of competitive bidding and the provision of an appropriate bond may be waived. The furnishing of labor and materials requiring an expenditure of less than fifty thousand dollars ($50,000.00) and of labor only regardless of the expenditure amount by be exempted from the requirement of an appropriate bond for public improvements and the maintenance of public facilities.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 95-109, § 4, 5-25-95</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-280</num>
        <heading>Certain work orders to be approved by city council.</heading>
        <text>Notwithstanding any other provisions of the <cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>, no work orders for the provision of professional services as defined in F.S. § 287.055, exceeding one hundred thousand dollars ($100,000.00) to any single provider or for any project shall be allowed or permitted with the city unless and until such work order shall first be approved by resolution passed by the city council.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 95-109, § 5, 5-25-95</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2020-21, § 2, 2-20-2020</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-281</num>
        <heading>On-line vendor (bidder) system.</heading>
        <text>The purchasing department maintains an on-line bidder system in the mainframe computer for all vendors (bidders) desiring to do business with the City of Tampa. To be placed in the computer system, vendors (bidders) must submit a completed vendor application to the purchasing department.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 96-168, § 2, 8-15-96</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-288, § 1, 11-6-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-282</num>
        <heading>Procurement protest procedures.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><em>Purpose.</em><cite path="2-282">This section</cite> shall govern any protest made by any actual bidder or proposer, who is allegedly aggrieved in connection with the issuance of a bid solicitation, proposal solicitation or pending award of any contract in any competitive process utilized by the City of Tampa for procurements of supplies, materials or services and construction of public improvements and has standing to protest under Florida law. Protests not complying with the provisions of <cite path="2-282">this section</cite> shall not be reviewed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><em>Time for filing a protest.</em> Protests shall only be accepted within the timeframes as stated herein. Any protest received outside of these timeframes shall not be considered. Protests shall be filed with the director of the soliciting department, either the director of purchasing or designee, or the director of contract administration or designee, which shall be specified in the solicitation by the city. For all solicitations with estimated expenditures of twenty-five thousand dollars ($25,000.00) or more, protests must be filed with the director of the soliciting department in writing within five (5) city business days after the city posts notice of intent to award by means which shall be specified in the solicitation by the city. For solicitations with estimated expenditures of less than twenty-five thousand dollars ($25,000.00), the protesting party shall bear the responsibility of ascertaining whether the city has made a decision of intent to award and of filing any protest within five (5) city business days of said decision. All protests must be received by the director of the soliciting department or designee by 4:30 p.m. on the date as specified above. Protests received after this timeframe will not be considered. It is the responsibility of the bidder(s) or proposer(s) to review posted notices from the city in order to file a protest in a timely manner. Standing to protest is limited to parties that have submitted bids or proposals.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><em>Required form of protest.</em> All protests shall be in writing and state that the bidder or proposer is submitting a formal notice of protest. Failure to follow the required form of protest shall be just cause for rejection of the protest. Delivery by certified or registered mail, email, fax (original copy sent immediately following), or hand delivered to the director of the soliciting department or designee is acceptable. Protests shall be date and time stamped upon receipt and if hand-delivered a receipt shall be issued to the protesting party stating the date and time the protest was filed. A party protesting may be represented by legal counsel at its own expense. A protesting party shall bear all costs of the protest other than salary and personnel costs of city employees. No documentation may be submitted after filing of the protest. The notice of protest shall include the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The name, postal and email address, telephone and facsimile numbers of the party protesting;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The city bid or proposal number and title;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>A concise statement indicating the grounds and evidence, including facts, rules, regulations, statutes and constitutional provisions, the factual and legal basis, upon which the protest is based, with inclusion of all supporting documentation. Grounds not specifically stated in writing shall be waived;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>A statement of the specific ruling or relief requested; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Signature by an authorized agent of the party protesting.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text><em>Rights of other interested parties to protest procedures.</em> Interested parties, other than the protesting party and the city, which will be directly affected by the resolution of the protest, and have legal standing, shall have the right to intervene in such protest proceeding by providing written documentation related to the protested solicitation. Said interested parties shall bear the responsibility of determining whether a protest has been filed with the city. Any documentation submitted by these interested parties must be filed with the director of the soliciting department within five (5) city business days of receipt of the protest by the city. Said documentation must be received by the director of the soliciting department or designee by 4:30 p.m. on the date as specified above. Documentation received after this timeframe will not be considered. Delivery by certified or registered mail, email, fax (original copy sent immediately following), or hand delivered to the director of the soliciting department or designee is acceptable. Said documentation shall be date and time stamped upon receipt and if hand-delivered a receipt shall be issued to the party stating the date and time the said documentation was filed. Any said interested party may be represented by legal counsel at its own expense. Any said interested party shall bear all costs of its submissions to the city. The notice of protest shall be made available to said interested parties upon a written request for same. Documentation shall include the following information:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The name, postal and email address, telephone and facsimile numbers of the party intervening;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The city bid or proposal number and title;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>A concise statement indicating the grounds and evidence, including facts, rules, regulations, statutes and constitutional provisions, upon which the intervention is based, with inclusion of all supporting documentation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>A statement of the specific ruling or relief requested;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Signature by an authorized agent of the interested party.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Determination of protest.</em>
          </text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>When a notice of protest is received, the director of the soliciting department shall serve as a review officer to evaluate the submissions by interested parties, including the notice of protest, the documentation from any other interested party, and documentation related to the protested solicitation provided to the director of the soliciting department from that department.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The decision by the review officer will be based on written submissions only.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The review officer shall issue a written decision to uphold or reject the protest, containing the basis of the decision within fifteen (15) city business days after submission of documentation by interested parties has been filed with the director of the soliciting department.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>If additional time is required to review the protest, interested parties shall be notified. In no event shall the additional time exceed more than ten (10) additional city business days.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Appeal of decision.</em>
          </text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>If a protest is denied, the protesting party may file a request for appeal with the director of the soliciting department. The appeal shall be submitted in writing and sent by certified or registered mail, or hand-delivered to the director of the soliciting department or designee. Appeals will be date and time stamped upon receipt and if hand-delivered, a receipt will be issued to the appealing party stating the date and time the appeal was filed.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The appeal must be filed with the director of the soliciting department within three (3) city business days of the issuance of the decision of the review officer. Any appeal received outside of this timeframe will not be considered.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>At the filing of the appeal, the appealing party shall post with the director of the soliciting department, a security in the form of a bond (in a form, and with such terms, approved by the director) payable to the City of Tampa in an amount equal to ten (10) percent of the total bid or proposal amount, or the value of the solicitation as estimated by the city prior to a solicitation's opening date, or twenty thousand dollars ($20,000.00), whichever is less. The surety issuing the bond must be authorized to do business in the State of Florida and be in compliance with the Florida Insurance Code. Any bond submitted shall have a duly executed power of attorney attached. In lieu of a bond, the city may accept an irrevocable letter of credit, cashier's or certified check, or money order in the above amount (in a form, and with such terms as approved by the director). Noncompliance with this requirement, in whole or in part, shall be deemed to be a waiver by the protesting party of the right to appeal. Said security shall be designated and held for the payment of any costs that may be levied against the appealing party. If the appeal is successful, the posted security shall be refunded in full.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The request for appeal must include the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>The name, postal and email address, telephone and facsimile numbers of the party appealing;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>The city bid or proposal number and title;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <text>A concise statement indicating the grounds and evidence, including facts, rules, regulations, statutes and constitutional provisions, the factual and legal basis, upon which the protest is based, with inclusion of all supporting documentation. New grounds or evidence not previously set forth in the written protest that reasonably could have been raised when the protest was initially submitted will not be considered;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>d.</num>
              <text>A statement of the specific ruling or relief requested; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>e.</num>
              <text>Signature by an authorized agent of the party appealing.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Notice of hearing date and hearing.</text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>Upon filing of a timely request for appeal, the director of the soliciting department shall notify the city attorney and forward the request for appeal within three (3) days of receipt of the request to the procurement appeals hearing officer so designated by the city attorney pursuant to <cite path="2-282|(j)">subsection (j)</cite>.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>The procurement appeals hearing officer shall set a hearing date not more than ten (10) city business days from the date of receipt of the request for appeal from the director of the soliciting department. The procurement appeals hearing officer shall cause notice of the hearing date, time and location to be served upon all parties who will be directly affected by the resolution of the appeal by certified mail, return receipt requested. The procurement appeals hearing officer may extend the deadline for completion of the hearing upon written petition for good cause shown; however, such extension shall not exceed an additional five (5) city business days.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <text>The procurement appeals hearing officer shall conduct a de novo hearing. The burden of proof shall rest with the appealing party. The standard of proof shall be whether the decision by the review officer was clearly erroneous, arbitrary or capricious, fraudulent, or otherwise without basis in fact or law. Any decision shall be based on substantial competent evidence. The hearing shall begin with a statement by the procurement appeals hearing officer of the rules and procedures of the hearing, followed by a general statement of the facts by the director of the soliciting department. Representatives of the appealing party, limited to its owners, officers, employees and/or legal counsel, will then be required to present its case. Those parties, other than the appealing party, who have standing and will be directly affected by the resolution of the appeal, limited to its owners, officers, employees and/or legal counsel, will be given an opportunity to be heard and to present information, which will be followed by a statement and presentation of information from the director of the soliciting department and its legal counsel. Party presentations shall be limited to two (2) hours per party. All examinations and cross-examinations shall be conducted by the procurement appeals hearing officer. All parties shall be provided a fair and impartial hearing. Strict rules of evidence shall not apply. Hearsay evidence may be admissible, and used to supplement or explain other evidence, but shall not be sufficient in itself to support a finding unless it would be admissible over objections in civil actions.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>d.</num>
              <text>Decision and notice of decision. The procurement appeals hearing officer shall, within seven (7) days of the hearing, make a written decision on the appeal, which decision shall affirm or deny the decision by the review officer. The decision shall be sent to all parties by registered mail and shall set forth the reasons for the decision.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>e.</num>
              <text>Recovery of costs by the city. If at the appeals hearing the city prevails, the procurement appeals hearing officer shall assess against the appealing party reasonable costs incurred by the city in convening the hearing, including the costs and fees for the procurement appeals hearing officer. Such costs of the hearing shall be paid to the city within five (5) business days after receipt by the appealing party of the decision upholding the decision of the review officer. Any costs not fully discharged by the amount of the appealing party's bond shall be paid by the appealing party. Failure to timely pay said costs shall result in the appealing party being suspended from the city's vendor list until such payment is made.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>f.</num>
              <text>The decision by the procurement appeals hearing officer under <cite path="2-282">this section</cite> shall be final and binding on the city and shall thereafter represent the position of the city.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Protest remedies.</em>
          </text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>If a protest is upheld, the city, at its sole discretion, may do one (1) or more of the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>Cancel the solicitation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>Award in part.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <text>Re-compete the procurement.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>In no event will a contract be automatically awarded to a protesting party if the protest is upheld.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Nothing herein shall prevent the city, at its sole discretion, from providing for an alternative remedy which is in the best interest of the city and in compliance with any applicable law.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text><em>Stay of contract award.</em> In the event of a timely protest and/or appeal, the city will not proceed further with the award of the bid or proposal, unless the director of the soliciting department sets forth in writing particular facts and circumstances which require the continuance of the solicitation or contract award process without delay in order to avoid an immediate and serious danger to the public health, safety, or welfare.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text><em>Communication during pendency of solicitation.</em> During any solicitation period, including any protest and/or appeal, no contact with city officers or employees, other than with the individuals specifically identified in the solicitation, the director of the soliciting department or the legal department, is permitted from any bidder or proposer. Such communication shall result in an automatic disqualification for selection in the pending solicitation and any subsequent city solicitations for a period of six (6) months, no matter the outcome of the solicitation or any protest and/or appeal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text><em>Procurement appeals hearing officers.</em> The city attorney, on behalf of the city, shall negotiate contracts with two (2) or more procurement appeals hearing officers who shall be assigned on a rotating basis in alphabetical order. If a procurement appeals hearing officer is unable to accept a case because of a conflict, time constraints, or any other reason, the case shall be assigned to the next procurement appeals hearing officer in said order. The officers shall possess the educational background and public or private employment experience to examine facts and apply legal principles, including, but not limited to experience with evidentiary and civil procedure issues, to controversies regarding procurement of goods and services, public improvement construction, professional and consultant services, and information technology in the municipal government sector. No city employee, city official, or anyone who owns any financial interest in any business entity which does business with the city shall be considered. Each officer shall hold hearings upon appeals of procurement protest decisions which shall be held in a municipal building and shall be open to the public. Administrative services, as may be required by the officers, shall be furnished by city departments. The procurement appeals hearing officer shall have the authority to review and determine any appeal by an aggrieved party from determination of a procurement protest by a review officer as authorized in <cite path="2-282">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text><em>Filing documents and computation of time.</em> All dates, time frames and deadlines shall be calculated as city business days. A city business day shall mean 8:00 a.m. to 5:00 p.m. Monday through Friday, with the exception of city holidays. In all instances any document required to be transmitted by a certain date must be received in the required office by 4:30 p.m. Postmark by the required date in [is] not sufficient. Transmittal by fax, email or other electronic means may be accepted. However, it shall be the responsibility of the party transmitting the documents(s) to ensure that the document(s) were received, and the transmitting party shall bear any risk of an interruption or failure in the electronic transmission.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2010-92, § 2, 7-29-2010</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2012-67, § 2, 6-28-2012</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-283</num>
        <heading>Integrity of public contracting and purchasing; disqualification of certain persons and entities; etc.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>In recognition that the preservation of the integrity of public contracting, purchasing and other transaction of the business of the city is vital and is a matter of great public interest, the council determines and declares that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The procedures of the city for determining with whom the city transacts business exist to secure for the public the benefits of free, fair, and open competition among those persons or entities seeking to transact such business.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The opportunity to bid on public entity contracts or to supply goods and services to the city or to otherwise transact business with the city is a privilege, not a right.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>In order to preserve the integrity of the public contracting and purchasing process, the privilege of transacting business with the city should be denied to persons involved in public entity crimes or certain other crimes or activities involving fraud, deceit or misrepresentation ("disqualifying activity"), with the allowance for waiver of same in exceptional circumstances and only after review and approval by the city council or public contract review board, established in the manner set forth herein.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>It is the intent of <cite path="2-283">this section</cite> to provide sufficient authority to the city, its departments and agencies, to ensure the integrity of public contracting and purchasing.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>It is the further intent that any contract or business relationship with the city entered into in violation of <cite path="2-283">this section</cite> shall not be void, but that the contract or business relationship be voidable pursuant to written notice by the city official with the authority to enter into such contract or business relationship or the mayor to the extent within the mayor's purview under the Charter of the city or the city council to the extent within its purview under the Charter of the city. The termination or voiding of any such contract or business relationship and the disqualification of any person or entity from doing business with the city shall be subject to review by the appellate body established hereunder, with such appellate body's determination subject to review by writ of certiorari to the Circuit Court in and for Hillsborough County, as and when provided below.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Unless the application of <cite path="2-283">this section</cite> shall be waived by resolution or ordinance by city council, the city shall not enter into a contract or transact business:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>With an individual who, personally or through an affiliated entity, as that term is defined herein, has been found to have engaged in disqualifying activity within the past five (5) years by a local, state or federal court or found to have committed, participated in or fostered any disqualifying activity as determined by a local, state or federal court or as determined pursuant to any administrative, regulatory, licensure or investigative process;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>With an individual who has been indicated or against whom an information has been issued with respect to a "public entity crime";</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>With a corporation, partnership or other business entity ("disqualified entity") whose affairs and policies are legally or factually controlled by an individual (either directly or through intermediaries) who would be disqualified from doing business with the city under (b)(1) or (2) above ("disqualified person") or with any such entity providing consideration to such a disqualified person;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>With a corporation, partnership or other business entity which is an affiliated entity of a disqualified entity or disqualified person. An affiliated entity, or the transferee of any person or business entity disqualified from doing business with the city under this <cite path="2-283|(b)">subsection (b)</cite> or any subsequent transferee pursuant to a transfer, sale or assignment made in whole or in part for the purpose of avoiding the sanctions of <cite path="2-283">this section</cite> shall be a disqualified entity hereunder.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In the awarding of any contract or grant, or in the providing of any guaranty of payment (whether by direct guaranty, promise to pay, administration of a grant or fund or assignment of a right to receive payment) or other action constituting the transaction of business with the city, the determination of the "lowest responsive responsible bidder" shall not simply be the lowest bidder, but also shall include but not be limited to the following factors:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The bidder's skill, judgment, experience, reputation for satisfactory work, financial soundness and other considerations relative to the quality of the goods or services to be provided, the terms of their delivery and the likelihood of any attendant expense and delay;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The conviction or findings of participation by any individual or affiliated entity in any crime, civil proceeding or activities described in <cite path="2-283|(b)">subsection (b)</cite> above;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Any determination reflecting adversely on the integrity of such an individual or affiliated entity as may be evident from the issuance of any indictment, sanction, administrative determination, licensure, revocation or warning, regulatory action or civil proceeding related thereto;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Any other act or action, whether determined in a court, administrative proceeding, professional licensure hearing, investigation, or regulatory review which is determined to constitute a failure to meet any requirement of law, ordinance, rule or policy which otherwise reflects on the bidders compliance with applicable laws, rules, regulations and ordinances governing the conduct of its business;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Experience of delays, lack of coordination with any related work or service or poor performance on prior contracts with the city, which have been documented.</text>
          </para>
          <text>All officers or employees of the city awarding any contract or approving any payment or guaranty by the city, shall apply these "lowest responsive responsible bidder" criteria in a fair and legal manner and not arbitrarily or capriciously.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Any transfer of all or part of the ownership of an entity otherwise disqualified from public contracting, purchasing or transacting business with the city hereunder made at least in part for the purpose of avoiding or evading the requirements of subsections (b) and (c), shall be considered a sham transaction and shall result in a transferee being subject to the same requirements, limitations or provisions as would apply to the transferor hereunder. Any determination of disqualification from doing business with the city under this provision shall result in a written finding setting forth the basis therefor and shall be delivered to the party so disqualified. The notified party may contest the finding with the official or with the appellate body established herein. Such appeal shall be a hearing de novo.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>As used in <cite path="2-283">this section</cite>:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text><em>Affiliated entity</em> means an entity under the control or subject to the ownership (whether legal, beneficial or equitable) or which provides compensation or other thing of value to any disqualified persons or disqualified entity. The term "affiliate" includes any entity which has any officer, director, executive, partner, shareholder, employee, member, or agent who is a disqualified person, who owns or benefits therefrom or is active in the management of that entity or receives consideration therefrom. The ownership by one (1) person of shares constituting a controlling interest in another person or entity, or a pooling of equipment or income among persons when not for fair market value under an arm's length agreement, shall be a prima facie case that one (1) person or entity controls another person or entity.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text><em>Business relationship</em> shall mean the relationship, arrangement, agreement or contract established with the city for goods, work, services or products which the city either: (i) pays directly; (ii) guarantees payment; (iii) assigns the right to receive payment; or (iv) pays through or on behalf of another pursuant to a grant, fund or program administered by the city.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text><em>City</em> means the City of Tampa and all its departments and agencies.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text><em>Convicted</em> or <em>conviction</em> means a finding of guilt of a disqualifying activity, with or without final adjudication of guilt, in any federal, state or local court of record relating to charges brought by indictment or information as a result of a jury verdict, nonjury trial, or entry of a plea of guilty or nolo contendere.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text><em>Found</em> or <em>finding</em> means a determination, finding of fact or conclusion of a fact finder, court, administrative body, licensing board or other regulatory agency, tribunal or organization pursuant to a process subject to reasonable safeguards intended to assure the accuracy thereof.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text><em>Owned</em> or <em>benefiting from</em> means a twenty (20) percent or more ownership or the receipt of payments or other items of value whether received as employee, consultant, independent contractor or other relationship directly, or through an affiliated entity or related person.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text><em>Public entity crime</em> means a violation of any city, state or federal law by a person with respect to and directly related to the transaction of business with any public entity or with an agency or political subdivision of any other state or with the United States, including, but not limited to, any bid or contract for goods or services, any lease for real property, or any contract for the construction or repair of a public building or public work or a contract which is paid or for which payment is made in whole or in part from public funds, involving antitrust, fraud, theft, bribery, collusion, racketeering, conspiracy, or material misrepresentation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text><em>Transacting business</em> means the entering into a contract with the city or any part thereof or entering into an agreement under which payments or the guaranty of payment is made by the city directly or to a third party who will make payment for such a contract whether from city funds or pursuant to the grant or other source of payment administered, reviewed, managed or approved by the city.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>The city council or the public contract review board, if constituted as provided herein, shall overturn the improper application hereof, or otherwise repeal or waive any determination of disqualification made pursuant to the provisions of <cite path="2-283">this section</cite>, if it is determined that there is very little risk to the free, fair and open competition to transact business with the city after considering all relevant factors including but not limited to:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The nature and details of the disqualifying activity.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Whether the disqualifying activity was committed by the individual, corporation, partnership or other entity seeking the contract or business relationship with the city, or by an individual in factual control or by a direct or an indirect owner or party benefited therefrom.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The degree of culpability of the individual, corporation, partnership or other business entity seeking the contract.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The promptness of the payment of any damages or penalty or other remedial action agreed upon or assessed in connection with the disqualifying activity.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The level of cooperation with any state, federal, regulatory or licensure investigation or prosecution at issue; provided that a good faith exercise of any constitutional, statutory, or other right during any portion of the investigation or prosecution of any crime shall not be considered a lack or cooperation.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>The disassociation (or failure to disassociate) from any disqualified person or disqualified entity.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>The commitment, if any, to self-policing or other curative measures to prevent any further disqualifying activity.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>The reinstatement or grant of clemency by any jurisdiction, agency or authority in relation to any disqualifying activity.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(9)</num>
            <text>The relationship of the disqualifying activity to the provision of work or procurement of goods and services sought.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(10)</num>
            <text>The subsequent demonstration of good citizenship by the individual, corporation, partnership or other business entity seeking the contract.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(11)</num>
            <text>The cost to the city or third party beneficiaries in voiding a contract or of refusing to waive the provisions.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(12)</num>
            <text>The determination that any finding on which the exclusion from doing business with the city is based is not reliable, is no longer applicable (as in the case of the acquittal or dismissal of charges) or otherwise do not pose a sufficient concern to the integrity of the public contracting or procurement process.</text>
          </para>
          <text>Any decision so made shall be appealable by writ of certiorari filed with the Circuit Court in and for Hillsborough County within thirty (30) days after the delivery of any written determination by the city council or public contract review board.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>A public contract review board may be set up to carry out the review, approval, waiver and appeal procedures of <cite path="2-283">this section</cite>. If so, it shall be determined by the city council that it wishes to set up such a board rather than serving in that capacity itself. If the city council passes such an ordinance or resolution the board shall consist of three (3) members, two (2) of which shall be appointed by the mayor and the other by city council and all of whom shall be experienced in contract and procurement matters. The board so constituted shall conduct any such review, approval, waiver or appeal pursuant to the requirements set forth herein and shall provide a fair and open hearing of all matters brought before it including all relevant evidence. It shall meet as needed to review such matters to be brought before it and shall have procedures and policies for receiving information and evidence as other similar city boards and as appropriate to its task.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>Except for the appellate rights provided herein, no party shall have standing to enforce <cite path="2-283">this section</cite> in a court of competent jurisdiction except the city.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The director of the purchasing department or other city representative designated by the mayor shall maintain a list of disqualified persons or disqualified entities and provide same to other city agencies and departments for the purpose of complying with <cite path="2-283">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-134, § 1, 5-27-04</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-284</num>
        <heading>Bidder's criminal history screening practices.</heading>
        <text>All competitive procurement methods utilized by the city shall contain a provision addressing whether the bidder has criminal history screening practices similar in nature to the practices contained in Chapter 12, Article VI, <cite>City of Tampa Code</cite> of Ordinances.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2015-49, § 1, 4-16-15</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-285-2-325</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>ARTICLE</prefix>
    <num path-omit="true">VI</num>
    <heading>RESERVED</heading>
    <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container">11 <strong>Editor's note—</strong> Ord. No. 2003-255, § 1, adopted Oct. 2, 2003, amended the title of Art. VI from "Board of Ethics; <cite path="2-500">Code of Ethics for City Officials</cite> and Employees" to "Reserved." Sections 2 and 3 of said ordinance renumbered former provisions of Art. VI as current sections of new Art. VIII and repealed others. For a detailed analysis of inclusion of Ord. No. 2003-255 see the Code Comparative Table.</annotation>
    <section>
      <num>2-326-2-400</num>
      <heading>Reserved.</heading>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>ARTICLE</prefix>
    <num path-omit="true">VII</num>
    <heading>CIVIL EMERGENCIES</heading>
    <section>
      <num>2-401</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>For the purposes of <cite path="2">this chapter</cite>, the following words are defined:</text>
      <text><em>Disaster</em> means the occurrence or imminent threat of widespread or severe damage, injury or loss of life or property resulting from any natural or man-made cause. These can include, but are not limited to, fire, flood, hurricane, wind, thunderstorm, tornado, hazardous material spill, epidemic, air contamination, critical material shortage, infestation, act of terrorism, cyber attack, explosion, radiological dispersion or other major incident requiring emergency action to avert danger or damage.</text>
      <text><em>Emergency management</em> means all those activities and measures undertaken by or on behalf of the city, designed:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>To minimize the effect upon persons and property of natural or man-made disasters;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>To deal with the immediate emergency conditions created by natural or man-made disasters; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>To effectuate emergency repairs to, or emergency restoration of, vital public utilities and facilities destroyed or damaged by natural or man-made disasters.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 91-188, § 2, 10-3-91</annotation>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2009-96, § 8, 7-16-09</annotation>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container"><strong>Editor's note— </strong>Ord. No. 2009-96, § 8, adopted July 16, 2009, changed the title of <cite path="2-401">§ 2-401</cite> from "Declaration of a state of local emergency; duration; alteration and rescission" to read as herein set out.</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2-402</num>
      <heading>Declaration of a state of local emergency; duration; alteration and rescission.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A state of local emergency shall be declared by executive order of the mayor if the mayor finds that an emergency, as defined in F.S. § 252.34, has occurred in the city or that the threat thereof is imminent. All executive orders issued under this article shall indicate the nature of the emergency, the area or areas threatened, and the conditions which have brought the emergency about or which make possible its termination. The executive order shall be promptly disseminated by means calculated to bring its contents to the attention of the general public; and, unless the circumstances attendant upon the emergency prevent or impede such filing, the order shall be filed promptly with the city clerk's office.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The duration of each state of local emergency declared is seven (7) days; it may be extended, as necessary, in seven (7) day increments by executive order.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Any state of local emergency declared may be altered during the continued or threatened existence of a state of local emergency, or rescinded, in the event that the emergency conditions cease to exist, by the issuance of a subsequent executive order(s).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>In the event a state of local emergency declared pursuant to <cite path="2-402">this section</cite> has been in effect continuously for more than thirty (30) days, and in the event a state or federal state of emergency is not also in effect, the mayor shall appear before city council at its next regular meeting to present the reasons for further continuance of the state of local emergency. If upon presentation of the mayor, the city council determines emergency conditions exist, the city council may extend the local state of emergency by resolution of the council. If upon presentation by the mayor, city council finds that emergency conditions no longer exist, city council may terminate the local state of emergency by resolution of the council. The mayor shall retain the authority to continue to extend any state of local emergency, pursuant to subsections 2-402(b) and (c), in seven-day increments in excess of thirty (30) days when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A declared state or federal state of emergency continues to exist;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>City council has not yet acted pursuant to this <cite path="2-402|(d)">subsection (d)</cite>;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>City council has acted to extend the local state of emergency pursuant to this <cite path="2-402|(d)">subsection (d)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2009-96, § 9, 7-16-09</annotation>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2009-167, §§ 2, 3, 12-3-09</annotation>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container"><strong>Editor's note— </strong>Ord. No. 2009-96, §§ 2 and 9, adopted July 16, 2009, repealed the former <cite path="2-402">§ 2-402</cite> and enacted a new <cite path="2-402">§ 2-402</cite> as set out herein. The former <cite path="2-402">§ 2-402</cite> pertained to emergency management powers of the mayor, and derived from Ord. No. 91-188, § 2, 10-3-91. See also the Code Comparative Table.</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2-403</num>
      <heading>Emergency management powers of the mayor.</heading>
      <text>Upon declaration of a state of local emergency, the mayor, in addition to any other powers conferred upon the mayor by law, City of Tampa Charter or city ordinance, has the following power and authority:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To direct and compel the evacuation of all or part of the population from any stricken or threatened area within the city if he deems this action necessary for the preservation of life or other emergency mitigation, response, or recovery.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>To waive the procedures and formalities otherwise required of the city by law or ordinance pertaining to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Performance of public work and taking whatever prudent action is necessary to ensure the health, safety, and welfare of the community;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Entering into contracts;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Incurring obligations;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Employment of permanent and temporary workers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>Utilization of volunteer workers;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>f.</num>
          <text>Rental of equipment;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>g.</num>
          <text>Acquisition and distribution, with or without compensation, of supplies, materials, and facilities; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>h.</num>
          <text>Appropriation and expenditure of public funds.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>Request emergency assistance and resources from higher levels of government, other local governments and/or other agencies, in accordance with the State of Florida Comprehensive Emergency Management Plan and/or the Statewide Mutual Aid Agreement and/or in accordance with the needs of the city and the resources available.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2009-96, § 10, 7-16-09</annotation>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container"><strong>Editor's note— </strong>Ord. No. 2009-96, §§ 3 and 10, adopted July 16, 2009, repealed the former <cite path="2-403">§ 2-403</cite> and enacted a new <cite path="2-403">§ 2-403</cite> as set out herein. The former <cite path="2-403">§ 2-403</cite> pertained to specific restrictions authorized and exemptions, and derived from Ord. No. 91-188, § 2, 10-3-91. See also the Code Comparative Table.</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2-404</num>
      <heading>Specific restrictions authorized; exemptions.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>During the existence of a declared state of local emergency, the mayor may impose by executive order any or all of the following restrictions:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Prohibit or regulate the purchase, sale, transfer or possession of explosives, combustibles, dangerous weapons of any kind (except firearms which may be restricted by F.S. § 870.044), or alcoholic beverages;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Prohibit or regulate any special event, demonstration, parade, march, vigil or participation therein from taking place on any of the public rights-of-way or upon any public property;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Prohibit or regulate the sale or use of gasoline, kerosene, naphtha or any other explosive or flammable fluids or substances altogether, except by delivery into a tank properly affixed to an operable motor vehicle, bike, scooter, boat, or airplane and necessary for the propulsion thereof;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Prohibit or regulate the participation in or carrying on of any business activity, and prohibit or regulate the keeping open of places of business, places of entertainment and any other place of public assembly;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Prohibit or regulate travel upon any public street, highway or upon any other public property. Persons in search of medical assistance, food or other commodity or service necessary to sustain the well being of themselves or their families or some member thereof may be excepted from such prohibition or regulation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>A curfew upon all or any portion of the city thereby prohibiting persons from being on public streets, highways, parks or other public places during the hours which the curfew is in effect;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Prohibit state and/or local business licensees, vendors, merchants and any person operating a retail business from charging more than the normal average price for any goods, materials or services sold during a declared state of local emergency, except that the normal average price for any merchandise may be increased, but only to the degree that the maximum increase in retail price shall be a percentage less than or equal to the amount representative of the average mark-up percent between wholesale and average retail price for any merchandise during the thirty-day period immediately preceding the declared state of local emergency. The normal average price as used herein is defined to be that price at which similar merchandise, or services, has been sold during the thirty (30) days immediately preceding the declaration of a state of local emergency;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>Prohibit any person, firm, or corporation from using the fresh water supplied by the city for any purpose other than cooking, drinking or bathing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The executive order of the mayor may exempt, from all or part of such restrictions, physicians, nurses and ambulance operators performing medical services, on-duty employees of hospitals and other medical facilities, on-duty military personnel, bona fide members of the news media, personnel of public utilities maintaining essential public services, city authorized or requested firemen, law enforcement officers and personnel and such other classes of persons as may be essential to the preservation of public order and immediately necessary to serve safety, health and welfare needs of the people within the city.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2009-96, § 11, 7-16-09</annotation>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2015-90, § 1, 8-27-2015</annotation>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container"><strong>Editor's note— </strong>Ord. No. 2009-96, §§ 4 and 11, adopted July 16, 2009, repealed the former <cite path="2-404">§ 2-404</cite> and enacted a new <cite path="2-404">§ 2-404</cite> as set out herein. The former <cite path="2-404">§ 2-404</cite> pertained to evacuation levels established, and derived from Ord. No. 91-188, § 2, 10-3-91 and Ord. No. 93-92, § 1, 7-15-93. See also the Code Comparative Table.</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2-405</num>
      <heading>Evacuation levels established; specific restrictions authorized.</heading>
      <text>The evacuation levels of the city are hereby established as designated upon the Hillsborough County Evacuation Map, 1993, as now or hereafter revised, on file or to be filed in the office of the city clerk; and such map and all notations, references or other information shown thereon shall be as much a part of <cite path="2-405">this section</cite> as if such information set forth on such map were fully described and set out herein.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2009-96, § 12, 7-16-09</annotation>
        <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container"><strong>Editor's note— </strong>Ord. No. 2009-96, §§ 5 and 12, adopted July 16, 2009, repealed the former <cite path="2-405">§ 2-405</cite> and enacted a new <cite path="2-405">§ 2-405</cite> as set out herein. The former <cite path="2-405">§ 2-405</cite> pertained to penalties, and derived from Ord. No. 91-188, § 2, 10-3-91. See also the Code Comparative Table.</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2-406</num>
      <heading>Emergency operations center.</heading>
      <text>The City of Tampa will maintain a hardened emergency operations center (herein "EOC") to provide standard local coordination and control of emergency, special event, or disaster response and relief operations for up to a twenty-four (24) hour-per-day basis, if necessary. The EOC will be equipped with the necessary computers, redundant communication devices, maps, displays, audio visual technology, status and situation boards, plans and procedures and will be supported by appropriate city emergency management personnel. The EOC will be managed by the director of emergency management and/or its emergency coordinator in accordance with the National Incident Management System. The EOC will be staffed with senior city officials and support organization representatives.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>EOC staff will exercise appropriate authority over all emergency operations from or through the center in the event of a disaster or emergency including, declaring the onset and/or termination of a disaster or emergency.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The city's EOC will serve as the city's command center for executive leadership and direction and provide for the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>To control and coordinate actions generated as result of orders from the executive policy group.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Provide direction and support to the disaster incident commander in the field.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Arrange for and deploy logistical resources that exceed the capabilities or purview of a single city department.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Initiate and coordinate recovery activities to meet the requirements that will follow the disaster and so that the public can receive all eligible assistance, allowing the city can return to a state of normalcy at the earliest time.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>Coordinate and release disaster related public information.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2009-96, § 13, 7-16-09</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2-407</num>
      <heading>Continuity of operations; continuity of government.</heading>
      <text>The city shall maintain, through the Office of Emergency Management and Homeland Security, a viable continuity of operations plan that addresses the continuity of critical, essential and emergency functions performed by the City of Tampa to its citizens and visitors in the event of a natural or man-made disasters that diminishes, threatens or incapacitates one (1) or many departments of city government or the city government as a whole.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>To maintain a viable COOP capability, each City of Tampa department's plan shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>a.</num>
          <text>Be maintained at a high level of readiness.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>b.</num>
          <text>Be capable of implementation both with and without warning.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>c.</num>
          <text>Be operational no later than twelve (12) hours after activation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>d.</num>
          <text>Require that operations must be maintained for up to thirty (30) days.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>e.</num>
          <text>Take maximum advantage of existing agency field infrastructures.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2009-96, § 14, 7-16-09</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>2-408-2-499</num>
      <heading>Reserved.</heading>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>ARTICLE</prefix>
    <num path-omit="true">VIII</num>
    <heading>CITY OF TAMPA ETHICS CODE</heading>
    <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container">12 <strong>Editor's note—</strong> Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, adopted Oct. 2, 2003, amended the title of Art. VIII from "Lobbying" to "<cite path="2-500">City of Tampa Ethics Code</cite>." Said ordinance also renumbered former <cite path="2-500">§ 2-500</cite> as <cite path="2-580">§ 2-580</cite>. Additionally, provisions of former Art. VI have been renumbered and amended as current sections in this Art. VIII. See the Code Comparative Table for a detailed analysis of Ord. No. 2003-255.</annotation>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">1</num>
      <heading>GENERALLY</heading>
      <section>
        <num>2-500</num>
        <heading>Title.</heading>
        <text>The provisions of this Article VIII shall be collectively referred to as "The <cite path="2-500">City of Tampa Ethics Code</cite>" or "city ethics code."</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-501</num>
        <heading>Purpose and legislative intent.</heading>
        <text>[JACKSONVILLE] It is declared to be the policy of the City of Tampa that all officers and employees of the city are public servants of the people and hold their positions for the benefit of the public. These public servants shall perform efficiently and faithfully their duties under the laws of the federal, state, and local governments. Such officers and employees shall strive to meet the highest standards of ethics consistent with <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite>, regardless of personal considerations, recognizing that maintaining the respect of the people must be their foremost concern. <cite path="2-500">This Code</cite> shall serve not only as a basis for discipline of public servants who violate these provisions, but also as an aspirational guide for conduct.</text>
        <text>Various provisions from state and local law have been created and adapted to guide the ethical behavior of local public servants. <cite path="2-500">This Code</cite> coordinates existing laws, adds new provisions outlining guidelines for appropriate behavior, and includes new substantive provisions which impose higher standards and expectations on public servants. Although the people of Tampa have learned from and responded to past mistakes, there should be an aspiration to much higher standards.</text>
        <text>Ethics is defined as the study of the general nature of morals and moral choices to be made by the individual in his or her relationships with others. Ethics is more than avoidance of criminal behavior. It is a commitment for public servants to take individual responsibility in creating a government that has the trust and respect of its citizens. There needs to be a proactive approach in strengthening the emphasis on ethics and in guiding city officers and employees in upholding them. To preserve and maintain the integrity of responsible government and its decision-making process, the City of Tampa believes it is necessary that the identity, activities and expenditures of certain persons who engage in efforts to influence officers and employees of the city on matters within their official cognizance, either by direct communication or by solicitation of others to engage in such efforts, be publicly and regularly disclosed. The provisions and requirements of <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> shall apply to every person who attempts to influence government action, unless such person is clearly exempt herefrom by an express provision hereof.</text>
        <text>With the above in mind, the City of Tampa hereby adopts the following goals for the city ethics program:</text>
        <text>• Promulgate and implement a comprehensive approach to ethics and integrity in Tampa City government;</text>
        <text>• Promote public confidence in public officers and employees and the ethical operation of government;</text>
        <text>• Promote and ensure compliance with local, state, and federal ethics law;</text>
        <text>• Centralize laws and regulations on the ethical conduct of city officers and employees;</text>
        <text>• Heighten knowledge and understanding of the laws and ethical principles which are the inherent obligations of city officers and employees;</text>
        <text>• Establish a system to train city officers and employees to encourage compliance with these standards and to also provide for periodic review, education and certification on ethics;</text>
        <text>• Enact a city ethics officer system that will continue to evolve and update our city's ethics program and to provide guidance and education to all city departments; and</text>
        <text>• Educate city officers and employees to avoid the appearance of impropriety and violations of the city ethics code.</text>
        <text>• Through this comprehensive code and the above stated goals, the city will strive to elevate the level of ethics in local government, to provide honest and responsible service to the citizens of Tampa, and to maintain the confidence and trust of the public that this government serves.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-502</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <text>The following words, terms and phrases, when used in this article, shall have the meanings ascribed to them in <cite path="2-502">this section</cite>, except where the context clearly indicates a different meaning:</text>
        <text><em>Affected personnel</em> means any member of city council, mayor, chief of staff, appointed employees, or any employee who has the authority to make final decisions.</text>
        <text><em>Appointed officer or official</em> means any person appointed to a public board of the city.</text>
        <text><em>Appointed employee</em> means any employee, regardless of the classified or unclassified service status, who holds a managerial position on the mayor's executive staff, and/or department and division heads or directors, deputy department and deputy division heads or directors, city attorney and all assistant city attorneys.</text>
        <text><em>Business entity</em> means a corporation, partnership, limited partnership, limited liability corporation, limited liability partnership, proprietorship, firm, enterprise, franchise, association, self-employed individual or trust, whether fictitiously named or not.</text>
        <text><em>Candidate</em> means any individual who has filed a statement of financial interest and qualification papers, has subscribed to the candidate's oath required by F.S. § 99.021, and seeks the election to become mayor or a member of the Tampa City Council.</text>
        <text><em>City</em> means the government of the City of Tampa.</text>
        <text><em>City reporting individual</em> means all elected officers, appointed officers, appointed employees, procurement employees, permitting employees and zoning employees.</text>
        <text><em>Close personal relationship</em> means dating, cohabitation, and/or having an intimate sexual relationship. Dating includes but is not limited to casual dating, serious dating, or casual sexual involvement where the parties have no intention of carrying on a long-term relationship, cohabitation, and any other conduct or behavior normally associated with romantic or sexual relationships. This definition applies regardless of the sexual orientation of the employees involved. Persons involved in a close personal relationship shall be referred to as a "close personal relation."</text>
        <text><em>Compensation</em> means any money, payment, remuneration, gift, favor, thing of value or financial benefit conferred in return for services rendered or to be rendered.</text>
        <text><em>Confidential information</em> means information not available to the general public and gained principally through one's employment or position with the city.</text>
        <text><em>Conflict</em> or a <em>conflict of interest</em> means a situation in which regard for a private interest outweighs a public duty or interest.</text>
        <text><em>Controlling financial interest</em> means ownership, directly or indirectly, to ten (10) percent or more of the outstanding capital stock in any corporation or a direct or indirect interest of ten (10) percent or more in a firm, partnership, or other business entity or such other interest or position in a business entity sufficient to allow him or her to control its operations.</text>
        <text><em>Elected officer or official</em> means any person elected to any city office.</text>
        <text><em>Employee</em> means any individual, other than an elected official, receiving compensation for services performed for the city (except individuals who perform services as independent contractors), whether part time or full time.</text>
        <text><em>Ethics commission</em> means the City of Tampa Ethics Commission.</text>
        <text><em>Fair market value</em> means the price that would be paid by a willing buyer to a willing seller in a good faith transaction in which neither party is compelled to enter.</text>
        <text><em>Financial interest</em> means any interest which shall yield, directly or indirectly, a monetary or other material benefit (other than the duly authorized salary or compensation for his services to the city) to the official or employee or to any person employing or retaining the services of the official or employee.</text>
        <text>
          <em>Gift:</em>
        </text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Gift means the transfer of anything of value that is accepted by a donee or by another on the donee's behalf, or that which is paid or given to another for or on behalf of a donee, directly, indirectly, or in trust for his or her benefit or by any other means, for which equal or greater consideration is not given. Among other things, a gift may be:</text>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <text>Real property;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b.</num>
            <text>The use of real property;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>c.</num>
            <text>Tangible or intangible personal property;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>d.</num>
            <text>The use of tangible or intangible personal property;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>e.</num>
            <text>A preferential rate or terms on a debt, loan, goods, or services, which rate is below the customary rate and is not either a government rate available to all other similar situated government employees or officials or a rate which is available to similarly situated members of the public by virtue of occupation, affiliation, age, religion, sex, or national origin;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>f.</num>
            <text>Forgiveness of indebtedness;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>g.</num>
            <text>Transportation, other than that provided to a public officer or employee by an agency in relation to officially approved governmental business, lodging or parking;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>h.</num>
            <text>Food or beverage;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>Membership dues;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>j.</num>
            <text>Entrance fees, admission fees, or tickets to events, performance or facilities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>k.</num>
            <text>Plants, flowers, or floral arrangements;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>l.</num>
            <text>Services provided by persons pursuant to a professional license or certificate;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>m.</num>
            <text>Other personal services for which a fee is normally charged by the person providing the services;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>n.</num>
            <text>Any other similar service or thing having an attributable value not already provided for in <cite path="2-502">this section</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Gift does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <text>Salary, benefits, services, fees, commissions, gifts, or expenses associated primarily with the donee's employment or business or provided to the donee by the city, to the extent that such gift is not inconsistent with the applicable provisions of F.S. § 112.3148;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b.</num>
            <text>Contributions or expenditures reported pursuant to F.S. Ch. 106, campaign-related personal services provided without compensation by individuals volunteering their time, or any other contribution or expenditure by a political party;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>c.</num>
            <text>An award, plaque, certificate, or similar personalized item given in recognition of the donee's public, civic, charitable, or professional service;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>d.</num>
            <text>An honorary membership in a service or fraternal organization presented merely as a courtesy by such organization;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>e.</num>
            <text>The use of a public facility or public property, made available by a governmental agency, for a public purpose;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>f.</num>
            <text>An honorarium or an expense related to an honorarium event paid to a person or a person's spouse;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>g.</num>
            <text>Transportation provided to an officer or employee by an agency in relation to officially approved governmental business;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>h.</num>
            <text>Gifts provided directly or indirectly by a state, regional or national organization which promotes the exchange of ideas between, or the professional development of, governmental officials, officers, or employees, and whose membership is primarily composed of elected or appointed officials, officers, or staff, to members of that organization or officials, officers, or staff of governmental agency that is a member of that organization;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>i.</num>
            <text>Gifts solicited or accepted from a "relative", as that term is defined in F.S. § 112.312(21).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <text>For the purpose of <cite path="2-502|(1)">subsection (1)</cite> above, "intangible personal property" means property as defined in F.S. § 192.001(11)(b).</text>
        <text>
          <em>Honorarium:</em>
        </text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Honorarium means a payment of money or anything of value, directly or indirectly, to a city reporting individual, or to any other person on his or her behalf, as consideration for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <text>A speech, address, oration or other oral presentation by the city reporting individual, regardless of whether presented in person, recorded, or broadcast over the media.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b.</num>
            <text>A writing by the city reporting individual, other than a book, which has been or is intended to be published.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The term honorarium does not include:</text>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <text>The payment for services related to employment held outside the city reporting individual's public position which resulted in the person becoming a city reporting individual;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b.</num>
            <text>Any ordinary payment or salary received in consideration for services related to the city reporting individual's public duties;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>c.</num>
            <text>A campaign contribution reported pursuant to F.S. Ch. 106;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>d.</num>
            <text>The payment or provision of actual and reasonable transportation, lodging, and food and beverage expenses related to the honorarium event, including any event or meeting registration fee for a city reporting individual and spouse.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <text><em>Immediate family</em> means spouse, parents and children of the person involved.</text>
        <text><em>Joint enterprise</em> means any contractual relationship, or a common property interest enjoyed or common liability incurred by two (2) or more persons and shall include, but not be limited to such matters as being a cosignatory of indebtedness, guarantor or a surety on a note, bank note, or other indication of indebtedness, joint ownership of any property right, legal or beneficial interest or any other equitable, financial, or contingent interest, however evidenced which entitles the owner or holder thereof, directly or indirectly, to receive or direct any part of the profits from, or to exercise any part of the control over, a business entity, as well as any interest which, conditionally or unconditionally, with or without consideration, is convertible thereto.</text>
        <text><em>Lobbying</em> means communicating directly or indirectly, outside a duly noticed public meeting or hearing on the record with affected personnel in order to encourage the passage, defeat, or modification of any item pending or likely to be pending in the near future, before the city council, or being considered by the lobbied employee for presentation or recommendation to the city council, the mayor or to any employee who has the authority to make final decisions, or in order to attempt to obtain the goodwill of any such affected personnel. If any such communication with any affected personnel occurs with respect to an item that is not presently pending before such affected personnel, and an item discussed therein subsequently comes before such affected personnel within twelve (12) months of such communication, that communication shall also constitute lobbying and shall be subject to prompt registration and other restrictions hereunder. For purposes of timely registration, the communication shall be deemed to have occurred upon the date such item becomes pending before such affected personnel. Lobbying shall include all forms of communication, whether oral, written or electronic.</text>
        <text><em>Lobbying principal</em> means any person providing compensation to a lobbyist in consideration of his or her performance of lobbying activities, regardless of the technical or legal form of the relationship between the principal and the lobbyist. Principal specifically includes a person whose employee or agent lobbies on behalf of the employer for the benefit, or in the name of the employer.</text>
        <text><em>Lobbyist</em> means any person who shall, for compensation of any kind, including but not limited to, salary, payment, retainer, commission, consideration of any type, forbearance, forgiveness or any combination thereof, either received or expected, engage in lobbying as defined herein. For purposes of <cite path="2-502">this section</cite>, compensation shall only include something of monetary value. Lobbyist does not include federal, state, county or other local government employees and quasi-government agency or entity employees who contact a city official or city employee to discuss such federal, state, county, other local government or quasi-government agency or entity business and such activity shall not be considered lobbying hereunder.</text>
        <text><em>Material interest</em> means the direct or indirect ownership of more than five (5) percent of the total assets or capital stock of a business entity. For purposes of this act, indirect ownership does not include ownership by a spouse or child.</text>
        <text><em>Official</em> or <em>officer</em> means any elected or appointed officer or official.</text>
        <text><em>Participate</em> means any attempt to influence a decision by oral, written or other communication, whether made by a person subject to this city ethics code or at his or her direction.</text>
        <text><em>Permitting employee</em> means any employee of the city who participates through decision, approval, disapproval, recommendation or preparation of a permit or permit application.</text>
        <text><em>Person</em> or <em>entity</em> means any individual, firm, business entity, company, corporation (profit and not-for-profit), professional corporation or associations, group, organization, joint venture, partnership, limited partnership, agency, estate, trusts, business trust, syndicate, fiduciary, or other body having an independent existence and all other groups or combinations however constituted.</text>
        <text><em>Personal interest</em> means any interest arising from blood, marriage, or close personal relationships or from close business association, whether or not any financial interest is involved.</text>
        <text><em>Procurement employee</em> means any employee of the city who participates through decision, approval, disapproval, recommendation or preparation of any part of a purchase request, influencing the content of any specification or procurement standard, rendering of advice, investigation or auditing or in any other advisory capacity in the procurement of contractual services or commodities as defined in F.S. § 287.012, if the cost of such services or commodities exceeds one thousand dollars ($1,000.00) in any year.</text>
        <text><em>Public board</em> means any agency, board, commission or other public body which is created pursuant to City Charter or ordinance and authorized to render decisions or make recommendations in accordance with said enabling legislation.</text>
        <text><em>Public body</em> means any agency, board, body, commission, committee, department, bureau, division, or office of the city.</text>
        <text><em>Public statement</em> means a statement, written or oral, describing the nature and extent of the financial interest, personal interest or employment involved.</text>
        <text><em>Quasi-government agency or entity</em> means any agency or entity conducting governmental or regulatory functions pursuant to general or special act of the Florida Legislature, the laws of any state or the United States, or federal law.</text>
        <text><em>Relative</em> means an individual who is related to the subject official or employee as father, mother, son, daughter, grandfather, grandmother, grandchild, brother, sister, uncle, aunt, first cousin, nephew, niece, husband, wife, father-in-law, mother-in-law, son-in-law, daughter-in-law, brother-in-law, sister-in-law, stepfather, stepmother, stepson, stepdaughter, stepbrother, stepsister, half brother, or half sister, anyone who is engaged to be married to the subject official or employee, or anyone who is a domestic partner pursuant to <cite path="12-120">section 12-120</cite>, City of Tampa Code.</text>
        <text><em>Reporting individual</em> or <em>city reporting individual</em> means and includes:</text>
        <text>Elected officials;</text>
        <text>Appointed officials;</text>
        <text>Appointed employees;</text>
        <text>Procurement employees;</text>
        <text>Permitting employees;</text>
        <text>Zoning employees.</text>
        <text><em>Represent</em> or <em>representation</em> means actual physical attendance on behalf of a client in a city proceeding, the writing of letters or filing of documents on behalf of a client, and personal communications made with the officers or employees of the city on behalf of a client.</text>
        <text><em>Special private gain</em> means economic benefit of any kind that inures to the person, as opposed to a class of similarly situated persons.</text>
        <text><em>Transact any business</em> means the purchase or sale by the city of specific goods or services for a consideration.</text>
        <text><em>Zoning employee</em> means any employee of the city who participates through decision, approval, recommendation or preparation of a zoning or land use matter or application.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-110, § 1, 4-29-04</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-21, § 1, 1-26-06</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2016-161, § 2, 11-3-2016</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-503</num>
        <heading>General provisions.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><em>Applicability of state statutes.</em> [Jacksonville] In addition to the provisions of this ethics code, all officers and employees of the city shall comply with all applicable provisions of state law, including but not limited to the following:</text>
          <text>Chapter 99 (Candidates, Campaign Expenses, and Contesting Elections);</text>
          <text>Section 100.361 (Municipal Recall);</text>
          <text>Section 102.031 (Maintenance of good order at polls; authorities; persons allowed in polling rooms; unlawful solicitation of voters;</text>
          <text>Section 104.071 (Remuneration by Candidate for services, support, etc.; penalty);</text>
          <text>Section 104.271 (False or malicious charges against, or false statements about, opposing Candidates; penalty);</text>
          <text>Section 104.31 (Political activities of state, county, and municipal officers and employees);</text>
          <text>Chapter 106 (Campaign financing);</text>
          <text>Section 111.075 (Elected officials; prohibition concerning certain committees);</text>
          <text>Section 112.042 (Discrimination in county and municipal employment; relief);</text>
          <text>Section 112.043 (Age discrimination);</text>
          <text>Section 112.044 (Public employers, employment agencies, labor organizations, discrimination based on age prohibited; exceptions; remedy);</text>
          <text>Chapter 112, Part III (Code of Ethics for Public Officers and Employees);</text>
          <text>Chapter 119 (Public Records);</text>
          <text>Section 163.367 (Public officials, commissioners, and employees subject to code of ethics);</text>
          <text>Section 286.011 (Public meetings and records; public inspection; criminal and civil penalties);</text>
          <text>Section 286.0115 (Access to local officials);</text>
          <text>Section 286.012 (Voting requirements at meeting of government bodies);</text>
          <text>Chapter 838 (Bribery, Misuse of Public Office);</text>
          <text>Chapter 839 (Offenses by Public Officers and Employees).</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-504-2-509</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">2</num>
      <heading>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST</heading>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subdivision</prefix>
        <num path-omit="true">I</num>
        <heading>Non-City Employment Restrictions</heading>
        <section>
          <num>2-510</num>
          <heading>Prohibited incompatible non-city employment or private business entity.</heading>
          <text>[Jacksonville] No official or employee of the city shall have any other outside employment ("non-city employment") or controlling financial interest in any private business entity, if that non-city employment or private business entity, or compensation received as a result thereof, impairs, or could reasonably be expected to impair, his independence in judgment or performance of city duties.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-21, § 6, 1-26-06</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-511</num>
          <heading>Mandatory disclosure by officials and employees of non-city employment or private business entity.</heading>
          <text>[Dade County] All officials and employees engaged in non-city employment or private business entity, shall file, under oath, an annual report indicating the source of the non-city employment or private business entity and the nature of the work being done pursuant to same non-city employment or private entity. Said official's and employee's reports shall be filed with the city ethics officer no later than 12:00 noon on July 1st of each year, including the July 1st following the last year that person held such employment or was engaged in such private business entity. Said reports shall be available at a reasonable time and place for inspection by the public. The city ethics officer may require monthly reports from individual employees or groups of employees for good cause.</text>
          <text>[Palm Bch Co] With regard to any non-city employment or private business entity activity, the disclosure statement shall contain the following information:</text>
          <text>• The name, address, and telephone number of the non-city employer or private business entity;</text>
          <text>• A brief description of the purpose and activities of the non-city employer or private business entity;</text>
          <text>• The position held by the disclosing individual;</text>
          <text>• The disclosing individual's relationship in and to the business;</text>
          <text>• The nature and extent of any ownership interest in the business.</text>
          <text>[Jacksonville] For officers or employees currently employed by the city, the disclosure shall be filed within thirty (30) days from the effective date of this article. For officers or employees who become officers or employees after the effective date of this article, the disclosure shall be filed within thirty (30) days from the beginning date of his or her employment with the city. All officers or employees of the city shall file an updated disclosure form within thirty (30) days whenever any of the information required by the form changes.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-21, § 6, 1-26-06</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-512</num>
          <heading>Approval required for non-city employment of or active participation in a private business entity by employees.</heading>
          <text>All employees must obtain prior written approval from his or her department director before accepting non-city employment or engaging in active participation in any private business entity. A copy of such written approval shall be filed with the city ethics officer. All current such activity shall be disclosed in writing to the department director within thirty (30) days of the effective date hereof. In determining the acceptability of such employment or activity, the department director shall review all factors relevant to the successful and fair operation of city business, including but not limited to, potential conflict with business hours, misuse of confidential information, or impairment of the performance of the city employee's duties and responsibilities. If the department director determines such non-city employment or engagement in a private business entity is prohibited, that decision shall be automatically appealed to the ethics commission for review. All department directors must obtain prior approval from the mayor before accepting non-city employment or actively participating in any business entity. The mere ownership of stock in a privately held or publicly traded company shall not constitute active participation in that business entity. Serving as an officer, director, or owning a controlling financial interest therein shall constitute active participation.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-21, §§ 2, 6, 1-26-06</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-513</num>
          <heading>Parties contracting with city; prohibition of employment of certain officials and employees.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The mayor, members of city council, and all department heads or directors of the city shall not solicit, accept, nor be employed, directly or indirectly, by any person, firm or corporation having any contractual relation with, or rendering any services to the city, or any department or agency thereof.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>No person, firm or corporation having any contractual relation with, or rendering any services to the city, or any department or agency thereof, shall employ, directly or indirectly, the mayor, any member of the city council, or any department head or director of the city. No persons, firm or corporation which has the mayor, member of the city council, or department head or director as an employee, shall be eligible to be considered to have a contractual relation with or to render for any consideration, services to the city.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>[Orlando] No employee of the city (other than those employees identified in <cite path="2-513|(a)">subsection (a)</cite> above) or member of any board, commission or agency of the city, shall be directly or indirectly employed by any person, firm or corporation having, or proposing to have, any contractual relation with or rendering, or proposing to render for any consideration, services to the city or any department, board or agency thereof, if the approval, concurrence, decision, recommendation or advice of the official or employee shall be sought, obtained or required in any connection with such contract or service.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>No person, firm or corporation having, or proposing to have any contractual relationship with, or rendering or proposing to render for any consideration services to the city, or any department, board or agency of the city, shall employ, directly or indirectly, any employee or member of any board, commission or agency of the city, if the approval, concurrence, decision, recommendation or service of such official or employee shall be sought, obtained, or required in connection with such contract or service.</text>
            <text>For purposes of <cite path="2-513">this section</cite>, a person, firm or corporation shall be deemed to be "proposing to have a contractual relation with the city" or to be "proposing to render services to the city" if such person, firm, or corporation has submitted a bid to the city for a city contract, has made a contractual offer to the city or has requested the city to reconsider entering a contractual relation with the person, firm or corporation.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subdivision</prefix>
        <num path-omit="true">II</num>
        <heading>Contractual Restrictions</heading>
        <section>
          <num>2-514</num>
          <heading>Prohibition against receipt of benefit from contracts with the city.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>No officer or employee, nor any member of their immediate family or close personal relation, either individually or through any firm of which they are a member, or through any corporation of which they are a stockholder, or through any business entity of which they have a controlling financial interest, shall receive any substantial benefit or profit out of any contract or obligation entered into with the city department for which the officer or employee works, or have any direct or indirect financial interest in effecting any such contract or obligation; and in the event of violation of <cite path="2-514">this section</cite> by an elected officer same shall be grounds for his recall, and in the event of violation by any other officer or employee of the city the person offending shall be immediately removed or discharged.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Any affected city officer or employee or department may seek a conflict of interest opinion from the city ethics commission prior to the submittal or award of a bid, response, or application of any type to contract with the city by the employee or his or her immediate family.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Notwithstanding any provision herein to the contrary, the city and any person or agency acting for the city shall not award a contract or influence the award of a contract to any employee, his or her immediate family, or close personal relation, individually or through a firm, corporation, partnership or business entity in which the employee, any member of his or her immediate family, or close personal relation has a controlling financial interest, unless the ethics commission has rendered an opinion that entering into the contract would not be a conflict of interest.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(d)</num>
            <text>The city is directed to include language in all solicitations for city contracts advising employees of the applicable conflict of interest code provisions, the provisions of this ordinance, including the requirement to obtain an ethics commission opinion and make disclosure, and the right to seek a legal opinion from the State of Florida Ethic's Commission regarding the applicability of state law conflict of interest provisions.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-21, § 3, 1-26-06</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-515</num>
          <heading>Prohibition against conflicting contractual relationships.</heading>
          <text>[F.S. § 112.313(7)] (a) No official or employee shall have or hold any contractual relationship with any individual, business entity or agency which is subject to the regulation of, or is doing business with, the city department or public body of which he or she is an official or employee. No official or employee shall have a contractual relationship that will create a continuing or frequently recurring conflict between his or her private interests and the performance of his or her public duties or that will impede the full and faithful discharge of his or her public duties.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text><cite path="2-515">This section</cite> shall not prohibit an appointed officer or official from practicing in a particular profession or occupation when such practice by persons appointed to a public board is required by law or ordinance.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-225, § 2, 9-30-04</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-516</num>
          <heading>Prohibition against doing business with one's department or the city.</heading>
          <text>[F.S. § 112.313(3)] No official or employee of the city acting in his official capacity, shall directly or indirectly purchase, rent, or lease realty, goods, or services for his own department or public body from any business entity of which the official or employee, or the official's or employee's immediate family or close personal relation, or any combination of them, has a material interest. Nor shall an official or employee, acting in a private capacity, rent, lease, or sell any realty, goods or services to the official's or employee's public body or department.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subdivision</prefix>
        <num path-omit="true">III</num>
        <heading>Financial Interest Restrictions</heading>
        <section>
          <num>2-517</num>
          <heading>Actions prohibited when certain financial interests involved.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>[Dade Co] No official or employee shall participate in any official action directly or indirectly affecting a business in which he or any member of his immediate family or close personal relation has a financial interest.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>[Dade Co] No official or employee shall have or acquire a financial interest in any enterprise, project, business entity or property when he believes or has reason to believe that the said financial interest will be directly affected by his official actions or by official actions by the city department in which he is employed or public body of which he is an official.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>[Jacksonville] No official or employee shall have any interest, financial or otherwise, direct or indirect, or engage in any business or activity or incur any obligation of any nature which is in substantial conflict with the proper discharge of his or her duties in the public interest.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-518</num>
          <heading>Mandatory disclosure of real estate owned by certain officials and employees.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>[Miami] All the elected officers, appointed officers and appointed employees shall, within thirty (30) days from the effective date of this article, submit to the city ethics officer a complete itemized list of all real property owned by him or his spouse or close personal relation, whether the title be either legal or equitable, whether owned in whole or in part, including corporate real property in which he has a controlling interest or is an officer of such corporation, and shall include the following information as to each parcel of land:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>The legal description and common address;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>The municipal or county zoning classification wherein the property is located;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>The manner in which the property is presently being utilized;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>A description of the nature of the interest in the property.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Only those real properties required to be listed are those properties located within the corporate limits of the city or those properties located five hundred (500) feet beyond the corporate limits of the city. The real properties required to be listed shall be on the form provided by the city ethics officer.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>All the elected officers and appointed officers or employees who are elected or appointed subsequent to the effective date of this ethics code shall, within thirty (30) days of their election or appointment, submit an itemized list of real estate holdings as provided above.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subdivision</prefix>
        <num path-omit="true">IV</num>
        <heading>Voting Conflict Restrictions</heading>
        <section>
          <num>2-519</num>
          <heading>Prohibited voting conflicts.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>[Palm Bch Co] No city official shall vote or participate in his or her official capacity on any matter if that member knows or should know that doing so would inure, either directly or indirectly, to:</text>
          </para>
          <text>• His or her special private gain; or</text>
          <text>• The special private gain of any person by whom he or she is retained, or</text>
          <text>• The parent or subsidiary organization thereof; or</text>
          <text>• The special private gain of a relative of the official's.</text>
          <text>For the purpose of this subsection, "special private gain" shall mean economic benefit of any kind which inures to the individual, as opposed to a class of similarly situated individuals.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>No appointed officer or official shall vote or participate on any matter in which the appointed officer or official has or holds a contractual relationship with an individual, business entity or agency subject to the regulation of the public board to which that officer or official is appointed. An appointed officer or official may be removed from office by the mayor, after review by and with the recommendation of the ethics commission, if such appointed officer or official has disclosed a conflict of interest, pursuant to <cite path="2-519|(c)">section 2-519(c)</cite>, in ten (10) percent or more of the applications filed with the public board to which that officer or official is appointed.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Disclosure. Officials prohibited from voting and participating on any matter pursuant to <cite path="2-519|(a)">subsection (a)</cite> or (b) above, shall:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>Publicly state to the assembly the nature of their interest in the matter in which they are prohibited from voting and participating; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>Disclose the nature of their interest in the matter from which they are prohibited from voting and participating within fifteen (15) days after the vote occurs in a memorandum filed with the clerk of such board, who shall incorporate the memorandum in the minutes.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-225, § 3, 9-30-04</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-520</num>
          <heading>Reserved.</heading>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="Editor's Notes" dest="container"><strong>Editor's note— </strong>Ord. No. 2006-21, § 4, adopted Jan. 26, 2006, repealed <cite path="2-520">§ 2-520</cite>, which pertained to additional voting conflicts. See also the Code Comparative Table.</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
      </container>
      <container>
        <prefix>Subdivision</prefix>
        <num path-omit="true">V</num>
        <heading>Other Conflict Restrictions</heading>
        <section>
          <num>2-521</num>
          <heading>Representation of private persons.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>[<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>] No official or employee shall appear on behalf of any private person, other than himself, before any public body or agency of the city; provided, however, this shall not preclude an individual appointed to a board, commission, agency or body from appearing on behalf of any private person before any public body, other than the public body to which he is appointed; provided further, this exemption shall not be construed as an exemption from applicable provisions of F.S. Ch. 112, Pt. III, Code of Ethics for Public Officers and Employees.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>[Dade Co] No official or employee shall appear before the city department in which he works, nor board on which he or she serves, (except as provided in sub<cite path="2-515|(b)">section 2-515(b)</cite> above), either directly or indirectly through an associate, and make a presentation on behalf of a third person with respect to any license, contract, certificate, ruling, decision, opinion, rate schedule, franchise, or other benefit sought by the third person. Nor shall such official or employee receive compensation, directly or indirectly in any form, for services rendered to a third party, who has applied for or is seeking some approval or benefit from the city department in which he works or board on which such he serves, (except as provided in sub<cite path="2-515|(b)">section 2-515(b)</cite> above), in connection with the particular benefit by the third party.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>[Jacksonville] It shall be unlawful for an officer or employee of the city, otherwise than in the proper discharge of his or her official duties:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>To act as agent or attorney for anyone before any unit of government in connection with a proceeding, application, request for a ruling or other determination, contract, claim, controversy, charge or other particular matter with respect to which he or she, or a unit of government of which he or she is a member, has acted upon in an official capacity either before or concurrently with his or her acting as agent or attorney.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>To testify as an expert witness in any proceeding before any body or court over the objection of the city or an independent agency.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>Nothing in <cite path="2-521">this section</cite> shall prevent an officer or employee of the city from acting, with or without compensation, as agent or attorney for his or her parents, spouse, child or any person for whom, or for any estate for which, he or she is serving as personal representative, except in those matters in which he or she has participated personally and substantially as an officer or employee of the city or an independent agency, through decision, approval, disapproval, recommendation, the rendering of advice, investigation or otherwise, or which are the subject of his or her official responsibility; provided, that the official responsible for appointment to his or her position approves.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, sec. 2(2-665), 9-28-89</annotation>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 98-95, sec. 2.4-23-98</annotation>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-225, § 4, 9-30-04</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-522</num>
          <heading>Business ethics commitment required of contracting parties.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>[Dade Co] Each person or entity that seeks to do business with the city shall provide a business ethics commitment which acknowledges, agrees and commits that the person or entity shall comply with all applicable governmental and city rules and regulations including, among others, <cite path="2-500">this code</cite> of ethics. The business ethics commitment shall be incorporated into and apply to all contracts that the person or entity enters into with the city.</text>
            <text>The failure of a contracting party to comply with the business ethics commitment shall render any contract between the contractor and the city voidable, and subject violators to debarment from future city contracts.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-523</num>
          <heading>Prohibition against recommending business or professional services.</heading>
          <text>[Dade Co] No official or employee shall recommend the services of any lawyer or law firm, architect or architectural firm, public relations firm, or any other person or firm, professional or otherwise, to assist in any transaction involving the city or any of its agencies, provided that such recommendation may properly be made when required to be made by the duties of office and in advance at a public meeting attended by other city officials, officers or employees.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-524</num>
          <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
          <text>No official or employee shall be held in violation of any provision of the city ethics code if the total amount of a transaction or matter in the aggregate between a business entity and the city does not exceed five hundred dollars ($500.00) per calendar year.</text>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-525</num>
          <heading>Standards of conduct and accountability requirements for non-profits provided financial support by the city.</heading>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text><em>Purpose:</em> The purpose of <cite path="2-525">this section</cite> is to provide ethical guidance and enforceable requirements for each of the non-profits to which the city provides financial support. Partnerships with the private non-profit sector can be a valuable, cost-effective mechanism for delivering services and providing amenities for the people of the city. For this public-private partnership to be successful the city and the city's non-profit partners must recognize that adherence to high levels of transparency and ethics is essential.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text><em>Scope:</em><cite path="2-525">This section</cite> of the Code shall apply to each and every non-profit that accepts twenty-five thousand dollars ($25,000.00) or more in financial support from the city. The act of acceptance of this financial support by a non-profit shall constitute acceptance of the requirements of <cite path="2-525">this section</cite> and agreement by the non-profit, its board members, and its executive staff to comply with each of the requirements of <cite path="2-525">this section</cite>. Any transaction between the city and a non-profit subject to the requirements of <cite path="2-525">this section</cite> shall be void if the non-profit refuses to accept or fails to substantially comply with the requirements of <cite path="2-525">this section</cite>. The requirements of <cite path="2-525">this section</cite> may not be waived by contract, resolution, or any act of any city officer or employee.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>
              <em>Definitions:</em>
            </text>
            <text><em>Board of directors</em> shall mean the governing body of the non-profit.</text>
            <text><em>Board member</em> shall mean any member of the governing body of the non-profit.</text>
            <text><em>Executive staff</em> shall mean the senior tiers of management of the non-profit. At a minimum, executive staff shall include the chief executive officer plus the individual(s) ultimately responsible for:</text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>Financial accountability and controls;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>Facilities management and operations;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <text>Personnel and human resources; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>d.</num>
              <text>Development, marketing and/or public relations.</text>
            </para>
            <text>
              <em>Financial support:</em>
            </text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>Financial support includes, but is not limited to, transactions of twenty-five thousand dollars ($25,000.00) greater where the following occurs in support of a public purpose:</text>
              <para>
                <num>1.</num>
                <text>Transfer or assignment of cash or a cash equivalent from the city to the non-profit, including distribution of funds under any state, federal or other governmental program administered by the city;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>2.</num>
                <text>Transfer or assignment of any interest in real property;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>3.</num>
                <text>Any agreement for use or operation by a non-profit of any real property owned or controlled by the city;</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>4.</num>
                <text>Payment of any debt or debt service that is for the benefit of the non-profit; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>5.</num>
                <text>Any other transaction where an item of value is made available to the non-profit in support of a public purpose.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>Financial support does not include:</text>
              <para>
                <num>1.</num>
                <text>Any transaction in which an item of value less than twenty-five thousand dollars ($25,000.00) is transferred or assigned by the city to the non-profit.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>2.</num>
                <text>Payments made by the city pursuant to a contract for goods or services that have been procured through a competitive process. Any contract with a non-profit that was a sole source procurement or otherwise for goods or services not procured through a competitive process shall be presumed to be financial support.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>3.</num>
                <text>Goodwill, advertising, sponsorship (including city services), promotional consideration, and in-kind support not otherwise specified herein as an item of value.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>4.</num>
                <text>Any one-time transaction in which an item of value other than cash is transferred or assigned by the city to a non-profit, and that follows the city's existing policy for making such transfer or assignment.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>5.</num>
                <text>Funding in the form of an award made by the city pursuant to a state or federal grant program that is subject to other reporting, monitoring, or audit requirements.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>6.</num>
                <text>Payments made as a result of a special assessment services agreement, municipal services or other service agreement, where specific services are provided and invoices are submitted to the city by the non-profit on a reimbursement basis subject to review and approval by the city.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>7.</num>
                <text>Funding provided to any governmental or quasi-governmental agency or entity, whether or not said agency or entity is designated as a section 501 entity under the Internal Revenue Code.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <text><em>Item of value</em> shall include payment of any debt, any interest in real property, stocks, intellectual property rights, royalties, bonds, insurance or insurance coverage, cash, and other valuable personal property.</text>
            <text><em>Non-profit</em> shall include all entities designated as non-profit by the U.S. Internal Revenue Service under section 501 of the Internal Revenue Code, or any not-for-profit corporation incorporated under the laws of the State of Florida or other state law.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>
              <em>Obligations of the non-profit, board of directors, and executive staff:</em>
            </text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>The board of directors shall adopt a conflict of interest policy applicable to all board members and executive staff that shall prohibit the following:</text>
              <para>
                <num>1.</num>
                <text>Any transactions between the non-profit and a board member or executive staff which may inure to the personal financial benefit of a board member, executive staff, or the immediate family of a board member or executive staff, except:</text>
                <para>
                  <num>i.</num>
                  <text>After an open and competitive process and full disclosure of the transaction and the relationship to the board member or executive staff;</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>ii.</num>
                  <text>When any personal financial benefit would be de minimus or limited solely to good will or other speculative benefits; or</text>
                </para>
                <para>
                  <num>iii.</num>
                  <text>Executive staff compensation for employment by the non-profit.</text>
                </para>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>2.</num>
                <text>Employment by executive staff with an entity directly or indirectly competing with the non-profit.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>The board of directors shall adopt a policy prohibiting transactions with any for-profit entity affiliated with, owned by, or employing a board member or executive staff or the immediate family of a board member or executive staff, except:</text>
              <para>
                <num>1.</num>
                <text>After an open and competitive process and full disclosure of the transaction and the relationship to the board member or executive staff; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>2.</num>
                <text>When any financial benefit to the for-profit entity would be de minimus or limited solely to good will or other speculative benefits.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <text>The non-profit board of directors shall adopt an anti-nepotism policy, except in the case where the non-profit is a family trust or foundation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>d.</num>
              <text>The non-profit board of directors shall adopt a whistleblower policy that, at a minimum, shall include a method to allow any employee to bring to the attention of the non-profit's designated ethics officer any actions that violate federal, state, or local laws or established non-profit policies regarding personnel, finance, ethics, and asset management.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>e.</num>
              <text>The non-profit board of directors shall endeavor to have a diverse board and shall not discriminate in the recruitment or selection of board members, except in the case where the non-profit is a family trust or foundation.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>f.</num>
              <text>The board of directors, board members, and executive staff shall not enter into any arrangement involving any form of kickbacks.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>
              <em>Reporting and recordkeeping requirements:</em>
            </text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>Each non-profit shall annually file with the city finance director:</text>
              <para>
                <num>1.</num>
                <text>A statement, in substantially the form provided in the attached certification, approved by the board of directors certifying on behalf of the non-profit compliance with <cite path="2-525">this section</cite> and compliance with any leases, operating agreements or other contracts or agreements between the non-profit and the city,</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>2.</num>
                <text>Total compensation provided by the non-profit, and any of its affiliated entities, to each executive staff member,</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>3.</num>
                <text>Total amount of city financial support.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>Each of the items in paragraphs (5)a. shall be filed annually on or before April 1 for the prior calendar year.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>c.</num>
              <text>The board of directors of the non-profit shall keep accurate written minutes of all meetings of the board of directors, all meetings of the executive committee and any meetings of committees designated to address ethics, finances, or compensation of executive staff. These minutes must include recordation of all votes of each individual board member on all actions of the board of directors where the action of the board of directors is not unanimous, and shall be made available to the city upon receipt of written request.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>d.</num>
              <text>Each non-profit shall maintain the following documents and provide any or all of the documents within seven (7) days of a request by the city finance director:</text>
              <para>
                <num>1.</num>
                <text>Copies of the policies and procedures demonstrating the non-profit's compliance with <cite path="2-525">this section</cite>, and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>2.</num>
                <text>Copies of records documenting compliance with non-profit policies and procedures required by <cite path="2-525">this section</cite>, and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>3.</num>
                <text>List of all board members and executive staff and contact information for each, including address and phone number, sufficient for the city to directly contact the each board member and executive staff member, and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>4.</num>
                <text>List of all transactions approved by the board of directors pursuant to the policies required by paragraphs (4)a. and b., including the persons or business entities involved in the transactions, the nature of the transactions, the nature of the relationship(s) that implicated paragraphs (4)a. or b, the dollar amount of the transaction, and the date of the board of directors approval of the transaction, and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>5.</num>
                <text>Copies of all Form 990 and related schedules filed with the Internal Revenue Service and any additional filings regarding related party transactions as defined by the Internal Revenue Code.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>e.</num>
              <text>In the event any violation of <cite path="2-525">this section</cite> becomes known to the non-profit board of directors or executive staff, a report shall be filed with the city finance director not more than fifteen (15) days after the violation becomes known to the board of directors or executive staff.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>
              <em>Enforcement:</em>
            </text>
            <para>
              <num>a.</num>
              <text>The city shall have the right to audit all records and inspect all assets of the non-profit as necessary to determine compliance with <cite path="2-525">this section</cite> and any other terms or conditions of any grant agreement, contract, lease, deed, or other agreement with the city.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>b.</num>
              <text>In the event the city becomes aware that a non-profit has failed to comply with any aspect of <cite path="2-525">this section</cite>, the city shall provide notice in writing to the non-profit board of directors. If the non-profit fails to cure a material failure to comply with <cite path="2-525">this section</cite> within sixty (60) days of written notice of the material failure, the non-profit shall:</text>
              <para>
                <num>1.</num>
                <text>Refund all city financial support provided in the city's fiscal year within which the non-profit failed to comply with <cite path="2-525">this section</cite>; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>2.</num>
                <text>Be barred from applying for or receiving financial support from the city for a period of one (1) year; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>3.</num>
                <text>In no event shall the non-profit receive financial support from the city until the non-profit has demonstrated full compliance with <cite path="2-525">this section</cite>.</text>
                <text>The sixty-day period for cure of a material failure to comply with <cite path="2-525">this section</cite> may be extended for two (2) additional thirty-day periods by the city finance director.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text><em>Effective date:</em><cite path="2-525">This section</cite> shall be effective upon becoming law. <cite path="2-525">This section</cite> shall apply to all transactions on or after the effective date, but shall not be construed to impair contracts effective and in force prior to the effective date.</text>
          </para>
          <annotations>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2010-153, § 1, 10-21-2010</annotation>
            <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2012-8, § 1, 1-19-2012</annotation>
          </annotations>
        </section>
        <section>
          <num>2-526-2-539</num>
          <heading>Reserved.</heading>
        </section>
      </container>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">3</num>
      <heading>MISUSE OF POSITION AND PROPERTY</heading>
      <section>
        <num>2-540</num>
        <heading>Use of public property.</heading>
        <text>[<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>] No official or employee shall request, use or permit the use of any publicly owned or publicly supplied property, vehicle, equipment, material, labor or service for the personal convenience or the private advantage of himself or of any other person. This rule shall not be deemed to prohibit an official or employee from requesting or permitting the use of such publicly owned or publicly supplied property, vehicle, equipment, material, labor or service which it is the general practice to make available to the public at large or which is provided as a matter of stated public policy for the use of officials and employees in the conduct of official business.</text>
        <text>[Jacksonville] In addition to any other penalty provided by law, upon conviction and adjudication of guilt, he or she may also be fined in a sum equal to the value of the money or property embezzled or converted for a violation of <cite path="2-540">this section</cite>.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, sec. 2(2-662), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-541</num>
        <heading>Officer or employee trading in public funds/revenues.</heading>
        <text>[Jacksonville] It is unlawful for any officer or employee of the city or any party who contracts with the city involved in the collection or disbursement of the revenues of the city to carry on any trade or business with the funds or debts or with any public property of the city, for any purpose other than official responsibilities.</text>
        <text>[Jacksonville] In addition to any other penalty provided by law, upon conviction and adjudication of guilt, he or she may also be fined in a sum equal to the value of the property traded for a violation of <cite path="2-541">this section</cite>.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-542</num>
        <heading>Activities of officers and employees in matters affecting the city.</heading>
        <text>[Jacksonville] It shall be unlawful for an officer or employee of the city, except in the proper discharge of his or her official duties (including authorized union duties):</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>To act as agent or attorney for prosecuting any claim against the city, or to receive any gratuity or any share of or interest in any claim against the city, in consideration of assistance in the prosecution of the claim;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>To act as agent or attorney for anyone before any unit of government in connection with any proceedings, application, request for ruling or other determination, contract, claim, controversy, charge, accusation, arrest or other particular matter in which the city is a party or has a direct and substantial interest.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-543</num>
        <heading>Use of confidential information.</heading>
        <text>[<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>] No official or employee shall use or permit the use of confidential information to advance the financial or personal interest of himself or any other person. [Dade Co] Further, no official or employee shall accept employment or engage in any business or professional activity in which he might reasonably be expected, required or induced to disclose confidential information.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, sec. 2(2-667), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-544</num>
        <heading>Impartiality.</heading>
        <text>[<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>] No official or employee shall request, use or permit the use of any consideration, treatment, advantage or favor beyond that which it is the general practice to grant or make available to the public at large.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, sec. 2(2-661), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-545</num>
        <heading>Misuse of position.</heading>
        <text>[Jacksonville] It is unlawful for an officer or employee of the city to intentionally use his or her official position to secure, by coercion or threat or otherwise, a special privilege or exemption for himself, herself, or others, or to secure confidential information for any purpose other than official responsibilities.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-546</num>
        <heading>Restriction on appointment, employment, promotion or advancement of relatives.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>[F.S. § 112.3135 and City Personnel Manual B24.] No official or employee may appoint, employ, promote, or advance, or advocate for appointment, employment, promotion, or advancement, in or to a position in the department or public body in which the official or employee is serving, or over which the official or employee exercises jurisdiction and control, any individual who is a relative of the official or employee.</text>
          <text>Further, an individual may not be appointed, employed, promoted, or advanced in or to a position in the city if such appointment, employment, promotion, or advancement has been advocated by an officer or employee, serving in or exercising jurisdiction and control over the city department or public body, who is a relative of the individual or if such appointment, employment, promotion, or advancement is made by a collegial body of which a relative of the individual is a member.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Individuals shall not be selected for any position in the same department of which a relative serves as the department head or director or to the same division or section of the department of which the relative serves as the managerial, supervisory, or lead employee. Individuals who are relatives of the mayor's executive staff shall not be selected to any position in the city. Further, employees who hold a status prior to the relative's appointment or selection as a department director, manager, or supervisor, or who become related by marriage shall not be placed on any eligibility lists for promotion within that same department, division, or section as applicable and shall be placed in a different department, division, or section as soon as practicable.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-547</num>
        <heading>Prohibited activities relating to promotion or appointment.</heading>
        <text>[Jacksonville] It shall be unlawful for any person seeking employment to, or promotion in, the city to either directly or indirectly give, promise, render, or pay any money, service, or other valuable thing to any person for, or on account of, or in connection with or for the purpose of influencing or affecting their test, appointment, proposed appointment, promotion or proposed promotion.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-548</num>
        <heading>Prohibited activities relating to fraternization.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>[City of Tampa Personnel Manual B24.1] No official or employee shall appoint, employ, promote or advance, nor recommend or advocate the appointment, employment, promotion or advancement in or to any position, any individual with whom they have a close personal relationship. An officer or employee is considered to "recommend or advocate" if they urge or support the action either orally or in writing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Individuals shall not be selected for any position in the same department when they have a close personal relationship with the employee who serves as the department director or to the same division or section of the department when they have a close personal relationship with the employee who serves as the managerial, supervisory, or lead employee. Individuals who have a close personal relationship with an employee of the mayor's executive staff shall not be selected to any position in the city. Further, employees who hold a status prior to the close personal relation's appointment or selection as a department director, manager, or supervisor, shall not be placed on any eligibility lists for promotion within that same department, division, or section as applicable and shall be placed in a different department, division, or section as soon as practicable.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Officials and employees who serve as a manager, supervisor, or lead employee are prohibited from having close personal relationships with their subordinate personnel. If any such relationship does occur, it must be immediately disclosed by both employees to the city ethics officer so that immediate steps can be taken to resolve conflict with this provision.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>All employees are discouraged from having close personal relationships with non-subordinate employees. All such relationships must be disclosed by both employees to the department director and may result in requiring that the employees work different shifts; transferring one (1) employee to another department; assigning one (1) of the employees to another facility, squad, or work unit; or other action determined to be appropriate by the city ethics officer.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-549</num>
        <heading>Product endorsements subject to approval by the mayor.</heading>
        <text>No City of Tampa public officer or employee shall publicly endorse or recommend any product, service, vendor, or person or entity, unless the mayor has issued prior written approval of such public endorsement or recommendation. This prohibition shall not apply to public endorsements or recommendations required to be made pursuant to statute, regulation, code, or the duties of office.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-110, § 2, 4-29-04</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-550-2-559</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">4</num>
      <heading>GIFTS, HONORARIA AND FINANCIAL DISCLOSURE</heading>
      <section>
        <num>2-560</num>
        <heading>Adoption of Florida Gift Law.</heading>
        <text>The city hereby adopts and incorporates by reference Florida's Gift Law (F.S. § 112.3148) as it may be amended from time to time. The following provisions applicable to certain city officials and employees are intended to be supplemental to the requirements of the Florida Gift Law.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-561</num>
        <heading>Prohibited receipt of gifts or charge of commissions for official transactions.</heading>
        <text>[Leon County and Jacksonville] It shall be unlawful for an officer or employee to charge, solicit, accept, be the beneficiary of or receive, directly or indirectly, any fee, commission, gift, gratuity, loan or other consideration for or in connection with any transaction or business done, performed or rendered in the course of his or her official duties or responsibilities, and which is intended, or can be reasonably inferred as intended to influence the performance of an official act.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-562</num>
        <heading>Prohibited gifts from parties doing business with the city.</heading>
        <text>No officer or employee of the city, excluding appointed officials, shall knowingly accept, directly or indirectly, from any person, company, firm or corporation to which any purchase order or contract is awarded, any rebate, gift, money or other consideration, with a value greater than one hundred dollars ($100.00), except when given for the use and benefit of the city, or except when given in public recognition of exemplary performance of official duties, subject to the limitations set forth below in <cite path="2-563">section 2-563</cite>, Prohibited offering/receipt of gifts from lobbyists.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-110, § 3, 4-29-04</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-563</num>
        <heading>Prohibited offering/receipt of gifts from lobbyists.</heading>
        <text>[Jacksonville] (a) No officer or employee of the city shall knowingly accept, directly or indirectly, any gift with a value greater than one hundred dollars ($100.00) from any person the recipient knows is:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A lobbyist who lobbies the recipient's agency or executive department; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Any principal or employer of a lobbyist.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>It is unlawful for a lobbyist, or principal or employer of a lobbyist, to knowingly offer a gift to an officer or employee of the city which would cause a violation of this ethics codes.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-564</num>
        <heading>Gift reporting.</heading>
        <text>[Jacksonville] In addition to any reporting required pursuant to the Florida Gift Law, all elected and appointed officers, appointed employees, procurement employees, permitting employees, and zoning employees ("city reporting individuals") who receive a gift in excess of one hundred dollars ($100.00) shall report that gift in an annual statement to the city ethics officer in accordance with the requirements (and exceptions) and in the manner provided in F.S. § 112.3148.</text>
        <text>Provided however, where this ordinance requires a person to file a report and that person is not required to file a report pursuant to state law, the report shall be on a form which is substantially the same in content as that required by state law, and the form shall be submitted annually, by July 1, to the city ethics officer. Where this article requires a person to file a report and that person is required to file a report pursuant to state law, the report shall be on a form which is substantially the same in content as that required by state law, and the form shall be submitted annually, by July 1, to the city ethics officer in addition to the filing required by state law.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-565</num>
        <heading>Honoraria.</heading>
        <text>[Jacksonville] An officer or employee is prohibited from soliciting an honorarium which is related to the officer or employee's public office or duties.</text>
        <text>An officer or employee is prohibited from knowingly accepting an honorarium from a political committee or committee of continuous existence, as defined in F.S. § 106.011, from a lobbyist or from the employer, principal, partner, or firm of such a lobbyist.</text>
        <text>A political committee of continuous existence, as defined in F.S. § 106.011, a lobbyist or the employer, principal, partner or firm of a lobbyist is prohibited from giving an honorarium to an officer or employee.</text>
        <text>A person who is prohibited from paying an honorarium to an officer or employee but who provides an officer or employee or officer and employee and his or her spouse, with expenses related to an honorarium event, shall provide to the officer or employee, no later than sixty (60) days after the honorarium event, a statement listing the name and address of the person providing the expenses, a description of the expenses provided each day, and the total value of the expenses providing for the honorarium event.</text>
        <text>An officer or employee who receives payment or provision of expenses related to any honorarium event from a person who is prohibited from paying an honorarium to an officer or employee shall publicly disclose on an annual statement the name, address, and affiliation of the person paying or providing the expenses; the amount of the honorarium expenses; the date of the honorarium event; a description of the date of the expenses paid or provided on each day of the honorarium event; and the total value of the expenses provided to the officer and employee in connection with the honorarium event. The annual statement of honorarium expenses shall be filed by July 1st of each year for such expenses received during the previous calendar year. The officer or employee shall attach to the annual statement a copy of each statement received by him or her in accordance with <cite path="2-565|(d)">subsection (d)</cite> regarding honorarium expenses paid or provided during the calendar year for which the annual statement is filed. Such attached statement shall become a public record upon the filing of the annual report. The annual statement of an officer or employee shall be filed in compliance with state law. Where this ordinance requires a person to file a report and that person is not required to file a report pursuant to state law, the report shall be on a form which is substantially the same in content as that required by state law, and the form shall be submitted annually, by July 1, to the city ethics officer.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-566</num>
        <heading>Financial disclosure; filing, deadlines.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>As used in <cite path="2-566">this section</cite>, "local officer" means every person who is elected to any public office in the city and every person who is appointed to fill a vacancy for an unexpired term in such elective office, and "appointed employee" means all members of the mayor's executive staff, department and division heads or directors, deputy department and deputy division heads or directors, city attorney and all assistant city attorneys.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>In addition to any financial disclosure required under state law, on or before July fifteenth of each year for the preceding calendar year, including the July fifteenth following the last year he is in office, each local officer shall file full and public disclosure of his financial interests and those of his spouse, as provided in <cite path="2-566">this section</cite>. Each local officer who is appointed to fill a vacancy shall file full and public disclosure of his financial interests and those of his spouse as provided in <cite path="2-566">this section</cite> within thirty (30) days from the date of appointment. A candidate for election to a local office shall file a full and public disclosure of his financial interests and those of his spouse as provided in <cite path="2-566">this section</cite> at the same time he files his qualifying papers.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>"Full and public disclosure of financial interests," for the purposes of <cite path="2-566">this section</cite> shall mean filing with the city ethics officer, on or before the specified disclosure deadline each year, a sworn statement which complies with the disclosure requirements set forth in F.S. § 112.3144, except as provided herein.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In addition to any financial disclosure required under state law, on or before July fifteenth of each year for the preceding calendar year, including the July fifteenth following the last year he is in office, each appointed employee shall file disclosure of his financial interests as provided in <cite path="2-566">this section</cite>. Each appointed employee who is appointed to fill a vacancy shall file disclosure of his financial interests as provided in <cite path="2-566">this section</cite> within thirty (30) days from the date of appointment.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>"Disclosure of financial interests" for the purposes of <cite path="2-566">this section</cite> shall mean filing with the city ethics officer, on or before the specified disclosure deadline each year, a sworn statement which complies with the disclosure requirements set forth in F.S. § 112.3145, except as provided herein.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>The city ethics officer shall prescribe the forms, which a disclosing party must use, for the disclosure of information required by <cite path="2-566">this section</cite> at least thirty (30) days prior to the disclosure deadlines set forth in <cite path="2-566">this section</cite>. The forms shall be substantially the same in content as required by state law. The city ethics officer shall provide these forms, which shall be made available at the city ethics officer's office at least thirty (30) days prior to the disclosure deadlines set forth in <cite path="2-566">this section</cite>, upon request of the disclosing party.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>A local officer or appointed employee who has filed a financial disclosure for any year pursuant to <cite path="2-566">this section</cite> shall not be required to file a second disclosure pursuant to <cite path="2-566">this section</cite> for the same year or any part thereof, notwithstanding any requirement of <cite path="2-566">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>Financial disclosures filed pursuant to <cite path="2-566">this section</cite> shall constitute public records within the meaning of F.S. Ch. 119.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>]</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, sec. 2(2-666), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-567</num>
        <heading>Disclosure of specified interests.</heading>
        <text>[<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>] If any elected official is an officer, director, partner, proprietor, associate, or general agent (other than a resident agent solely for service of process) of, or owns a material interest in any business entity, he shall file a statement disclosing such facts not later than forty-five (45) days after becoming an elected official, or no later than forty-five (45) days after the acquisition of such position or material interest, or no later than forty-five (45) days after the effective date of <cite path="2-567">this section</cite>, as applicable. The disclosure statement shall give the name, address, and principal business activity of the business entity and shall state the position held with such business entity or the fact that a material interest is owned and the nature of such interest. The disclosure statement shall be made upon forms provided by the city and filed with the city ethics officer.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 98-256, sec. 2, 12-3-98</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-568</num>
        <heading>Disclosure of joint enterprise by city officials.</heading>
        <text>[<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>] If any elected official has or enters into a joint enterprise as hereinabove defined with any other elected official or with any city employee, said elected official shall file a statement disclosing such fact no later than forty-five (45) days after becoming an elected official, or no later than forty-five (45) days after the date said elected official enters into the joint enterprise, or no later than forty-five (45) days after the effective date of <cite path="2-568">this section</cite>, as applicable. The disclosure statement shall be made upon forms provided by the city and the same shall be filed with the city ethics officer.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 98-256, sec. 2, 12-3-98</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-569-2-579</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">5</num>
      <heading>LOBBYING AND POST-EMPLOYMENT RESTRICTIONS</heading>
      <section>
        <num>2-580</num>
        <heading>Lobbying.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><em>Registration of lobbyists</em>. All persons who are lobbyists pursuant to <cite path="2-502">section 2-502</cite> must register prior to lobbying using the registration process maintained by the city ethics officer. Lobbying prior to registration is prohibited. Thereafter, all lobbyists shall register and re-register annually, as applicable, prior to January 1 of each year or as soon thereafter when known that a person will be engaging in lobbying activities. Each lobbyist is required to submit a separate registration for each principal represented. All lobbyists must update their registrations when they engage a new client prior to initiating any lobbying activities with affected personnel. Registration forms shall be in the manner designated by the city ethics officer and shall require the following information: the name, business address and phone number of the lobbyist, the name, business address and phone number of each principal represented, the general and specific areas of interest, and the manner and extent of any direct business association or partnership with any current member of city council or other affected personnel. Each lobbyist shall sign the registration form, indicating that the lobbyist has read the lobbying provisions of the City of Tampa Ethics Code and will abide by its provisions. The registration form shall be submitted in paper or electronic form pursuant to city policies and procedures to the city ethics officer. A lobbyist shall promptly send written notice to the city ethics officer canceling the registration for a principal upon termination of the lobbyist's representation of that principal. The lobbyist is responsible for ensuring the information contained in the registration is current and up to date.</text>
          <text>Registered lobbyists shall be prohibited from lobbying any member of city council, the mayor, or other affected personnel regarding official city business via text message on that member of city council's, the mayor's, or other affected personnel's private cell phone or other private media, such as private emails. In cases where such communication cannot be avoided, the lobbyist must send a copy of the communication to the member of city council's, the mayor's, or other affected personnel's city email address.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><em>Annual expenditure reporting.</em> A lobbyist shall annually on or before January 31 of each year submit to the city ethics officer's office a signed statement, executed under oath, listing all lobbying expenditures for the preceding calendar year, the source of the funds and an itemization of the amount expended for each city official by each registered lobbyist. It shall be the responsibility of the lobbyist to obtain this form from the city ethics officer's office. Expenditure reporting forms shall be made available in paper or electronic form pursuant to city policies and procedures. The city ethics officer shall maintain such filings available and open for public inspection.</text>
          <text>The city ethics officer shall notify any lobbyist who fails to timely file an expenditure report on or before February 28 of any year. In addition to any other penalties which may be imposed, a fine of fifty dollars ($50.00) per day shall be assessed for reports filed after the due date. The city ethics officer shall notify the ethics commission of the failure of a lobbyist to file a report and/or pay the assessed fines after notification. A lobbyist may appeal a fine and may request a hearing before the ethics commission. A request for a hearing on the fine must be filed with the ethics commission within fifteen (15) calendar days of receipt of the notification of the failure to file the required disclosure form.</text>
          <text>In addition to any other penalty provided for herein, a lobbyist shall not be permitted to engage in any lobbying activity until the required report is filed. Where a fine of fifty dollars ($50.00) per day has already been assessed, the ethics commission shall not impose another fine.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><em>Exceptions.</em> The following persons and activities shall be exempted from the requirement of lobbying registration and annual reporting:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Appointed officers or employees of the City of Tampa discussing matters relevant to their official duties;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Employees or representatives of federal, state, county, municipal or independent authority discussing the business of their government or authority;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>An elected official or government employee acting in his official capacity or in connection with his job responsibilities;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Law enforcement personnel conducting an active investigation;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>Persons or representatives of organizations contacted by city official when such contact is initiated by the city official;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(6)</num>
            <text>A person who appears under compulsion or subpoena by the city council, board or staff member of a board;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(7)</num>
            <text>Any person in contractual privity with the city who appears only in his or her official contractual capacity to discuss issues related to their services under contract.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(8)</num>
            <text>Any person who only appears in his or her individual capacity for the purpose of self-representation without compensation or reimbursement, whether direct, indirect or contingent, to express support of or opposition to any item, shall not be required to file a lobbying disclosure form.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text><em>Record of meetings; meeting logs</em>. Except when appearing at a duly noticed public meeting or hearing on the record, all persons who meet with a member of the city council or the mayor shall sign meeting logs maintained and available in the office of reception of the city council or the mayor. Meeting logs shall be available in designated city departments for meetings with other affected personnel. Meeting logs shall be made available in paper or electronic form pursuant to city policies and procedures. Each person shall provide his or her name, whether the person is attending the meeting as a part of his or her employment or otherwise for compensation, the name of each principal, if any, represented in the course of the particular meeting, and the subject matter of the meeting. Upon submitting the information in the meeting log, the member of city council and his or her aide, the mayor and his or her aide, or the affected personnel, and the city ethics officer will receive concurrent notification. All meeting logs shall be maintained by the city for a period of five (5) fiscal years, and in no event for a period of time less than provided under state law.</text>
          <text>The following shall not be required to sign the meeting logs:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>City of Tampa employees, and employees of other Hillsborough County agencies;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Law enforcement officers;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Relatives, unless such meeting constitutes lobbying as defined in <cite path="2-502">section 2-502</cite>, <cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text><em>Enforcement</em>. The enforcement of expenditure reporting shall be as provided in <cite path="2-580|(b)">section 2-580(b)</cite>. If the city ethics officer is informed of any person who has failed to comply with the requirements of any other provisions of this section, the city ethics officer shall conduct a preliminary investigation as deemed necessary under the circumstances. In the event the city ethics officer determines that a violation may have occurred based on the results of the investigation, the ethics officer shall assess the penalty as provided in <cite path="2-580|(f)">section 2-580(f)</cite>. Any appeal of the assessment shall go to the ethics commission for final resolution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text><em>Violations/penalties</em>. Violations of expenditure reporting shall be punishable as provided in <cite path="2-580|(b)">section 2-580(b)</cite>. The following shall apply to all other violations of this section. A first violation of the provisions of this section shall result in the issuance of a warning by the city ethics officer. A second violation within a period of twelve (12) months shall be punishable by a fine of two hundred fifty dollars ($250.00). If a third violation occurs within twelve (12) months, the violator shall be prohibited from lobbying for six (6) months. If a fourth violation occurs within twelve (12) months, the violator shall be prohibited from lobbying for one (1) year. The city ethics officer shall notify all affected personnel should a lobbyist be suspended under this subsection. If a lobbyist lobbies any affected personnel while under suspension, the city ethics officer shall impose a fine of five hundred dollars ($500.00). The validity of any action or determination of the city council or city employees, board or committee shall not be affected by the failure of any person to comply with the provisions of this section.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 97-153, sec. 1, 7-17-97</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 97-176, sec. 1, 8-28-97</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-110, § 4, 4-29-04</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2016-161, § 3, 11-3-2016</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-581</num>
        <heading>Post-employment restrictions; representation of others before city.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>No elected officer shall personally represent another person or entity for compensation before the city on any matter for a period of two (2) years following vacation of office.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No appointed employee shall personally represent another person or entity for compensation before the city on any matter (except collective bargaining) for a period of two (2) years following termination of employment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>No city employee (other than appointed employees subject to (b) above) shall personally represent another person or entity for compensation before the city for a period of two (2) years following termination of employment in connection with:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any particular matter involving a specific party or parties in which the city is a party or has a direct and substantial interest; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Any matter in which he participated personally and substantially as an employee through decision, approval, disapproval, recommendation, the rendering of advice, investigation or otherwise while employed by the city, except for purposes of collective bargaining.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-139, §<cite path="1-4">§ 1-4</cite>, 6-15-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2006-21, § 5, 1-26-06</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-582</num>
        <heading>Reemployment of elected official.</heading>
        <text>[City Charter sec. 10.06] No former elected official shall hold any compensated appointed city office or employment until one (1) year after the expiration of the term for which he was elected.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-583-2-599</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">6</num>
      <heading>CAMPAIGN ETHICS</heading>
      <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">None [Section 4.23 City of Tampa Related Laws; F.S. § 106.51(3)]</annotation>
      <section>
        <num>2-600</num>
        <heading>Political activity of officers and employees; coercion of votes and moneys prohibited; penalty.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Any person holding a position with the City of Tampa, Florida, in the classified service or in the unclassified service, shall have the same right to take part in political campaigns and to exercise their rights of franchise as any other citizen, subject to the following limitations:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>No officer or employee of the city, except an elected official, shall engage in any political activities during hours of duty, service or work with the city ("hours of duty, service or work" includes the hours for which the employee is paid and is hereinafter referred to as "work hours", but does not include annual leave);</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>No officer or employee shall conduct political activity while wearing a uniform with a visible insignia of the City of Tampa or any other words or lettering identifying the City of Tampa; nor shall any person conduct political activity while using a city vehicle, equipment, or supplies on which there is a visible insignia of the City of Tampa or any other words or lettering identifying the City of Tampa;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>No person, officer or employee shall use a city vehicle, equipment, supplies, or support staff in conducting political activity, unless it is the general practice to permit such use by the public at large ("use" shall mean utilization of the vehicle, equipment, or supplies in a consumptive fashion or for the purpose for which it is intended, or utilization of the services of a city staff member).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(a.1)</num>
          <text>For purposes of <cite path="2-600">this section</cite>, the term "political activities" shall include, but is not limited to the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Request that any individual contribute any time, money or other thing of value to any candidate, political party or committee of continuous existence;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Solicit support/opposition, funds or votes for any candidate, political party or public measure; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Participate in the operation or management of a political campaign;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Conduct any service or activity on behalf of a political campaign.</text>
          </para>
          <text>Nothing in <cite path="2-600">this section</cite> shall prohibit a city officer or employee, during work hours, from discussing, advising, or explaining to any qualified candidate for public office, issues or matters specifically related to the official performance of the employee's or officer's duties.</text>
          <text>Nothing in <cite path="2-600">this section</cite> shall preclude voluntary contributions by a city officer or employee to the party or candidate of his or her choice provided the contribution does not occur during work hours.</text>
          <text>Nothing in <cite path="2-600">this section</cite> shall prohibit a city officer or employee from engaging in authorized union activity during work hours.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>No leave of absence for any time whatsoever shall be granted to any officer or employee of the city for the purpose of engaging in political activities for any candidate, other than the employee's own candidacy for public office. Any violation of this provision shall be deemed to be neglect of duty. Any person holding a position with the City of Tampa, Florida, in the classified service or in the unclassified service, except an elected officer, must take a leave of absence, without pay, beginning when said person completes his qualification as a political candidate in any election for:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>A City of Tampa office;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>A County of Hillsborough office;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>A State of Florida office;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>A federal office.</text>
          </para>
          <text>Such leave of absence shall cease when the individual is no longer a candidate for one of said offices.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>[City Related Laws 4.23; F.S. § 104.31(a)(b)] It shall be unlawful for any officer or employee, or any person connected therewith, to directly or indirectly coerce, or attempt to coerce, command, or advise any other officer or employee of the City of Tampa to vote for or against any person in any election specified in <cite path="2-600|(b)">subsection (b)</cite>, or to collect, receive or attempt to collect or receive, by coercion, or attempted coercion, any moneys whatsoever for any purpose, or to pay, lend, or contribute any part of his salary, or any money, or anything else of value, to any party, committee, organization, agency, or person for political purposes.</text>
          <text>No officer or employee shall use his or her official authority or influence for the purpose of interfering with an election or a nomination of office or coercing or influencing another's vote or affecting the result thereof. No officer or employee shall require, directly or indirectly, any other city officer or employee to participate, in any manner, in an election campaign.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Nothing in <cite path="2-600">this section</cite> shall prohibit a city employee from suggesting to another employee, in a noncoercive manner that he or she may voluntarily contribute to a fund which is administered by a party, committee, organization, agency, person, labor union or other employee organization for political purposes. Nothing contained in <cite path="2-600">this section</cite> shall be deemed to prohibit any officer or employee from expressing his or her opinion on any candidate or issue during non-work hours, so long as the activities otherwise comply with the provisions of <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite>.</text>
          <annotation>(Laws of Fla. 1947, Ch. 24927, sec. 23; Laws of Fla., Ch. 57-1891, sec. 1; Compiled Charter 1958, sec. 132; Laws of Fla., Ch. 70-950, sec. 1; Laws of Fla., Ch. 81-496, sec. 22)</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Jacksonville; F.S. § 106.15(4)]</annotation>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-601</num>
        <heading>Campaign contributions in city owned buildings prohibited.</heading>
        <text>It is unlawful for a person to make or solicit or knowingly accept any campaign contribution in a building owned by the city. For purposes of <cite path="2-601">this section</cite>, "accept" means to receive a contribution by personal hand delivery from a contributor or his agent, and a solicitation shall be deemed to occur where the solicitor of the solicitation is located at the time of the solicitation. <cite path="2-601">This section</cite> shall not apply when a building owned by the city, or any portion thereof, is rented for the specific purpose of holding a campaign fundraiser. Nothing in <cite path="2-601">this section</cite> shall preclude voluntary contributions by a city officer or employee to the party or candidate of his or her choice provided the contribution does not occur in a city-owned building.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-602</num>
        <heading>Political signs; prohibited on public property.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to erect, place or install a political sign or advertisement on public property.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>All signs which do not conform with the provisions of <cite path="2-602">this section</cite> shall be removed by the appropriate department of the city, as designated by the mayor. In addition and notwithstanding any other provisions of <cite path="2-602">this section</cite>, any such political sign or advertisement placed on any roadway in violation of <cite path="2-602">this section</cite> is hereby declared to be abandoned property and is thereby subject to being removed by any person, so long as such removal is accomplished in a safe and peaceful manner. Nothing herein shall be construed to permit any person who removes such abandoned property to do so in a manner that endangers any person, property or the safety of any other person traveling on such roadway.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>In accordance with City of Tampa Sign Code <cite path="27-289.6|(a)|(10)">section 27-289.6(a)(10)</cite>, as amended, all political campaign signs shall be removed within thirty (30) days after the election upon which the political sign is based.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-603-2-619</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">7</num>
      <heading>ADMINISTRATION, TRAINING, PENALTIES AND ENFORCEMENT</heading>
      <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">None [Jacksonville]</annotation>
      <section>
        <num>2-620</num>
        <heading>City ethics officer duties assigned.</heading>
        <text>The duties of the city ethics officer shall be assigned to the appropriate department(s) of the city, as designated by the mayor.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-621</num>
        <heading>Mission and duties of the city ethics officer.</heading>
        <text>The mission of the city ethics officer is to encourage each of the officers and employees of the city to act ethically in all actions. This mission requires that the city ethics officer not only encourage, assist and support compliance with various laws, but more importantly, encourage each employee and officer to adhere to the highest standards of ethical behavior as set forth in aspirational goals of <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite>. In pursuing that broad mission, the duties of the city ethics officer include, but are not limited to the following:</text>
        <text>• Develop policies, programs and strategies to deal with all ethics-related matters;</text>
        <text>• Develop training and education programs in coordination with the city attorney and the ethics commission;</text>
        <text>• Assist in the selection of departmental ethics liaisons;</text>
        <text>• Assist departmental ethics liaisons in training and education;</text>
        <text>• Conduct meetings with any or all of the departmental ethics liaisons as well as management to discuss or provide advice on ethics issues;</text>
        <text>• Obtain copies of all reports and disclosures made pursuant to state law by persons subject to <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> if such reports and disclosures are substantially similar to reports and disclosures required under <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> to eliminate filing similar information under <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite>;</text>
        <text>• Maintain a directory of where all reports and disclosures filed pursuant to <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> may be obtained;</text>
        <text>• Encourage compliance with the spirit and letter of ethics laws;</text>
        <text>• Review periodically <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> and other applicable laws and regulations and recommend to the ethics commission appropriate changes to <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite>;</text>
        <text>• Serve as the liaison between the ethics commission and the officers and employees of the city;</text>
        <text>• Seek formal opinions from the ethics commission on interpretation of his or her duties or of <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite>; and</text>
        <text>• Accomplish other duties as requested by the mayor or city council.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-622</num>
        <heading>Designation of department ethics liaison.</heading>
        <text>The head of each department of the city shall assign an employee the duties of department ethics liaison with the concurrence of the city ethics officer. Appointment of additional personnel will be at the discretion of the mayor. Each department ethics liaison's duties are in addition to his or her principal operational role within the department.</text>
        <text>The head of the department shall communicate the selection of the department's ethics liaison to all employees in the department, while emphasizing his/her personal support for the person and the program. Employees should be encouraged to communicate directly with the city ethics officer on issues or questions that are ethics-related.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-623</num>
        <heading>Responsibilities of the department ethics liaison.</heading>
        <text>Specific responsibilities assigned to the department ethics liaison include, but are not limited to the following:</text>
        <text>• Conduct periodic meetings with department director, senior management, and employee groups to discuss or provide information on ethics issues.</text>
        <text>• Conduct a review of and disseminate within his/her department the appropriate city and department policies and regulations that relate to the code of ethics of employees.</text>
        <text>• Assist the city ethics officer in the formulation of ethics awareness training sessions, conferences, and seminars that are developed for and presented to department employees.</text>
        <text>• Report compliance with the ethics code to the city ethics officer.</text>
        <text>• Make recommendations for improvement in training to the city ethics officer.</text>
        <text>• Accomplish such other duties as are delegated by the city ethics officer, including participating in investigations of complaints as authorized by the city ethics officer.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Jacksonville]</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-624</num>
        <heading>Ethics education and training program.</heading>
        <text>Officers and employees of the city, as public servants, are considered stewards of the public's trust and should aspire to the highest level of integrity and character. Officers and employees shall be informed of their ethical responsibilities at the start of their work with the city and shall receive updates and training materials on ethics issues throughout the span of their public service, as designated by the city ethics officer.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Every officer and employee of the city must be responsible for understanding and complying with the provisions of <cite path="2">this chapter</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Every elected official shall attend an ethics in government program within ninety (90) days of taking office. Upon fulfillment of this requirement, each elected official will be issued a certificate of completion by the ethics commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Every appointed employee shall attend an ethics in government program within the first six (6) months of his/her employment with the city. Upon fulfillment of this requirement, each appointed employee will be issued a certificate of completion by the city ethics officer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Every employee of the city shall complete an employee ethics training program within the first six (6) months of his/her employment with the city. Current employees shall complete training as designated in a schedule developed by the city ethics officer. Upon fulfillment of this requirement, each employee will be issued a certificate of completion by the city ethics officer.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The city ethics officer shall provide ethics education materials to appointed officials, and encourage appointed officials to attend an ethics in government program.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>The ethics in government program and employee ethics training program shall be created and delivered by the city ethics officer with the assistance of the city attorney's office and the ethics commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>The programs shall include topics as determined necessary to explain the provisions of this article, Florida Statutes concerning ethics, and general ethics issues.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-625</num>
        <heading>General penalties.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><em>Elected officers.</em> A determination or finding by the ethics commission of a violation of any provision set forth in <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> by an elected officer constitutes malfeasance, misfeasance, or neglect of duty in office, and may be grounds for suspension or removal from office pursuant to applicable statutory and constitutional procedures.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><em>Appointed officers.</em> A determination or finding by the ethics commission of a violation of any provision set forth in <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> by an appointed officer constitutes malfeasance, misfeasance, or neglect of duty in office, and may be grounds for suspension or removal from office pursuant to applicable statutory and constitutional procedures.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><em>Employees.</em> A determination or finding by the ethics commission of a violation of any provision set forth in <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> by an employee may be grounds for employment sanctions, including but not limited to reprimand, suspension, or discharge pursuant to the policies and procedures under which the employee is governed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text><em>Other persons.</em> A determination or finding by the ethics commission of a violation of any provision set forth in <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> by any person (other than an officer or employee) may be punished as provided herein or in accordance with the provisions of City of Tampa Code <cite path="1-6">section 1-6</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Palm Bch]</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-626</num>
        <heading>Additional penalties.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text><em>Liability for breach of public trust-restitution.</em> [Jacksonville] Article II, Section 8(c) of the Constitution of the State of Florida applies to all officers and employees of the city. Section 8(c) states the following:</text>
          <text>Any public officer or employee who breaches the public trust for private gain and any person or entity inducing such breach shall be liable to the state for all financial benefits obtained by such actions. The manner of recovery and additional damages may be provided by law.</text>
          <text>Any officer or employee of the city who breaches the public trust for private gain and any person or entity inducing such breach shall be liable to the city for all financial benefits obtained by such actions.</text>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Jacksonville]</annotation>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><em>Penalties for bidders or proposers.</em> [Dade County] In addition to any other penalties provided herein, violation of <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> by a particular bidder or proposer may render any contract, request for proposal (RFP) award, request for qualification (RFQ) award or bid award to said bidder or propose voidable. Any person who violates a provision of this ordinance shall be prohibited from serving on a City of Tampa competitive selection committee.</text>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Jacksonville]</annotation>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text><em>Voiding transactions in violation of chapter; recovery by city.</em> The mayor may declare void and rescind any contract, loan, grant, subsidy, license, right, permit, franchise, use, authority, privilege, certificate, ruling, decision, opinion or other benefit that has been awarded, granted, paid, furnished or published, in relation to which there has been a final determination of any violation of <cite path="2">this chapter</cite>. The city shall be entitled to recover, in addition to any penalty prescribed by law or in a contract, the amount expended or the thing being transferred or delivered on its behalf, or the reasonable value thereof.</text>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Palm Bch]</annotation>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text><em>Prohibition against misuse and frivolous claims.</em> Individuals covered by <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> shall not use its provisions to further frivolous claims against another. Frivolous claims shall be those forwarded with knowledge that the claim contains one or more false allegations or with reckless disregard for whether the complaint contains false allegations of fact material to a violation of <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite>.</text>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Jacksonville]</annotation>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>
            <em>Forfeiture of pension rights.</em>
          </text>
          <para>
            <num>F.</num>
            <text>§ 112.3173, applies to all officers and employees of the city and independent agencies. Section 112.3173(3) states the following:</text>
            <text>FORFEITURE.—Any public officer or employee who is convicted of a specified offense committed prior to retirement, or whose office or employment is terminated by reason of his or her admitted commission, aid, or abetment of a specified offense, shall forfeit all rights and benefits under any public retirement system of which he or she is a member, except for the return of his or her accumulated contributions as of the date of termination.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>F.</num>
            <text>§ 112.3173(2)(e) defines specified offense as follows:</text>
            <text>The committing, aiding or abetting of an embezzlement of public funds; the committing, aiding or abetting of any theft by a public officer or employee from his or her employer; bribery in connection with the employment of a public officer or employee; any felony specified in Ch. 838, except section 838.15 and section 838.16; the committing of an impeachable offense; or the committing of any felony by a public officer or employee who, willfully and with intent to defraud the public or the public agency for which the public officer or employee acts or in which he or she is employed of the right to receive the faithful performance of his or her duty as a public officer or employee, realizes or obtains a profit, gain, or advance for himself or herself or for some other person through the use or attempted use of the power, rights, privileges, duties, or position of his or her public office or employment position.</text>
            <text>Said forfeiture shall be determined as specified in section 112.3173(5).</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-627-2-649</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">8</num>
      <heading>ETHICS COMMISSION</heading>
      <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">None [<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>]</annotation>
      <section>
        <num>2-650</num>
        <heading>City of Tampa Ethics Commission; created; purpose.</heading>
        <text>There is hereby created and established the City of Tampa Ethics Commission to administer the <cite path="2-500">code of ethics for city officials</cite> and employees.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, sec. 2(2-646), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Dade County]</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-651</num>
        <heading>Composition and appointment.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>The ethics commission shall be composed of five (5) members. The members of the ethics commission shall be appointed as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>The President of the Hillsborough County Bar Association shall be requested to appoint one (1) former federal judge, or former United States Magistrate or former State court judge;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>The President of the Hillsborough County Bar Association shall be requested to appoint one (1) former U.S. Attorney or Assistant U.S. Attorney, former State Attorney or Assistant State Attorney, former County Attorney or Assistant County Attorney or former City Attorney or Assistant City Attorney;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>The Dean of the Stetson University School of Law shall be requested to appoint one (1) full time or adjunct faculty member from his or her law school who is knowledgeable in legal ethics.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>The President of the University of South Florida or University of Tampa shall be requested to appoint one (1) full time or adjunct faculty member who is knowledgeable in ethics; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(5)</num>
            <text>The mayor shall be requested to appoint one (1) member who has held elective office at the local level prior to appointment.</text>
          </para>
          <text>In the event that a person empowered to appoint a member(s) is unable to identify a person who meets the qualifications for appointment, the appointing individual shall notify the mayor in writing including the reasons for the inability to appoint, in which case the mayor shall appoint a member to the ethics commission who substantially meets the qualifications hereof. Said appointment shall be subject to confirmation by city council.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text><em>Additional qualifications.</em> Each member of the ethics commission shall be a United States citizen, resident of the City of Tampa and shall be of outstanding reputation for integrity, responsibility and commitment to serving the community. The members of the ethics commission should be representative of the community-at-large and should reflect the racial, gender and ethnic make-up of the community. Prior to final selection of each member of the ethics commission, those persons empowered herein to appoint members shall meet and evaluate the qualifications of each person(s) under consideration to ensure that (a) that said person(s) is qualified to serve on the ethics commission and (b) that the membership of the ethics commission will be representative of the community-at-large and reflect the racial, gender and ethnic make-up of the community. Before entering upon the duties of office, each appointee on the ethics commission shall take the prescribed oath of office.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-110, § 5, 4-29-04</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-61, § 2, 4-20-2017</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-652</num>
        <heading>Term.</heading>
        <text>The members of the ethics commission shall serve staggered terms of four (4) years each, provided that of the original members, two (2) members shall be appointed for a term of two (2) years and three (3) shall be appointed for a term of four (4) years, and each member shall continue to serve until their successor has been appointed.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-653</num>
        <heading>Vacancies.</heading>
        <text>A vacancy occurring during or at the expiration of a member's term on the ethics commission shall be filled as provided in <cite path="2-651">section 2-651</cite>, subsections (a) and (b).</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2017-61, § 3, 4-20-2017</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-654</num>
        <heading>Additional requirements.</heading>
        <text>No individual, while a member of the ethics commission shall:</text>
        <text>• Hold or campaign for any elective political office;</text>
        <text>• Hold office in any political party or political committee;</text>
        <text>• Actively participate in or contribute to any political campaign for city office;</text>
        <text>• Be employed by the City of Tampa; or</text>
        <text>• Allow his or her name to be used by a campaign in support of or against any candidate for city office or any city referendum or other city ballot question.</text>
        <text>Nothing herein shall preclude a member of the ethics commission from signing a petition in support of or against any referendum or other ballot question.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>]</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-655</num>
        <heading>Organization; rules and regulations; swearing witnesses; keeping minutes.</heading>
        <text>The members of the ethics commission shall elect a chairman annually. The board may promulgate written rules and regulations to govern its proceedings and all hearings held before it. The board may conduct investigations upon complaints or information received by it and may swear witnesses. The board shall keep accurate and complete minutes of its business.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, sec. 2(2-651), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>]</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-656</num>
        <heading>Compensation.</heading>
        <text>Members of the ethics commission shall not be entitled to compensation; however, all members shall receive reimbursement for parking in city garages and for mileage for any board-related business except travel to and from regularly scheduled and specially called board meetings. Such reimbursement shall be consistent with city policy.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, sec. 2(2-652), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Dade County]</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-657</num>
        <heading>Powers, duties and jurisdiction of ethics commission.</heading>
        <text>The ethics commission shall be empowered to review, interpret, render advisory opinions and letters of instruction and enforce this ethics code. Jurisdiction of the ethics commission shall automatically extend to elected officers, appointed officers, and employees and lobbyists, as defined herein, who are required to comply with <cite path="2-500">this code</cite> of ethics ordinance.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>]</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-658</num>
        <heading>Procedure on complaints of violations.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upon the filing with the city ethics officer of a written sworn complaint of any person alleging facts which, if true, would constitute improper conduct under the provisions of this article, the city ethics officer shall present the complaint to the ethics commission. Within five (5) days after receipt of a complaint by the ethics officer, a copy shall be transmitted to the alleged violator. The ethics commission shall investigate any alleged violation of this article in accordance with procedures set forth in <cite path="2-658">this section</cite>.</text>
          <text>In no event shall a complaint under <cite path="2-658">this section</cite> against a candidate in any city election be filed or the filing of or intention of filing such a complaint be disclosed on the day of any such election or within the five (5) days immediately preceding the date of the election.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A preliminary investigation shall first be undertaken by the ethics commission to determine if the facts alleged in the complaint constitute probable cause to believe that a violation has occurred.</text>
          <text>If, upon completion of the preliminary investigation, the ethics commission finds no probable cause to believe that this article has been violated, the ethics commission shall dismiss the complaint; and the complaint shall then become a matter of public record, together with a written statement of the findings of the preliminary investigation and a summary of the facts, all of which the ethics commission shall transmit to the complainant and the alleged violator.</text>
          <text>If the ethics commission finds from the preliminary investigation probable cause to believe that this article has been violated, it shall so notify the complainant and the alleged violator in writing. Such notification and all documents made or received in the disposition of the complaint shall then become public records. Upon request submitted to the ethics commission in writing, any person who the ethics commission finds probable cause to believe has violated any provision of this article shall be entitled to a public hearing. Such person shall be deemed to have waived the right to a public hearing if a request therefor is not received by the ethics commission within thirty (30) days following the receipt of the probable cause notification required by <cite path="2-658">this section</cite>; however, the ethics commission may on its own motion require a public hearing and may conduct such further investigation as it deems necessary.</text>
          <text>The complainant and alleged violator shall be given notice in writing of the date and time set for such public hearing at least ten (10) days before the public hearing is held. The hearing shall be conducted in accordance with all requirements of due process of law and in accordance with any written rules and regulations that have been promulgated by the ethics commission. Any person filing such a sworn complaint and any alleged violator may appear before the ethics commission in person or by counsel and shall be entitled to question witnesses and present evidence in accordance with any rules that have been adopted by the ethics commission.</text>
          <text>Within ten (10) days after the public hearing, unless the commission determines additional time is needed, the ethics commission shall make and promulgate written findings of fact and conclusions based thereon, including a determination as to the propriety of the conduct of the alleged violator, all of which shall be transmitted to the complainant, the alleged violator and, in the event that it is found and determined that a violation has occurred, to the official, the city council or other appropriate body for appropriate action.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Any person who willfully discloses or permits to be disclosed his intention to file a complaint, the existence or contents of a complaint which has been filed with the ethics commission, or any document, action or proceeding in connection with a confidential preliminary investigation of the ethics commission before the same becomes a public record shall, any provision of this article to the contrary notwithstanding, be guilty of an offense against the city, punishable as provided in <cite path="1-6">section 1-6</cite> of <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>In any case in which the ethics commission finds probable cause to believe a violation of criminal law has been committed by an alleged violator or where the ethics commission finds probable cause to believe that a complainant has committed perjury in regard to any document filed with or any testimony given before the ethics commission, it shall refer such evidence to the appropriate law enforcement agency for prosecution.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, sec. 2(2-668), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2005-109, § 1, 4-28-05</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[<cite>City of Tampa Code</cite>]</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-659</num>
        <heading>Recommended</heading>
        <text>If the ethics commission, pursuant to the provisions hereof, shall make a determination that the conduct of any official or employee is or was a violation of this ethics code, the ethics commission shall make a recommendation to the official, city council, or other appropriate body or person to institute appropriate action for correction or rectification of that conduct or for the censure, suspension or removal from office of the official or employee, and may recommend appropriate action to void any transaction with a public body or any determination made by a public body.</text>
        <text>The official, city council, or other public body or person taking such action may base any action it takes upon the written findings of fact, conclusions and determination of the ethics commission and shall institute such action they deem appropriate within sixty (60) days of the promulgation of the ethics commission's findings, conclusions, and determination.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 89-222, sec. 2(2-669), 9-28-89</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Jacksonville]</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-660</num>
        <heading>Advisory opinions.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Every elected officer, appointed officer, candidate for city office, or city employee, when in doubt about the applicability and interpretation of any city ethics law to himself or herself in a particular context, may submit in writing the facts of the situation to the ethics commission with a request for an advisory opinion to establish the standard of public duty. Any officer or employee who has the power to hire or terminate employees may likewise seek an advisory opinion from the ethics commission as to the application of the provisions of the ethics laws to any such employee or applicant for employment. An advisory opinion shall be rendered by the ethics commission, and each such opinion shall be numbered, dated and published.</text>
          <text>Such opinion, until amended or revoked, shall be binding on the conduct of the officer, employee, or candidate who sought the opinion or with references to whom the opinion was sought, unless material facts were omitted or misstated in the request for the advisory opinion.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The ethics commission is authorized to call upon appropriate agencies of city government for such professional assistance as may be needed in the discharge of its duties. The city attorney's office shall provide legal assistance to the ethics commission; provided however, in the event the city attorney determines that he or any attorney in his office has a conflict of interest which prevents the city attorney's office from providing impartial representation to the ethics commission, the city shall engage outside legal counsel to provide the necessary legal assistance to the ethics commission.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>The ethics commission shall assist in the preparation of materials and programs designed to assist persons in complying with the ethics laws. The ethics commission shall work with the city ethics officer in establishing, presenting, and expanding the city's ethics education program.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Jacksonville]</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-661</num>
        <heading>Additional duties of the ethics commission; reporting.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>It shall be the further duty of the ethics commission to submit to the city council periodically a report of its work and recommendations for legislation deemed necessary to improve the ethics laws and their enforcement which shall be dutifully considered by the city council.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>The city ethics officer shall be responsible for documenting compliance with the financial disclosure, gift disclosure, lobbying registration and reporting, and ethics education and certification requirements of <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite> for all officers and appointed employees.</text>
          <text>The ethics commission shall receive annual reports from the city ethics officer regarding the compliance or non-compliance with financial reporting, gift reporting, lobbying registration and reporting, and ethics education and certification requirements of <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite>. The annual report shall also be filed with the mayor and city council.</text>
          <text>At the close of the reporting period, the city ethics officer shall notify any individual who has failed to timely comply with financial disclosure, gift disclosure, lobbying registration and reporting, or ethics education and certification requirements of <cite path="2-500">this Code</cite>. After expiration of any additional time to comply with said reporting requirement, the city ethics officer may request the ethics commission to institute action.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>It shall be the further duty of the ethics commission to review and make recommendations to the mayor relative to the removal from office those appointed officers or officials who disclosed a conflict of interest, pursuant to <cite path="2-519|(c)">section 2-519(c)</cite>, in ten (10) percent or more of the applications filed with the public board to which that officer or official is appointed. For purposes of this sub-section, the ten (10) percent threshold shall be based on the number of applications filed on an annual basis. Factors for consideration by the ethics commission in determining whether to recommend removal from office include but are not limited to the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Whether the conflicts of interest necessarily interfered with the full and faithful discharge of the appointed officer's public duties;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Whether the conflicts of interest jeopardized the appointed officer's independence and impartiality;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>Whether the conflicts of interest caused the appointed officer unable to perform his public duties efficiently and faithfully; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(4)</num>
            <text>Whether the conflicts of interest caused the appearance of public office being used for private gain.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-225, § 5, 9-30-04</annotation>
          <annotation type="Cross References" dest="container">[Jacksonville]</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-662</num>
        <heading>Investigatory powers.</heading>
        <text>The ethics commission may, on its own initiative, seek information and gather facts for the purpose of investigating any circumstance or situation of which the ethics commission may become aware that appears to violate or may potentially violate an acceptable standard of conduct for city officers and employees. If, as a result of such investigation, the ethics commission determines the need for remedial or preventative legislation, the ethics commission may make such recommendations to the city council as it deems appropriate.</text>
        <text>The services of other departments, boards and agencies of the city may be made available to the ethics commission at its request, subject to their ability and capacity to provide them. All city agencies shall cooperate with the ethics commission in the exercise of the ethics commission's responsibilities.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-663</num>
        <heading>Appeals.</heading>
        <text>Appeals from any decision of the ethics commission, with the exception of recommendations made pursuant to <cite path="2-661|(c)">section 2-661(c)</cite> herein, shall be to circuit court as provided by law.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2003-255, §§ 2, 3, 10-2-03</annotation>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2004-225, § 6, 9-30-04</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-664-2-674</num>
        <heading>Reserved.</heading>
      </section>
    </container>
    <container>
      <prefix>DIVISION</prefix>
      <num path-omit="true">9</num>
      <heading>WHISTLEBLOWER PROCEDURES</heading>
      <section>
        <num>2-675</num>
        <heading>Purpose and meaning.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>These provisions are designed to protect and promote the health, safety and welfare of persons within the city and to provide uniform requirements for the receipt, review and approval of information disclosed by whistleblowers and other citizens against employees, contractors, appointed officials or elected officials. These provisions are further intended to provide for the regulation and enforcement of this division.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>This division does not replace the state "Whistle-blower's Act" (see F.S. § 112.3187). Persons who wish to disclose information may utilize the procedures outlined in that Act in addition to, or in lieu of, the procedures in this division. The ethics officer shall be designated as the "appropriate local official" for the purposes of state law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>All words or terms used in this division, unless otherwise noted, shall have the same meaning as such words and terms have under the state Whistle-blower's Act, F.S. § 112.3187.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2016-155, § 2, 10-20-2016</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-676</num>
        <heading>Nature of and procedures for disclosed information.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Information disclosed under this division must allege that the city, its departments, its agencies, its employees, its appointed or elected officials, or its contractors are involved in:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Any violation or suspected violation of any federal, state or local law, rule or regulation which creates and presents a substantial and specific danger to the public's health, safety or welfare; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Any act or suspected act of gross mismanagement, malfeasance, misfeasance, gross waste of public funds, or gross neglect of duty, pursuant to F.S. § 112.3188.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>If a person knows or has a good-faith belief that he or she possesses information that meets the criteria in <cite path="2-676|(a)">section 2-676(a)</cite>, that person may contact the ethics officer to confidentially disclose the information and request whistleblower status. To render the person eligible for whistleblower status, the disclosure must be made in a signed, written complaint to the ethics officer.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2016-155, § 2, 10-20-2016</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-677</num>
        <heading>Procedures for investigating disclosed information.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Upon receiving a signed, written complaint from a person disclosing information under this division, the ethics officer shall conduct an investigation into the information and recommend any actions that the city can take to remedy the alleged violations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>During the investigation, the ethics officer may contact or forward the complaint to any appropriate agency, provided that the name and identity of the complainant are kept confidential.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(c)</num>
          <text>Prior to the completion of any such investigation, the ethics officer shall submit his or her report to the city attorney for review for legal sufficiency.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(d)</num>
          <text>Upon completion and approval of the report, the ethics officer shall present the report to the ethics commission for a hearing to determine:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(1)</num>
            <text>Whether probable cause exists for a violation of <cite path="2-676|(a)">section 2-676(a)</cite>;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(2)</num>
            <text>Whether the ethics officer's recommendations are sufficient to prevent additional offenses; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(3)</num>
            <text>If the complainant has requested whistleblower status, whether the complainant is a whistleblower (pursuant to the factors in F.S. § 112.3189).</text>
          </para>
          <text>This hearing and all subsequent proceedings shall be conducted in accordance with the procedures defined in <cite path="2-658">section 2-658</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(e)</num>
          <text>The complainant's identity must remain confidential throughout the proceedings; confidentiality may only be removed if the complainant waives it or the ethics commission finds that he or she is ineligible for whistleblower status.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(f)</num>
          <text>If a public hearing is scheduled under <cite path="2-658|(b)">section 2-658(b)</cite>, the complainant shall be allowed to confidentially appoint an attorney or other representative to attend in his or her place. The complainant may also waive his or her confidentiality and attend in person.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(g)</num>
          <text>Following the investigation, the ethics commission must provide written findings and determinations for a whistleblower complaint in accordance with state law. This subsection applies regardless of whether a public hearing occurs in the course of the investigation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(h)</num>
          <text>If the ethics commission determines that the complainant should be designated as a whistleblower, the report and findings shall be forwarded to the complainant for any comments. The report and findings are then public record, but the identity of the complainant shall continue to remain confidential.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(i)</num>
          <text>The ethics commission may still grant a complainant whistleblower status if it finds no probable cause for a violation, so long as the commission finds that the complainant evidenced a good-faith belief in the occurrence of the alleged violation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(j)</num>
          <text>No complainant may be designated as a whistleblower if the ethics commission finds that he or she knowingly took part in any alleged offense, or if he or she was in a city or county correctional facility at the time the complaint was filed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(k)</num>
          <text>If the ethics commission determines that the complainant should not be designated as a whistleblower, the report and findings shall be returned to the complainant with a statement as to why the complainant was not so designated, and with an explanation that the complainant cannot rely on the whistleblower protections in this division.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2016-155, § 2, 10-20-2016</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-678</num>
        <heading>Retaliation protections.</heading>
        <text>The city shall not dismiss, discipline, or take any other adverse personnel action that affects the rights or interests of any designated whistleblower in retaliation for:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Disclosing any information under the rules of this division;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Being asked, or compelled, to participate in an investigation as defined in <cite path="2-677">section 2-677</cite>; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Refusing to participate in another adverse personnel action as defined in <cite path="2-678">this section</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2016-155, § 2, 10-20-2016</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-679</num>
        <heading>Procedures for retaliation complaints and appeals.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>If a designated whistleblower (see <cite path="2-677">section 2-677</cite>) has a good-faith belief that his or her disclosure has resulted in retaliation under <cite path="2-678">section 2-678</cite>, the whistleblower may file a signed, written complaint with the ethics officer within sixty (60) days of the alleged action.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>A designated whistleblower may file an appeal of any adverse disciplinary action that he or she in good-faith believes resulted from retaliation under <cite path="2-679">section 2-679</cite>, pursuant to the disciplinary appeals methods available in the city's personnel policies.</text>
        </para>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2016-155, § 2, 10-20-2016</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-680</num>
        <heading>Existing rights.</heading>
        <text>This division shall not be construed to diminish the rights, privileges or remedies of any employee under any other law or rule or under any collective bargaining agreement or employment contract; however, the election of remedies provided by F.S. § 447.401, shall also apply to complaints under this division.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2016-155, § 2, 10-20-2016</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
      <section>
        <num>2-681</num>
        <heading>Rules and procedures.</heading>
        <text>The ethics officer is authorized to promulgate such rules and procedures and written forms necessary to effectuate the intent of this division.</text>
        <annotations>
          <annotation type="History">Ord. No. 2016-155, § 2, 10-20-2016</annotation>
        </annotations>
      </section>
    </container>
  </container>
</container>
